two
one boom all right we're live thank you
very much for doing this man i really
appreciate it i've been absorbing your
information and listening to you talk
for uh quite a while now so it's uh it's
great to actually meet you thanks for
having me my pleasure my pleasure you
are one of the rare guys
that is uh you're a big investor
you are um you're deep in the tech world
but yet you seem to have a very balanced
perspective in terms of how to live life
as opposed to not just be
entirely focused on
success and financial success
and
tech investing but rather
how to live your life in a happy way
that's a it's a it's not balance
yeah you know i think the reason why
people like uh hearing me is because
like if it's like if you go to a circus
and you see a bear right that's kind of
interesting but not that much if you see
a unicycle that's interesting but you
see a bear on a unicycle that's really
interesting right
so when you combine things you're not
supposed to combine right people get
interested it's like bruce lee right
striking thoughts philosophy plus
martial arts
and i think it's because at some level
all humans are broad we're all
multivariate but we get summarized in
pithy ways in our lives and at some deep
level we know that's not true right
every human basically is capable of
every experience and every thought uh
you know you're ufc comedian commentator
podcaster but you're also more than that
you're also father
uh lover you know thinker etc
so i like the model of life that the
ancients had the greeks the romans right
where you would start out and when
you're young you're just like going to
school then you're going to war then
you're running a business then you're
supposed to serve in the senate or the
government then you become a philosopher
there's sort of this arc to life
where you try your hand at everything
and as one of my friends says
specialization is for insects right
so everyone should just be able to do
everything and so i don't believe in
this model anymore of trying to focus
your life down on one thing you've got
one life just do everything you're going
to do
i couldn't agree more and i i think that
sometimes people find certain success in
whatever the endeavor is and then they
think that that is their niche and they
stick with it and they never change and
they almost out of fear
well it's hard because there's a you
know the analogy around mountain
climbing like if you find a mountain and
you start climbing you spend your whole
life climbing it and you get say two
thirds of the way and then you see the
peak is like way up there but you're two
thirds of the way up you're still really
high up but now to go the rest of the
way you're going to have to go back down
to the bottom and look for another path
nobody wants to do that people don't
want to start over yeah and it's the
nature of later in life that you just
don't know the time
so it's very painful to go back down and
look for a new path but that may be the
best thing to do and that's why when you
look at the greatest artists uh and and
creators they have this ability to start
over that nobody else does like elon
will you know be called an idiot and
start over doing something brand new
that he supposedly is not qualified for
or when madonna or paul simon or you two
come out with a new album their existing
fans usually hate it because they've
adopted a completely new style that
they've learned somewhere else and a lot
of times they'll just miss completely so
you have to be willing to be a fool
and kind of have that beginner's mind
and go back to the beginning to start
over if you're not doing that you're
just getting older yeah i mean i don't
even know if it's willing to be a fool
it's just to me that the most exciting
thing is to try to get better at
something to learn
things i mean it's really exciting when
you just have incremental progress and
something that you're completely new to
yeah i live for the aha moment that
moment when you connect two things
together that you hadn't connected
together before and it fits nicely and
solidly and it kind of helps form a
steel framework of understanding in your
mind that you can then hang other ideas
off of that's what i live for yeah it's
like curiosity fulfilled and it's what
little children do too you know my
little son is always asking why why why
why why and i always try and answer him
and half the times i realize actually i
don't really understand why i just have
a memorized answer for you but that's
not really understanding
yeah those are weird conversations right
when you're you're talking to your kids
and you say look uh the reality is i
don't know a lot of things yes i've just
memorized a lot of things
and there's certain things that you just
can't know yeah you realize that you
know you have
you have answers for a few things that
you've thought through then you sort of
have cover-ups like like trap doors like
don't go here this is just a cover-up i
don't really know the answer to what the
meaning of life is or how we got here
yes and then you've got a whole bunch of
memorized stuff because a lot of your uh
a lot of intelligence these days just
the external brain pack of civilization
i know it's out there i know the answers
are out there know how to look them up
and i've memorized some of them and i i
kind of understand how money works and
the federal reserve prints it and what
this government thing is but not really
right
so not good enough to teach it in
university yeah yeah
uh
i think people do that with almost
everything in life these days in terms
of like have a like a one page a one
cheat like a brief summary of what and
the explanation for what this very
complex subject might be tldr right
don't give me the don't give me the
lecture give me the book don't give me
the book give me the blog post don't
give me the blog post give me the tweet
don't give me the tweet i just i already
know yeah i got really fascinated by the
way you read because i thought there was
something wrong with me by doing that
but you you don't really just read a
book to completion you read and then you
pick something else up and you just kind
of go based on your whims whatever
you're interested in well i was raised
by my i was raised by a single mom in
new york and she used the local library
as a daycare center because it was a
very tough neighborhood and so she would
basically say when you get back from
school go straight to the library and
don't come out
until i pick you up late at night so i
used to basically live in the library
and i read everything i read every
magazine i read every pictograph or
every book or every map i just ran out
of stuff to read i just read everything
so i got over this idea of
that reading a large number of books or
reading a book to completion as a vanity
metric because really
when people are putting up photos on
twitter instagram of look at my pile of
books that i'm reading it's a show-off
thing it's a signaling thing yeah sure
and the reality is i would rather read
the best hundred books over and over
again until i absorb them rather than
read all the books right yeah because
your your brain has finite information
in a finite space
you get enough advice it all cancels to
zero
there's a lot of nonsense in books out
there too so
i don't read anymore to complete books i
read to satisfy my genuine intellectual
curiosity
and it can be anything it could be
nonsense it could be history could be
fiction it could be science it could be
sci-fi these days it's mostly sci-fi
philosophy science because that's just
what i'm interested in
but i will read for understanding so a
really good book i will flip through i
won't actually read it consecutively in
order and i won't even just even finish
it i'm looking for ideas things that i
don't understand and when i find
something really interesting i'll
reflect on it i'll research it
and then when i'm bored of it i'll drop
it or i'll flip to another book
thanks to electronic books i've got 50
70 books open at any time in my kindle
or ibooks and i'm just bouncing around
between them
it's also a little bit of a defense
mechanism to how in modern society we
get too much information too quickly and
so our attention spans are very low so
you get twitter you get instagram you
get facebook you're just used to being
bombarded with information so you can
take that to you you can view that as a
negative and be like i have no attention
span or you could view that as a
positive i multitask really well and i
can dig really fast i can if i find a
thread that's interesting i can follow
it through five social networks through
the web through the libraries through
the books and i can really get to the
bottom of this thing very quickly it's
like the library of alexandria that i
can research at my disposal so i i no
longer track books read or even care
about books read it's about
understanding concepts yeah you brought
up two awesome points first of all the
the social media aspect of of books and
basically anything it's like
it's such a weird way to display your
life because it's you know you're
displaying the best aspects of your life
and some sort of a glass
case
you know just it's an unrealistic
version of your life that you cultivate
and you curate
and i'm i'm as guilty of that as anybody
everybody's guilty of it i'm guilty of
it too yeah you know i mean i pose with
my dog every time i run
yeah we're always signaling yeah it's
like rather than really looking at
yourself you're looking at how other
people look at you so it's like this one
remove mental image and it's kind of a
disease because social media is making
celebrities of all of us and celebrities
the most miserable people in the world
right because they're this strong
self-image that gets built up it gets
built up by compliments every time
somebody pays you or me a compliment and
we're like oh well thank you right then
that builds up an image of who we are
and then one idiot comes along one out
of ten one out of a hundred and they can
easily tear it down because it doesn't
take many insults to cancel out a lot of
compliments and now you're carrying
around this big weighty self-image and
it's just very easy to be attacked and
because you're you're famous or you're
well known people want to attack you so
being a celebrity is no good it's
actually a problem
like one of my tweets is and these are
all reminders to myself is you want to
be rich and anonymous not poor and
famous
there's benefits to it of course of
course but we wouldn't do it it has
unusual
problems that you don't get trained for
and you really will not understand
unless you experience it you know i was
having this conversation with my wife we
were talking about um people that just
come up to you and they don't care what
you're doing they don't care if i'm with
my daughter if i'm holding her if i'm
feeding her for you know we're in the
middle of an intense conversation she's
crying she could be crying and some bro
will come over and just immediately have
to take a picture doesn't care his needs
supersede the daughter
and my wife was saying i that before she
knew me she used to think that that's
just part of the price of being famous
that people people like you that's just
part of the price being famous and now
when it interrupts her life and you know
it interrupts the children and it
interrupts friends and you know she now
she's like this is annoying like this is
not this is not healthy this is not a
smart way to to interact with people and
that people have this weird challenge
this weird thing that if you're if you
become famous there's this weird
challenge where people just want to come
to you especially today because if they
can get a photo of you then that boosts
their social media profile
like hey i'm sitting here with the vault
look at that smile
anonymity is a privilege on the other
hand it's self-inflicted i mean we
brought it on ourselves yeah we don't
think we knew what it was though we did
but we carry on so yeah
it tells us we are getting something out
of it so i you know there are times when
someone will approach me in public and
i'm a little resentful and there are
other times i'm just like actually i'm
really grateful that you know i worked
for this i got this right this is the
payoff just embrace it smile grit and
bear it but you have a different sort of
celebrity too right you're you're a hero
amongst investors
and amongst i mean you've just i'm a
hero
among young male geeks
which is those are some of my favorite
people right but that's not the kind of
celebrity i think most people set out to
get especially most guys right right
right you want the cute females yeah
yeah i look at my brief little youtube
clips i have a tiny little podcast going
now and it's like 95 mail oh sure yeah
this is very highly 18 to 35. yeah we
what do we what is the numbers
yeah it's in the 90s yeah um you you did
that one you do that one very small
podcast where you just have small like
three or four minute clips
yeah so what it was i i did a tweet
storm uh called how to get rich without
getting lucky and it got pretty popular
in twitter and it's really about wealth
creation i just use the clickbaity title
and it's trying to basically lay out
timeless principles of wealth creation
that if you absorb them you become the
kind of person who can create wealth
create business make money
and my theory behind that is like
there are three things everybody wants
there's actually more than three but
let's just start with three the three
basics everybody wants to be wealthy
everybody wants to be happy and
everybody wants to be fit
and i know there's a lot of virtue
signal that goes on like we don't want
to money and you know i don't care about
being happy and happiness is for stupid
people but let's face it like you want
to be rich and happy and healthy that's
the trifecta now of course you also want
an internally calm state of mind you
want a loving household so there are
other things that come into it but those
three i think
they can actually be taught right and
the fitness i'm not going to teach there
are a lot of people who you've had on
here including yourself who know a heck
of a lot more about fitness and health
than i do
but
i was born poor and miserable and uh i'm
now pretty well off and i'm very happy
and i don't and i worked at those and so
i've learned a few things there are some
principles and so i try to lay them out
but in a timeless manner where you can
kind of figure it out yourself because
at the end of the day i can't really
teach anything i can only inspire you
and maybe give you a few hooks so you
can remember things when they happen or
put a name to them so this podcast
actually ended up explaining this tweet
storm so there's a tweet storm with like
36 38 tweets got very famous got
translated to dozens of languages
and these were principles that i came up
with for myself when i was really young
around 13 14
and i've been carrying them in my head
for 30 years and i've been sort of
living them and over time i just
realized like sadly or fortunately the
thing that i got really good at was
looking at businesses and figuring out
the point of maximum leverage to
actually create wealth and capture some
of that
and do it in a very long-term kind of
way not let the you know banker
crash the economy get filled out kind of
way but you know build businesses and
help people and provide value kind of
way
especially when applied to modern
technology and leverage in this age of
infinite leverage that we live in
so the podcast is just explaining each
tweet so these are little three four
five minute snippets
i don't like to say the same thing twice
i don't like to explain in detail
i just i i feel like if you have
something original and interesting to
say you should say it otherwise it's
probably been said better so that
podcast tries to be information dense it
tries to be very concise it tries to be
high impact it tries to be timeless
and it has all the information i think
you need the principles that if you
absorb these and you work hard over 10
years you get what you want
so i've got the one on wealth creation
i'm going to attempt to do one on
happiness is a big word but you know
happiness and inner peace and calm and
all that because what you want is you
don't want to be the guy who succeeds in
life while being high strung high stress
and unhappy and leading the trail of
emotional wreckage with you and your
loved ones which is more common than not
yeah because you got to focus and it's
very hard to be great at everything you
want to be the guy or the gal who gets
there calmly
you know quietly
without struggle
uh you want to be the person who's the
when there's a crisis going on you want
to be the calmest coolest cucumber in
the room who still also figures out the
correct answer um if you can be you were
one of the things that you were saying
is that you feel like happiness is
something that you can learn and then
you can teach yourself to be happy even
just by adopting the mindset that you
are a happy person and proclaiming that
to your friends and so you've sort of
developed a social contract i'm a happy
person and i have to live up to that
yeah i've got hundreds of techniques but
then how did you develop that one
well
there's just a there's social
consistency right humans have a need to
be highly consistent with their past
pronouncements so the way i started my
first tech company was i was in working
inside a larger organization and i told
everybody that i was going to go start a
company i was like i hate this place i'm
going to do my own thing i'm going to be
successful entrepreneur six months past
nine months pass then people start
you're still here i thought you were
going to go start a company
are you lying right that was the
implication so we kind of know this
right social contracts are very powerful
like if you want to give up drinking
right and you're not serious about it
you'll say i'm going to cut back i'm
going to have only one drink a night i'm
going to only drink on weekends you tell
yourself but if you're serious you'll
announce it on facebook you'll tell all
your friends you'll tell your wife
you'll say i'm done drinking i'm
throwing everything out of the house
you'll never see me drink again when you
say that you know you're serious
so i think a lot of these are choices
that we make and happiness is just one
of those choices
and this is unpopular to say because
there are people who are actually
depressed you know chemically or what
have you and there are people who don't
believe that it's possible because then
it creates a responsibility on them it
says oh now if i'm you're saying if i'm
not happy that's my fault
i'm not saying that but i'm saying that
just like fitness can be a choice health
can be a choice nutrition can be a
choice working hard and making money can
be a choice happiness is also a choice
if you're so smart how come you aren't
happy how come you haven't figured that
out that's my challenge to all the
people who think they're so smart and so
capable if you're so smart and capable
why can't you change this
there are a bunch of people though that
actually take pleasure in being
miserable
there's something about the
pursuit of excellence
and of success that supersedes all other
pursuits
that in in their eyes it is
it is that the peak
the pinnacle the most important thing
it's not a trade-off
i would argue that if now when i say
happy happy is one of those words that
means a zillion different things right
it's like love right what does that mean
right i love cheese yeah i'm going to
define it a little bit more tightly
right
so
let's go back to desire right this is
old old buddhist wisdom i'm not saying
anything original but
desire to me is a contract that you make
with yourself to be unhappy until you
get what you want
okay and i keep that in front of mine so
when i'm unhappy about something i look
for what is the underlying desire that i
have that's not being fulfilled it's
okay to have desires you're a biological
creature you're put on this earth you
have to do something you have to have
desires you have a mission but don't
have too many don't pick them up
unconsciously don't pick them up
randomly don't have thousands of them my
coffee is too cold doesn't taste quite
right i'm not sitting perfectly oh i
wish it was warmer uh you know my dog
you know pooped in the lawn i didn't
like that whatever it is pick your one
overwhelming desire it's okay to suffer
over that one but on all the others you
want to let them go so you can be calm
and peaceful and relaxed and then you'll
perform a better job
most people when you're unhappy like a
depressed person
it's not that they have very clear calm
mind they're too busy in their mind
their sense of self is too strong
they're sitting indoors all the time
their minds working working working
they're thinking too much well if you
want to be a high performance athlete
how good of an athlete are you going to
be if you're always having epileptic
seizures if you're always like twitching
and running around and like jumping and
your your limbs are flailing out of
control the same way if you want to be
effective in business you need a clear
calm cool collected mind warren buffett
plays bridge all day long and goes for
walks in the sun he doesn't sit around
like constantly loading his brain with
non-stop information and and getting
worked up about every little thing
we live in an age of infinite leverage
what i mean by that is that your actions
can be multiplied a thousand fold either
by broadcasting at a podcast or by
investing capital or by having people
work for you or by writing code so
because of that the impacts of good
decision making are much higher than
they used to be because now you can
influence thousands or millions of
people through your decisions or your
code
so
a clear mind leads to better judgment
leads to a better outcome so a happy
calm peaceful person will make better
decisions and have better outcomes so if
you want to operate at peak performance
you have to learn how to tame your mind
just like you have to learn how to tame
your body
i love what you're saying warren buffett
might not be the best example because he
drinks like i think six coca-colas a day
and he eats mostly mcdonald's and he's
still alive somehow so that shows you
that low stress is more nobody looks
like [ __ ] like how old is he
i mean he's he's a fairly old man
charlie mungers i think in his 90s right
yeah he's made it really far i wonder
what warren's doing you know i mean just
he's got to know that's bad for him but
it's terrible he doesn't care he doesn't
care i think he's just a little stressed
yeah stresses right so he just enjoys
that coca-cola and that's probably
maybe there is a trade-off right like
maybe him enjoying that junk food and
that coke just ah
that that pleasing of the mind is maybe
better than him just eating
wheatgrass shots and yeah and
salads and just being yeah just super
worked up about everything it's like if
you need your glass of red wine to
de-stress and calm down that's probably
better than you flying off the rails
right right and i think that that's
applicable not just in business but in
probably any pursuit and i like what
you're saying about allow that one thing
to be your obsession
but everything else just you know learn
how to learn how to let things go pick
your battles
and
we like to think that we we like to view
the world as linear which is
i'm going to put in eight hours of work
i'm going to get back eight hours of
output right it doesn't work that way
guy running the corner grocery store is
working just as hard or harder than you
and me how much output is he getting
what you do who you do with how you do
it way more important than how hard you
work right outputs are
non-linear based on the quality of the
work that you put in the right way to
work is like a lion you don't you and i
are not like cows we're not meant to
graze all day right we're meant to hunt
like lions we're closer to carnivores in
our omnivorous development than we are
to herbivores um we don't tell vegans
that yeah sorry
look i wish all that stuff worked i
don't want to eat meat this future
generation will look back at us as worse
than slavers you know because the
holocaust we're committing with the
animals but they'll have artificial
meats that taste and are healthier is uh
better than the real thing so allegedly
allegedly but so as a modern
knowledge worker athlete as an
intellectual athlete you want to
function like an athlete which means you
train hard then you sprint
then you rest then you reassess you get
your feedback loop then you train some
more
then you sprint again then you rest then
you reassess this idea that you're going
to have linear output just by cranking
every day at the same amount of time
same that's
that's machines you know machines should
be working nine to five humans are not
meant work nine of are not meant to work
nine to five no i agree wholeheartedly
but that's it
for people that are
working for someone there's not really
that option
so that's unfortunately the the rub
right that's kind of where my tweet
storm starts which is
first of all the first thing if you're
going to make money is that you're not
going to get rich renting at your time
even lawyers and doctors who are
charging three four 500 an hour they're
not getting rich because their lifestyle
is slowly ramping up along with their
income and they're not saving enough uh
they just don't have that ability to
retire
so the first thing you have to do is you
have to own a piece of a business you
need to have equity either as an owner
an investor shareholder
or a brand that you're building that
accrues to you to gain your financial
freedom
yeah and
i was really fascinated by another thing
that you were bringing up about
working for yourself that you feel in
the future whether it's 50 or 100 years
from now virtually everyone is going to
be working for themselves and i believe
the way you put it is that
the information age is going to reverse
the industrial age yeah if you go back
to hunter-gatherer times how we evolved
we basically work for ourselves we
communicated and cooperated within
tribes but each hunter each gatherer
stood on their own and then combined
their resources with the family unit but
there was no boss hierarchy hierarchy
hierarchy or you're like the third
middle manager down
in the farming age we became a little
bit more hierarchical as we had to run
farms but even those were still mostly
family farms it's industrial work with
factories that sort of created this
model of thousands of people working
together on one thing and having bosses
and schedules and times to show up the
reality is if you have to go i don't
care how rich you are i don't care
whether you're like a top wall street
banker if you have to go if somebody has
to tell you if somebody can tell you
when to be at work and what to wear
and how to behave you're not a free
person you're not actually rich so we're
in this model now where we think it's
all about employment and jobs and
intrinsic in that is that i have to work
for somebody else
but the information age is breaking that
down so ronald kos is an economist who
has this coase theorem a very famous
theorem but it basically just talks
about
why is a company the size that it is why
is a company one person instead of 10
people instead of 100 instead of a
thousand and it has to do with the
internal transaction costs versus the
external transaction costs
let's say i want to do something let's
say i'm building a house and i need
someone to come in and provide the
lumber i'm a developer right do i want
that to be part of my company or do i
want that to be an external provider a
lot of it just depends on how hard it is
to do that transaction with someone
externally versus internally if it's too
hard to keep doing the contract every
time externally i'll bring that in-house
if it's easy to do externally and it's a
one-off kind of thing i'd rather keep it
out of the house
well information technology is making it
easier and easier to do these
transactions externally it's becoming
much easier to communicate with people
gig economy i can send you small amounts
of money i can hire you through an app i
can rate you afterwards so we're seeing
an atomization of the firm we're seeing
the optimal size of the firm shrinking
it's most obvious in silicon valley tons
and tons of startups constantly coming
up and shaving off little pieces of
businesses from large companies and
turning them into huge markets so what
looked like the small little vacation
rental market on craigslist is now
suddenly blown up into airbnb
one example
that's a great example but what i think
we're going to see
is
whether it's 10 20 50 100 years from now
high quality work will be available
we're not talking about driving an uber
we're talking about super high quality
work will be available in a gig fashion
where you'll wake up in the morning your
phone will buzz and you'll have five
different jobs from people who have
worked with you in the past or have been
referred to it's kind of like how
hollywood already works a little bit
with how they're organized for a project
you decide whether to take the project
or not the contract is right there on
the spot you get paid a certain amount
you get rated every day or every week
you get the money delivered and then
when you're done working you turn it off
and you go to tahiti or wherever you
want to spend the next three months and
i think the smart people have already
started figuring out that the internet
enables this and they're starting to
work more and more remotely on their own
schedule on their own time on their own
place with their own friends in their
own way and that's actually how we are
the most productive
so the information revolution by making
it easier to communicate connect and
cooperate is allowing us to go back to
working for ourselves and that is my
ultimate dream even when i run a company
and i have employees i always tell those
people hey i'm going to help you start
your company when you're ready because i
think that's the highest calling maybe
not everybody will get there but
it would be fine if we were even working
a ten person company or twenty person
company is way better than working in a
thousand person company a ten thousand
person company so this idea that we're
all factory like cogs in a machine who
are specialized and have to do things by
rote memorization or instruction it's
going to go away and we're going to go
back to being small groups of creative
bands of individuals setting out to do
missions and when those missions are
done we collect our money we get rated
and then we rest
and reassess until we're ready for the
next sprint has there ever been a study
done on happiness and as it regards the
size of companies
not that i'm aware but to me it's
obvious it's just obvious the smaller
the company the happier you're going to
be the more human your relations are the
less you have rules to operate under the
more flexible the more creative
the more you betray like a human just
because you're able to do multiple
things yeah
um this brings me to
what
is a subject that keeps getting brought
up nowadays is universal basic income
with the oncoming
apocalypse of automation this is how
it's being portrayed by andrew yang
who's running for president i sat down
and talked to him about is very
compelling
and he's a very smart guy and he's an
entrepreneur himself and when he starts
talking about automation and how it's
going to just eliminate massive amounts
of jobs and leave people stranded what
do you when i know you're a guy who
thinks about the future and i'm going to
take this popular point of view on this
i don't i think it's a non-solution to a
non-problem
[Music]
and i mean that in the sense that
automation has been happening since the
dawn of time
electricity came along that put a lot of
people out of work did it right a lot of
people carrying buckets of water and you
know lighting lamps and all those kinds
of things and this was the concern with
factories as well apps everything
literally every single thing that comes
even the printing pros absolutely and
what it does is it frees people up for
new creative work so the question is not
is automation going to eliminate jobs
there is no finite number of jobs we're
not like sitting around dividing up the
same jobs that we're around since the
stone age so obviously new jobs are
being created and they're usually better
jobs more creative jobs so the question
is how quickly is this transition going
to happen and what kinds of jobs will be
eliminated and what kinds of jobs will
be created it's impossible looking
forward to predict what kinds of jobs
will be created if i told you 10 years
ago that podcaster was going to be a job
or that you know playing video games is
going to be a job or commentating on
video games is going to be a job you
would have laughed me out of the room
those are nonsense jobs but yet here we
are so society will always create new
jobs civilization creates new jobs but
it's impossible to predict what those
jobs are so the question is how quickly
is that transition happening
well the reality is even though
everybody keeps talking about this
automation apocalypse we're at a record
low unemployment
explain that where's the transition
donald trump that's hard
all i'm saying is it's it's
i don't see it in the numbers i don't
see it actually happening the question
is how quickly can you retrain people so
it's an education problem the problem
with ubi there's a couple of problems
with ubi one is you're creating a
straight
you're creating a slippery slide
transfer
straight into socialism right the moment
people can start voting themselves money
combined with a democracy right it's
just a matter of time before the bottom
51 votes themselves everything in the
top 49. yeah and
it just it and by the way slippery slope
fallacy is not a fallacy and i know
people like saying that but they haven't
thought it through um but
the moment you start having a direct
transfer mechanism like that in a
democracy you're basically doing it with
capitalism which is the engine of
economic growth you're also forcing the
entrepreneurs out or telling them not to
come here
the estimate i saw for 15k a year
basic income for everybody would be
three quarters of current gdp and of
course gdp would shrink in response as
all the entrepreneurs fled so you would
essentially bankrupt the country
another issue at ubi is that people who
are
down in their luck they're not looking
for handouts it's not just about money
it's also about status it's about
meaning and the moment i start giving
money to you and put you on the dole
i've lowered your status i've made you a
second class citizen so i have to give
you meaning and meaning comes through
education and capability i have you have
to teach a man to fish not to basically
throw your rotting leftover carcasses at
him and say here eat the scraps so it
doesn't solve the meaning problem and
lastly it's nonsense to hand 15k out to
everybody you want to means test people
there's no reason to give it to you and
me so you end up back towards the
welfare system where you do have to
figure out who needs it and who doesn't
so i think the better route is that we
actually establish a set of basic
substance services that you have to have
and we provide those in abundance to
technology-based automation so get basic
housing get basic food get basic
transportation get high-speed internet
access get a phone in your pocket those
are the kinds of things you want to give
people
and finally in terms of the rate of
automation i think we can educate people
very quickly one of the myths that we
have today is that adults can't be
re-educated we view education as this
thing where you go to school you come
out when you're out of college and
you're done no more education well
that's wrong you have all these great
online boot camps and coding schools
coming up they're ones that will even
pay you to go there now
you can educate people and mass and you
can educate them into creative
professions people who are talking about
ai automating programming have never
really written serious code
coding is thinking it's automatic
structure thinking an ai that can
program
as well or better than humans is an ai
that just took over the world that's end
game that's the end of the human species
and i can give you arguments why i don't
think that's coming either
people who are thinking and i know i
take the opposite side from some very
famous people in this debate but we're
nowhere near close to general ai not in
our lifetimes you don't have to worry
about it even in our lifetimes
really it's so overblown uh it's it's
another
it's a combination of cassandra complex
you know it's fun to talk about the end
of the world
combined with a god complex like people
who have lost religion so they're
looking for meaning in some kind of end
of history right right um the reason why
i don't think ai is coming anytime soon
is because a lot of the advances in
so-called ai today are what we call
narrow ai they're really pattern
recognition machine learning to figure
out like what is that object on the
screen or how do you find this signal
and all that noise there's nothing
approaching what we call creative
thinking
to actually model general intelligence
you run into all kinds of problems first
we don't know how the brain works at all
number two we've never even modeled a
paramecium or an amiibo let alone a
human brain number three there's this
assumption that all of the computation
is going at the cellular level at the
neuron level whereas nature is very
parsimonious it uses everything at its
disposal there's a lot of machinery
inside the cell that is doing
calculations that is intelligent that
isn't accounted for and the best
estimates are would take 50 years of
moore's law before we can simulate
what's going on inside a cell near
perfectly and probably 100 years before
we can build a brain that can stimulate
inside the cells so putting it at saying
that i'm just going to model neuron is
on or off and then use that to build a
human brain is overly simplistic
furthermore i would posit there's no
such thing as general intelligence every
intelligence is contextual within the
context of the environment that it's in
so you have to evolve an environment
around it so i think a lot of people who
are peddling general ai the burden of
proof is on them i haven't seen anything
that would lead me to indicate we're
approaching general ai instead we're
solving deterministic closed set finite
problems using large amounts of data but
it's not sexy to talk about that if you
you're talking about mirroring the
actual abilities of cells or are you
talking about recreating the actual
mechanism like what what what is going
on inside
cells and and biological organisms yeah
we just don't know how intelligence
works right we don't know we literally
have no idea so most of the
ai approaches basically say we're going
to try and model
how the brain works but the model at the
neuron level which is saying this
neurons on that neurons often combining
their signal but i'm saying in the
neuron is a cell inside the cell there's
all this machinery going on that's
operating the neuron that is also part
of the intelligence apparatus you can't
just ignore that and abstract that out
you have to model it down to the in
inside the cell level it's also a part
of the biological organism itself
exactly and it has all these needs that
you know the biological organism has to
have food and rest and exactly there's a
balance going on but when you eliminate
all that when there is none of that and
it's just calculations
and we get to a point where it's just
this thing that we've created whether
you call it a computer whether it
doesn't have to be a moving thing even
but a thing that you've created that
stores virtually all the information
that's available in the world stores all
the patterns of all the thinking of all
the great people that have ever lived
all the the writers all the people that
have ever published anything all the
people that have ever spoken any words
stores all of their points all their
counterpoints all their contradictions
applies logic
and reason
and
some sort of sense of the future
and starts improving upon these patterns
and then starts acting on its own based
on the information that it's been
provided with
well first you would have to actually
simulate a structure the human brain
that can hold all that information
you're basically talking about tens of
thousands of brains worth of information
right we can't even build one brain the
next decade or two or three well in
terms of an actual physical brain yes
but what about something that recreates
the abilities of a brain
like i said nature is parsimonious so
we've got this three pound wet wear
object that can hold all this data
nature has been very efficient in
evolving kind of how we get there
i i just don't think computers are
anywhere close to that like they can
hold that amount of data with that
complexity with like the holographic
structure of the brain where it can
recall in many many different ways
and then
i don't think you can evolve a creature
to be intelligent outside of the
boundaries of feedback in a real medium
like if you evolved if you raised a
human being a concrete cell with no
input from the outside they wouldn't
have any feedback from the real world
they wouldn't evolve properly so i think
just dumping information
into into a thing isn't enough it has to
have an environment to operate in to get
feedback from it needs to have context
but isn't that biological i mean what if
you if you have just the all the
information that people have accumulated
and the lessons that people have learned
and you program that into the computer
like if if we can take a computer that
can beat someone at chess the the real
question was well can we make some sort
of an artificial intelligence could beat
someone at go which is far more complex
of chess they figured out how to do that
too and that was a giant shock
right these are still
man-made very closed bounded games
they're they're not they're not on the
road to the unbounded game of life
they are completely artificial but this
didn't go
didn't that give you like a little bit
of a pause a little bit go is not go or
league of legends or fortnite they're
not completely deterministic right
but they're still very artificial very
bounded games being good at go doesn't
mean that you can then suddenly figure
out how to write great poetry right the
creativity for sure is something that's
creativity is the last frontier so i do
believe that automation over a long
enough period of time will replace every
non-creative job or every non-creative
work but that's great news
that means that all of our basic needs
are taken care of and what remains for
us is to be creative which is really
what every human wants
yeah what are you doing right now this
is a creative job sure
um that that brings us back to the idea
of meaning and universal basic income uh
i think the idea of giving someone
15 000 a year
doesn't necessarily
cause whatever what everyone would worry
about is people being on the dole you
would have a bunch of listless people
out there with no meaning in life but
the idea is that fifteen thousand
dollars a year and i'm not necessarily
sure i agree with this i'm not even
endorsing this but that fifteen thousand
dollars a year would just provide you
with the necessities to get by in life
it would give you food it would give you
shelter well it's not gonna stop at 15
because the moment people are like i
mean like 15 like then people would
demand more bernie sanders would be on
this 16 7 45 thousand dollars yeah these
companies are too big yeah that could it
doesn't it doesn't stop it's just it
just goes all the way to bankruptcy the
concern is the slide to socialism
it's obvious yeah i mean heck if i was
on if i was not working and i was
getting my 15 a year i would happily
vote for the guy who would give me 20 or
25 it's just common sense what do you
say to the people that don't believe
that there is such a thing of ethical as
ethical or compassionate capitalism and
there's many people today that are
espousing marxism and they're espousing
some sort of a socialist society where
they believe that capitalism has screwed
people over and
eliminated
the middle class and there are absolute
problems with capitalism i think
monopolies are a problem
i think that uh crony capitalism is a
problem with the government you know
kind of gets in bed with them and sort
of forces things uh i think the bankers
have really you know raped society and
the rest of us are suffering for it yeah
they've essentially taken huge risks
where they privatize the gains and they
socialize the losses so when it fails
they basically get billed out and
bankrupt everybody else
so capitalism has gotten a really bad
name let's talk about its free exchange
free markets
free markets and free exchange are
intrinsic to humans from when the first
person started a fire and somebody came
along with a deer and said hey if i cook
my deer on your fire i'll share some of
it with you right so specialization
labor we trade that's built into the
human species basic math comes from
accounting keeping track of debts and
credits and so on we need to be able to
engage in free trade
the correct criticism of capitalism is
when it does not provide equal
opportunity and so we should always
strive to provide equal opportunity
but people confuse that with equal
outcome when you have equal outcome that
can only be enforced through violence
because different people free people
make different choices and when they
make different choices they have
different outcomes if you don't let them
suffer the consequences of bad choices
or reap the rewards from good choices
then you are forcibly redistributing
through violence it's interesting that
there isn't there are no
socialist working socialist examples
that exist without violence you
basically need someone to show up with a
gun and say okay you're not allowed to
do that you hand this over to that
person so one of the reasons why this
podcast is because i believe everybody
can be wealthy everybody it's not a
zero-sum game it is a positive sum game
you create something brand new you
exchange it with me for something brand
new i've created this higher utility for
both of us the sum of the value created
is positive it's not like status where
it's like you're higher up i'm lowered
down your president so must be vice
president you're a plus one i'm a minus
one and has to cancel a zero
we should all be all for playing
positive
some ethical games the problem is
because of these looters who have ruined
capitalism's name that then you get
socialists coming in and saying burn the
whole system down right you burn the
whole system down we end up like
venezuela or the former soviet union you
know you don't want to be a failed
socialist states with emaciated teens
hunting cats in the streets to eat right
that's literally what happens in some of
these places
so i think it's very important not to
destroy the engine of progress that
brought us here yeah the idea that
socialism just hasn't worked yet
that it needs to the we just need to do
it right if we do it right we can if you
ever 100 million dead and yeah yeah well
let's keep trying all over the world
yeah and and every single time it's been
implemented
have you ever had a conversation with
someone who's a socialist who where many
times some of my better friends are
socialists really we really get into it
yeah and what is there i mean does
anyone have a compelling
perspective at all
i i think
really socialism comes from the heart
right you all we all want to be
socialist
capitalism comes from the head because
they're always cheaters in any system
yes and there's incentives in any system
so
when you're young if you're if you're
not a socialist you have no heart when
you're older if you're not a capitalist
you have no head right you haven't
thought it through so i understand where
it comes from i always liked nassim
taleb's framing on this where he said
with my family i'm a communist with my
close friends i'm a socialist uh you
know at my state level politics i'm a
democrat at you know higher levels i'm a
republican and at the federal level i'm
a libertarian right so basically the
larger the group of people you have
massed together who have different
interests the less trust there is the
more cheating there is the better the
incentives have to be aligned the better
the system has to work the more you go
towards capitalism the smaller the group
you're in you're in a kibbutz you're in
your commune you're in your house you're
in your tribe by all means be a
socialist with my aunts with my brother
with my cousins with my uncles with my
mom with your family i'm a socialist
that's the right way to live a loving
happy
integrated life yes but when you're
dealing with strangers i mean you want
to be a real socialist great open all
your doors and windows tomorrow please
everybody come take what you want see
how that works out yeah
this idea of income inequality that
always strikes me as a very
it's a deceptive term
income inequality well let's flip it
around it comes from outcome
inequality yeah and the outcome
inequality is there because you made
different choices now again going back
if it was because you didn't have the
same opportunities that's a problem yes
so society should always try to give
people equal opportunities so for
example instead of basic income what if
we had a retraining program built into
our basic social fabric which said that
every four years or every six years or
whatever it is maybe it's every 10 you
can take one year out
and we'll pay for you to go retrain
completely and you can go into any
profession you like that has some
earning power and output
hopefully a creative long-term
profession and you can re-educate
yourself
that would be much better for society on
all levels than basically just saying
now you're going to be the dole for the
rest of your life
yeah you just you'd have to
lead that horse to water and then make
them drink it requires people to put in
some effort yeah you know we can't all
just sit around it's just not well
that's my my perspective on income
inequality there's always effort in
equality
and and thought inequality there's just
some people that are obsessed and if
those people become successful it
doesn't mean they stole from you it just
means that they put in the amount of
energy and effort that it's required to
reach where they're at and there's a lot
of virtue signaling that goes on now
where people say well it's because
you're privileged
well you know you know what the greatest
privilege is you're alive 85 of humanity
is dead yeah so how privileged are you
then you're living in the first world
and you're you know you have four limbs
etc so you can take that argument all
the way it's kind of a nonsense
discussion what's a very weird
progressive argument and it as it
pertains to uh race is always a weird
one right because white privilege to me
it although
it you could look at what they're saying
on paper like yes yeah i'm sure
there's more black people that are
harassed by the police i'm sure there's
more black people who are treated
suspiciously by shop owners and the like
but the problem isn't the people who
aren't treated poorly the problem is the
people who treat the people poorly the
problem is racism the problem is not
people that didn't ask to be born white
or whatever they are and they don't get
harassed
so this idea of white privilege or male
privilege or whatever it is that's not
the problem you're just looking at
someone who's not a victim of this
particular problem that you're
highlighting but you're not looking at
the perpetrators of the problem you're
making people perpetrators by simply
existing and having less melanin in
their skin or having their ancestors
come from actually
it's a sneaky way of being racist yeah
and then they say you can't be racist
it's not racist because you're white
that's right that is this hilarious if
you can't be racist against white people
that one that's what there's a variation
of the whole still while i hit you
argument you know stop struggling while
i'm hitting you but it's just so silly
you've just completely changed what
racism means but what's hilarious is
mostly the people who are yelling
racists are not the minorities when i
look on my twitter my social media or on
my news it's white on white violence
virtue signaling yeah it's white on
white violence yeah what's mostly going
on is its elitist whites blue state
whites college educated whites beating
up on high school educated whites blue
collar it's a white collar versus
blue-collar war that's going on and the
rest of us are just kind of watching
like oh that's kind of interesting well
it's also a side effect of the ability
to broadcast right like everyone with a
twitter handle has the ability to
broadcast everyone with a facebook page
has the ability to pontificate and have
these long rambling
these huge statements that people put
out when you you read them it's like how
much time did you put in this what the f
do you put that much time in your kids
or your job or your job or your life or
your future or planning for your you
know how much do you work out a day i
mean are you just these some i read some
people's facebook posts i'm like this is
a preposterous amount of effort that you
put into saying virtually nothing let's
see humans are being creative yeah and
ai do that well that's true it is
creative it's it's creative in a very
odd way right because it's creative and
that they're trying to elicit a response
from people and they're trying to raise
their their social value or raise their
their position on the social totem pole
it's signaling and it's easy signaling
because the kind of thing that everybody
has to agree with you on because nobody
wants to be seen as a horrible person
yeah and it's very hard to make the
nuanced arguments against than it is to
just kind of go along right well it's
also it's some of it is so
cliche that it seems like
i i know one guy who poses as a woman on
on twitter but he does it just obviously
yeah uh what is this the name tatiana
mcgregor
yes yeah yeah
used to be godfrey elwick yes oh is that
the same guy i think so yeah that's
hilarious
i did not they killed his account they
killed his account for 100 sure for
pretending to be transracial that's
right they did yeah
he basically says all the crazy stuff
that people in the left say but he says
the craziest version yes and kind of
just shows how it's okay like
i saw a tweet from recently just said or
her that it's not okay to be white yes
and then some people agree but it's it's
so close to what they say it's so close
that it's like the most artful form of
subtle parody because it's well if you
if you replace in half of these things
if you replace the word white with black
or asian
lynch
yeah yeah it's
it's a strange time in that respect that
there's a favor saying that if you want
to see who rules over you
see who you're not allowed to criticize
excellent yeah that is a that's so true
right yeah that's so true i wonder where
this is going i really do i wonder
because this is it seems like this
newfound ability to broadcast that we
have with
whether you have a youtube page or
whether you have twitter or whatever
you're doing this newfound ability to
spread whatever you're trying to say to
so many people with very little
understanding on the most part from
i think it's actually a great thing
overall yeah now it means that any human
can broadcast any other human on the
planet at any time so for example if you
know a totalitarian dictator were to
come to power and someone was beating up
you know had fascists beating up on old
women like that would get broadcast out
instantly there would be an instant
outrage hue and cry rallying so in that
sense it helps bring attention to the
plight of anybody
but
right now we're going through the phase
where we have this newfound power to
assemble mobs
and people don't know how to deal with
that so it becomes very easy to set up a
mob and have it attack somebody take all
the context out like even this
conversation i'm sure people will take
out snippets put them on social media
and try and get somebody outraged of
course and so you have to learn how
first of all society just has to get
over this idea of outrage like to me
like
outraged people are just people who get
easily outraged are the stupidest people
on social media those are the people i
block instantly uh it's just kind of
very low level thinking right these are
the foots of the these are the foot
soldiers and the mob
eventually society just has to get over
it they have to understand that these
are all snippets being taken out of
context these are doctored video clips
these are just someone who's trying to
get outraged over something
eventually there'll also be anti-mob
tactics like for example
if if i go to someone's twitter feed and
all it is is full of polit political
ranting raving conspiracy theories do i
want to work with this person do i want
to associate with this person do you
want to be friends with this person
their mind is just cluttered with junk
now i don't necessarily blame them i
think that the human brain is not
designed to
absorb all of the world's breaking news
24 7 emergencies injected straight into
your skull with clickbait headline news
if you pay attention to that stuff even
if you're well-meaning even if your
sound of mind and body it will
eventually drive you insane this goes
back to clockwork orange where he's you
know has his eyes opened up he's forced
to watch the news but i think that's
what's happening right now because these
are addictive right
twitter facebook instagram these are
weaponized you have social statisticians
and scientists and researchers and
people in lab coats literally best minds
of our generation figuring out how to
addict you to the news yes and if you
fall for it if you get addicted your
brain will get destroyed and i think
this is the modern struggle right the
modern struggle so the ancient struggle
used to be the tribal struggle you had
your tribe of friends and family you had
your religion you had your country you
had your loyalty you had your
nationality at least you had meaning and
support but now you would struggle
against other tribes
modern life we're so free everything's
become atomized we stand alone you live
in your apartment alone you live in your
house alone your parents don't live
nearby your friends don't live nearby
you don't have any tribal meaning you
don't believe in religion anymore you
don't believe in country anymore it's
fine you got a lot of freedom it's
fantastic but now when they come to
attack you
you're alone and you can't resist so how
do they attack you it's all well-meaning
i don't fault capitalism i love
capitalism but
look at how it happens social media
they've
massaged all the mechanisms to addict
you like a skinner's pigeon or a rat
who's just gonna click click click click
click can't put the phone down the food
they've taken sugar and they've
weaponized it they've put it into all
these different forms and varieties that
you can't resist eating drugs right
they've taken pharmaceuticals and plants
and they've
synthesized them they've grown them in
such a way that you can't you get
addicted you can't put them down porn
right if you're a young male you wander
on the internet it'll like sap away your
libido and you're not going out in real
life society anymore because you've got
this incredibly stimulating stuff coming
at you video games another way to addict
people so you have this you have entire
large factories of people that are
working to addict you to these things
and you stand alone so the modern
struggle as an individual is learning
how to resist these things in the first
place drawing your own boundaries and
there's no one there to help you
that's terrifying
i mean it is a new road that needs to be
navigated by young people that are
there's no map there's no guidebook on
how to handle this our generation is the
transition generation i think our kids
will know how to handle it better
because they'll grow but i hope i hope i
hope too because you're seeing some
ridiculous behavior from people today
that's so common i mean i don't know if
you've been paying attention to this but
there was a guy who
he made a video it turns out it wasn't
even him that made the video at least
that's not what he said but it was a
video where he sort of doctored nancy
pelosi talking and made it look like she
was drunk
and then a bunch of people retweeted it
like oh my god look she's drunk and and
so one of the online publications uh
some website
tracked him down
and doxed him and turned out he's just a
day laborer who is an african-american
trump fan
and thought it would be funny to do that
and it turns out that he didn't even at
least according to him he actually just
put it up on his facebook page what's
even more disturbing is facebook
gave up his information to this website
right
for what
because he made something funny that
made people seem drunk there's a million
of those about me i mean you could find
them i mean i think facebook and twitter
and a bunch of these other social media
platforms are committing slow-motion
suicide through these kinds of
activities
that was a stunning one though that they
would give up this guy who's a laborer
because he made a parody video or he
made someone look foolish with editing
well you now have basically the media
views it as their job to go after
individuals they don't like yeah i use
media with air quotes in that regard so
i don't think this is something that the
new york times would have done
anything responsible but the media is
getting more and more desperate right
because what happened was before the
internet you could have two local
newspapers in every town and you could
have two local
news stations you know tv stations in
every town
and then cnn came along and started
commoditizing the news 24 7 broadcast
and then the internet came along that
was the final nail in the coffin because
what the internet did was it said
actually if there's a fact
that's news you can distribute that
immediately it can go on twitter it can
go on facebook it gets reprinted on
google news a thousand times you know
you're going google news you're like
okay what's the piece of news which
source and three thousand other articles
too many right yeah so news has become
commoditized so the entire news media
has shifted into peddling opinions and
entertainment yes and so now they've
become
a variation between like cheerleaders
shock troops enforcers
you know talking heads so these are now
tribal these are not propaganda machines
signaling for their tribes it's a
right-wing one this left-wing one right
there's the alt-right there's a control
left and the two of them are just
fighting it out using their various
media organs and memes so
basically when you see one of these news
organizations doxing an individual
that's like a tank running over a
soldier
right that's what's going on it's just
war and so there's no there's no such
thing anymore as a neutral media
commentator
the the illusion of objectivity that
journalism had is lost there's no longer
one guy like a walter cronkite that
everyone's going to listen to it's now
all just shock troops fighting wars with
each other
how does this play out
have you thought about it yeah a little
bit uh so what the internet does a lot
of this is internet driven what the
internet does is the internet creates
one giant aggregator or two for
everything one taxi dispatcher one
e-commerce store one search engine one
uh you know
one social media site for friends and
family one for business etc so the
internet is this giant aggregator where
it creates one big hegemon for
everything
and it creates an atomized long tail of
millions and millions of individuals
what it gets rid of is the medium
medium-sized ones in the middle so for
example you might have had like seven
hollywood studios what's all going to be
netflix you had uh you know like
10 large e-commerce players so commerce
players from walmart to
costco to you know kmart and whatever
now it's just going to be amazon and a
ton of small individual brands so that's
the world that we're headed towards one
hegemon and millions of individuals so
where it ends up long term is media will
be a few gigantic outlets you know it
could be the new york times it could be
facebook a few like that and there's
going to be just a really long tale of
millions of independent people so this
idea of who's a journalist and who's not
you know is assange journalist or not
everyone's a journalist that's the world
that we're headed towards i do think the
extreme power the most powerful people
in the world today
and this is not well known but the most
powerful people in the world today are
the people who are writing the
algorithms for twitter and facebook and
instagram because they're controlling
the spread of information they're
literally rewriting people's brains
they're programming the culture and
they're doing it very subtly like google
i believe that you know one of their
execs got up in front of congress and
the congressman asked him uh you know do
you manipulate search results and he
said no we do not manipulate search
results really
that's your job that is literally all
google does google has one job which is
to manipulate search results to pull
them out of the noise and rank them
properly and the out the precise
algorithms of how they do that is very
hidden very complex but influences the
hearts and minds of everybody including
all the voters now if google facebook
and twitter had been smart about this
they would not have picked sides they
would have said we're publishers
whatever goes through our pipes goes
through our pipes if it's illegal we'll
take it down give us a court order
otherwise we don't touch it it's like
the phone company if i call you up and i
say something horrible to you on the
phone the phone company doesn't get in
trouble but the moment this started
taking stuff down that wasn't illegal
because somebody screamed they basically
lost their right to be viewed as a
carrier and now all of a sudden they've
taken on liability so they're sliding
down the slippery slope into ruin
sloping to ruin where the left wants
them to take down the right the right
wants him to take down the left and now
they have no more friends they have no
allies traditionally the
libertarian-leaning republicans and
democrats would have stood up in
principle for the common carriers but
now they won't so my guess is as soon as
congress this is this day is coming if
not already here it might even been here
today actually because this saw
something related
in the news the day is coming when the
politicians realize
that these social media
platforms are picking the next president
the next congressman they're literally
picking and they have the power to pick
so they will be controlled by the
government
in in what way how do you think they're
going to be controlled you think they're
going to have to adhere to strict
principles of freedom of speech no first
particularly unfortunately it's headed
the opposite direction right absolutely
i wish it was freedom of speech much
more likely they're going to be
in the short to medium term they're
going to be hauled in for hearings uh
they're going to be pressured massively
do this don't do that
my concern about that is the the
hearings that i saw with zuckerberg
those people were completely incompetent
they don't seem to understand
they don't but they're just applying
pressure they're just trying to scare
him so he'll do what they want and what
do they want him to do they want him to
basically suppress the other side so if
you're right wing you want to suppress
the left wing if you're left-wing you
want to suppress the right wing and if
you just see where these companies are
headquartered in silicon valley
all the sensors and that's really what
they are there are sensors working
inside these companies they're just
called they're called by different names
obviously right it's double speak you
call it the department defense when it's
the department of war so in this case
the department of safety and trust when
it releases the department of censorship
the sensors are inside silicon valley so
it's going to reflect silicon valley's
politics which is extremely progressive
left ring yeah and if you're not that
you really have no place there's i mean
right try being a conservative an open
conservative at google good luck now you
get lynched yes
that's crazy i mean i don't
think that there was ever
a thing like that
that was so influential and so
politically ideologically one-sided
yeah there's a there's a little saying
on the internet i think it's called
conquest law that any organization
that's not explicitly right-wing
eventually becomes left-wing
and i don't know why that's true but it
does seem to me to be true well it's a
fascinating battle that's going on right
now i mean it really is and
conservatives in as far as social media
is concerned they're just getting
chopped off at the hams left and right
yeah what'll eventually happen is that
whenever you suppress speech
the organism metastasizes then it has to
start turning towards other means if
you're unlucky goes towards violence
if you're lucky they find other outlets
i think what will happen is we will
start creating decentralized media
that's not owned by any single entity
that can't be suppressed or shut down
that will then start spreading these
various things and that will take the
place of twitter or facebook that's
right but it's going to take 10 years 20
years it's not overnight well you know
twitter took 10 years to get to the
point where it's at this mess right now
but it was so interesting to to have
jack dorsey and to to talk to him about
where it's going where he thinks it's
going in his own principles which he
believes that it's a fundamental right
and he believes that freedom of speech
is something that we all should have and
that these
platforms should essentially be
like
like utilities like the electric company
jack is correct and he has the right
vision it's just he's in an organization
where the other individuals in the
organization feel differently very
differently so the organization itself
can get hijacked and his timeline for
changing things it's like
it's decades
i mean i i don't know i shouldn't say
decades but i mean i was like when do
you think that something well there's a
part there was one idea of
having an uncensored twitter like one
twitter that's the wild west like you
could have regular twitter or you could
try wild west twitter like well that
that already exists there's a network
called gab yes but gab isn't even wild
west twitter they when when people dox
people they remove things like that yeah
i mean i think there's certainly lines
around violence and illegality that you
don't want to cross but yes gab is
closer to free speech platform but it's
still not decentralized it can still get
shut down it can still get taken out
it's also suppressed heavily yes so that
so there and the people on there are
right now are extremely right-wing so
it's not a pleasant place for someone
like me to hang out with all the people
that have been kicked off of something
that's right so that's right try going
over there and being moderate try going
over there
there's no room for you yeah
unfortunately because i don't identify
as any party or any creed you know it
doesn't work for me
is that a problem in silicon valley when
you don't identify as anything do you
get pressure it totally it used to be
okay it's not okay anymore when was it
okay like 10 years ago i would say it
was okay and then you started seeing a
shift yeah and now you have to pick
sides otherwise you're automatically the
enemy really yeah struggle sessions and
all that god struggle sessions i'm
exaggerating for effect but but it
definitely has that oppressive feeling
to it right and you also have to be
politically outspoken right yeah it
can't be something that you just stay
neutral about right it's like when uh
tim ferriss i think at some point put
out a tweet about how you can't just say
anything anymore and you know people are
being suppressed and a whole bunch of
people who love them from silicon valley
piled and said what is it that you can't
say what are you afraid to say you can
say whatever you want tim go ahead what
are you afraid of
right they don't like baiting yeah what
was he trying to say wow we have to put
him in that box what is someone who's
thinking about saying something he
shouldn't have said exactly now we know
one great tweet i saw was you know the
left one the culture wars now they're
just driving around shooting the
survivors wow
that's hilarious
yeah i wonder i wonder who as has won
the culture war there's certainly a
battle that's been won in terms of like
control of social media control of
social media is absolutely left well
this is unfortunate
for conservatives but technology is a
force that also pushes left so if you
look all throughout human history like
the left essentially grows and grows and
grows right why is that why is it
inexorably that
as some commentators have said leviathan
slouch is left right leviathan is the
government why does it slouch left and i
think a lot of that has been because of
technology uh technology has made it so
that it makes more like industrial
revolution technology we all band
together we're wards of the state right
contraception is a technology that kind
of helps lean leftward it takes away
from the family unit abortion is a
technology
right it wasn't possible thousands of
years ago
so technology actually empowers the
individual the individual means that you
have the breakdown of family structure
and religion and all that and i'm not
mostly opposed to that but it does mean
that there's a leftward shift to it
now we're getting a small set of
technologies that actually can take you
more rightward encryption is an example
because encryption makes it easier to
have privacy it makes it easier to have
money that is outside of the state
guns 3d printing of guns is an example
of a technology that is more of a
rightward shift
but generally technology leads the world
left
yeah it's it's also
usually highly educated people that are
involved in technology in the first
place and i think
when you look at universities in
particular they tend to lean left in
this country as well
well universities
what happened with the university is
very interesting
universities first when you know became
the arbiters of
data and intellectualism and what's
right and wrong so there's a time period
when it was like should we be doing that
or not well let's look at the university
what do they have to say what are the
smartest people the professors the think
tanks have to say and the universities
got this credibility from the hard
sciences so they got this from uh you
know physics and math and computer
science and chemistry because these
deliver real things the manhattan
project the microprocessor the space
vehicles and so on the electric car
so they gain this mantle of authority
and legitimacy from the hard sciences so
then come the social sciences kind of
sneak in then you get economy
economics and microeconomics is a real
discipline real science real math behind
it logic reason and then you get
macroeconomics which can be politicized
a little bit more voodoo and then you
get social studies and then you get
gender studies and then you get blah
blah blah blah blah blah
and so what happened is that
because we took scientists to be the
high priests
of our new world
science itself has gotten corrupted and
the social sciences and you can tell
they're fake sciences because the word
science tacked on at the end have come
in and hijacked the universities and
become the new think tanks
and so essentially what you see going on
today in the universities is a war
between the social sciences and the
physical sciences and the crossover
point is biology right where you can see
like the whole gender is a social
construct movement is attacking biology
and evolutionary biology
just like in the social sphere they're
coming after the comedians right but you
can see the struggle going on the
universities and i would say the
physical sciences are essentially losing
that war
what can be done
or is it just something that has to play
out is it do we have to realize the
consequences of the foolishness well the
good news is the physical sciences have
a reality on their side
yeah but it's not even i mean
in many ways it's not respected
yeah but you at the end of the day your
aircraft still has to fly
uh you know your microprocessor still
has to compute so there's only so far
they can they can take it uh but i do
see for example in biology a lot of
biologists are facing this difficult
thing where they have to say things that
they know are not true to keep their job
like what well you had brett weinstein
on here
right so that's a that's a clear example
so there's just
the crossover line of what is acceptable
and what's not is entering into biology
and biology will probably suffer the
most
synthetic biology for example
will you know a lot of this will end up
in china
because it won't be
you you won't be able to map facts and
reality
and actions together you won't be able
to get grants you won't be able to get
the adulation of your peers
i don't i don't know enough here so now
i'm in shaky territory but it's just my
sense that that crossover battleground
right now is an evolutionary biology
economics lost well it's certainly in
terms of gender and that that that sort
of that seems to be one of the major
battlegrounds yeah i mean it's also
going to happen for example blank slate
theory you know are we nature are we
nature
um it's kind of uh socially unacceptable
to say that you know a lot of it is
nature and not nurture or vice versa
depending on which side you're on right
those kinds of discussions get corrupted
they do get corrupted and it's really
unfortunate because that's an
unbelievably important thing to
understand like what makes a person a
sociopath what makes a person a super
successful person a winner what what
makes a person a drug addict
what are these factors you can't have a
reasonable conversation about climate
science anymore right it's not a science
it's all politicized you can't even
bring it up everyone's got their minds
made up already well it's what's
uncomfortable to me is people have their
minds made up and they don't even have
the data
well on most of these topics people are
talking past each other anyway they're
talking about different things like when
you get into
uh you know when you when you get into
gun control for example right
one side is talking about the right to
bear arms in case a tyrannical ruler or
king tries to take over the country the
other time the other side is talking
about school shootings and you know
protecting people in their homes right
from crime so they're just talking about
two different things right and it's just
not politically acceptable to even talk
about the same thing or when it gets to
immigration the right is talking about
uh you know
the left is like bundling together
illegal immigration and legal
immigration into one thing yes right
whereas in the on the right sometimes
you've got racist hiding in there so it
doesn't help their cause right they're
talking about two different things yeah
if they were talking about the same
thing which is how many immigrants
should we let into the country and you
know what are the criteria for that that
would be a very different conversation
than no immigrants or everybody comes in
and then also on the left you know you
have this benefit that everybody who's
currently coming in illegally is going
to vote for the left because of where
they're coming from in their
socioeconomic circumstances
to me the test of any good system is you
build a system hand it over to your
enemies to run for the next decade so
for example if you want a censorship on
twitter or facebook you should build
that system and then hand it over to the
other side to run so if you're a
left-winger who's promoting uh
censorship let somebody else running
same with immigration if you want
immigration system build the system then
hand it over to the other side to run it
that's how you know it's a good system
there's no room for nuance when you're
dealing with these political
battlegrounds when when you're dealing
with right versus left and one side has
a clearly established
stance that you're supposed to take
like gun control is a great example of
that right there's no room for
what about mental health what about the
fact that so many of these people are on
psych medications right
why is that not being discussed we're
running one of the greatest uh
mental health experiments in history
when we're doping everybody up and ssris
yeah and you know maybe if you give 30
million people sris maybe like 29.9
million are a lot happier and then you
have a fraction that commits suicide or
detonate yeah you're basically trading
the mean for the variance right you have
blow up risk
yeah there's no room for nuance which is
why i stay out of politics largely do
they drag you in though sometimes they
always try i mean these conversations in
this conversation you get to get dragged
in sure but i'm sure there's going to be
some people here here's the thing about
politics because they're we we have a
first-past-the-post system what that
means is that whoever wins 51 of the
vote in this country gets a lot of the
power right it's not like proportional
representation where the greens have ten
percent and you know libertarians are
three percent or whatever it's just like
you're all democrat in power now we're
all republican because of that to win
you have to pick one of these two sides
right you have you have to choose you
can't just you can't just
you can't just basically say i'm gonna
be
uh you know nuanced about it you you
can't vote for a third party that's
throwing over your vote right i have a
friend who's trying to fix that he's
starting this thing called a good party
where like you kick-start your vote so
you combine all your votes you hold them
in reserve and then when you have enough
to win then you vote that person in
power right you don't you don't throw
away your vote but outside of those
hacks we're never gonna get a third
party elected so because of that all of
your beliefs have to neatly fit into the
democrat bundle or the republican bundle
and so when you get into that tribe uh
if you signal outside of that out of
that bundle you get attacked yeah so
it's literally it's making you into an
unclear thinker it's making you into a
muddled thinker if all of your beliefs
line up into one political party you're
not a clear thinker if all your beliefs
are the same as your neighbors and your
friends you're not a clear thinker
you're literally just your beliefs are
socialized they're taken from other
people so if you want to be a clear
thinker you cannot pay attention to
politics it will destroy your ability to
think
what dread
most of modern life all our diseases are
diseases of abundance not diseases of
scarcity right old times i may have
starved
you know old times if i got sugar that
was a wonderful thing i should have
eaten all the sugar to get my hands on
if i gotten a piece of news or gossip
that was interesting data that would
have helped my life and moved me forward
if i'd gotten some brief amount of
entertainment whether through video
games or magazines or whatever that
would have been good
now it's all disease of abundance we are
overexposed to everything so the way to
survive in modern society is to be an
ascetic it is to retreat from society
there's too much society everywhere you
go society in your phone society in your
pocket society in your ears you're being
socialized right now by listening to
this podcast right we're socializing you
we're programming you everyone's trying
to program everybody the only solution
is turn it off
the only solution is to turn it off and
concentrate on your breathing
meditation yeah yes i mean it works it's
it's been a lifesaver for me oh i do it
and i i do it whenever i get like spare
time i was in the doctor's office this
morning and uh i knew it was going to be
20 minutes so i just sat there with my
eyes closed for 20 minutes and i
meditated you know when i was growing up
there was this statement i think it was
pascal he said you know all of man's
problems arise because he cannot sit by
himself in a room for 30 minutes alone
and it's very true i always needed to be
stimulated and when the iphone came
along boredom was dead i would never be
bored again even if i'm standing in line
i'm on my iphone and i thought it was
great and when i was a kid i used to try
and overclock my brain be like how many
thoughts can i think at once the answer
is only one but i would try to like
think multiple thoughts at once and i
was proud of that i was proud that my
brain was always running this engine was
always moving
and it's a disease it's actually the
road to misery and now that i'm older i
realize like
you actually want to again rest your
mind you want to learn how to settle
into your mind now i look forward to
solitary confinement you leave me alone
for a day it'll be like the happiest day
i've had in a while
and and that is a superpower that i
think everybody can attain
the superpower of learning to be alone
and enjoying it yeah
yeah
well i think it's critical and i and i
do think that this these times where you
just think about things just be alone
and think about things are so rare these
days
and i think
during those rare times is when you
really get to understand what you
actually believe or don't believe
yeah it's it's funny when i first
started meditating it was really hard
right because everybody i think a lot of
people who listen to this broadcast
they've heard of meditation that has a
good rep so everybody tries it they
struggle
they kind of give it up it's one of
those things that everybody says they do
but nobody actually does right it's like
not eating sugar right everyone talks
about how yeah i don't eat sugar but
like yeah then right then the dessert
tray rolls around and everyone's going
for the cookies yeah right
so it's become one of those things and
in fact it's not even become a signaling
thing where it's like oh how much did
you meditate i meditated this much or
you know there are people now wearing
headbands saying with tweety birds a
chirp and then when they're in deep
meditation i don't i don't know how they
make it work but they'll be like i got a
lot of trips today how many trips did
you get oh my god oh your meditation
technique is wrong mine is right but
really all it is is the art of doing
nothing okay and it's important because
i think when we
when we grow up right it's all this
stuff happening to you in your life and
some of it you're processing some of it
you're absorbing and some of it you
should probably think a little bit more
about and work through but you don't you
don't have time so it gets buried in you
and it's all these preferences and
judgments and unresolved situations and
issues and it's like your email inbox
it's just piling up email after email
after email that's not answered going
back 10 20 30 40 years
and then when you sit down to meditate
those emails start coming back at you
hey what about this issue what about
that issue have you solved this did you
think about that your regrets there you
have issues there
and that gets scary people don't want to
do that it's like it's not working i
can't clear my mind i better get up and
not do this but really what's happening
is it's it's self therapy it's just that
instead of paying a therapist to sit
there and listen to you you're listening
to yourself and you just have to sit
there as those emails go through one by
one you work through each of them until
you get to the magical inbox zero and
there comes a day when you sit down you
realize the only things you're thinking
about are things that happened yesterday
because you've processed everything else
not necessarily even resolved it but at
least listen to yourself
and that's when meditation starts and i
think it's a it's a very powerful thing
that everybody should experience and
that's when you arrive upon the art of
doing nothing well i think it's even a
problem that most people are getting
their meditation from an app
i will not use an app it's sneaky i mean
sam harris is a very good meditation app
i should say that but you should be able
to just do it and many people can it is
literally the art of doing nothing yeah
all you need to do for meditation is
just sit down close your eyes
comfortable position whatever happens
happens if you think you think if you
don't think you don't think don't put
effort into it don't put effort against
it it's all you need do you concentrate
on your breath or do you have a specific
technique nothing nothing no you just
sit you just sit i think about my breath
that's all i do i just need to try to
only concentrate on breathing i used to
do that but at some level all the
concentration every meditation technique
is leading you to the same thing which
is just witnessing yes and concentration
is a technique to still your mind enough
that you can then drop the object of
concentration
so you could also just try going
straight to the end game the problem
with what i'm talking about which is not
focusing on your breath is you will have
to listen to your mind for a long time
it's not going to work unless you do at
least an hour a day and preferably at
least 60 days before you kind of work
through a lot of issues so it'll be held
for a while but when you come out the
other side it's great you get rid of the
chatter
or when the chatter comes it's in the
background it's dimmer it's smaller
you've heard it before you see the
patterns
it's more recent it's something you need
to resolve anyway
and you will get moments of actual
silence what is your
what's your ultimate state when you
meditate like is there a state where
you've achieved
rarely if ever
where you just
you you're in bliss or you're in harmony
or you're in enlightenment like what
it's kind of it's kind of indescribable
uh because when you're really meditating
you're not there when there's no
thoughts there's no experience there's
nothing there's just
nothing uh so it's it's hard to describe
but i would say that uh it's like a
you can definitely
every psychedelic state that people
encounter using so-called plant
medicines can be arrived just through
pure meditation and i've definitely hit
some of those states you've hit some
transcendent psychedelic states where
you're vaccinating the whole deal i've
had trippy visuals i've had the kind of
the lights and colors i've had the
so-called downloads i've had the
realizations i've had the bliss i've had
the light i've had the colors but not
every time no it's really and in fact i
would say that that's a that's also like
an experience that you can start craving
which will then actually take you out of
meditation
um where you really and i'm not
enlightened or anything close to it so
not even the ballpark but my own
experience and this is this personal
experience is
the place where i end up the most that
is really the one that i i want to be at
is peace
it's just peace peace happy
yeah peace to me peace is happiness at
rest and happiness is kind of peace and
motion you can convert peace to
happiness anytime you want but peace is
what you want most of the time that's
interesting you can convert peace to
happiness anytime you want yeah if
you're a peaceful person anything you do
will be a happy activity
and by the way being on social media
engaging politics will not bring you
peace there is nothing less peaceful
right and
today's day and age the way we think you
get peace is by resolving all your
external problems but there's unlimited
external problems so the only way to
actually get pieces on the inside by
giving up this idea of problems who
thinks you can get peace by resolving
external problems other than politicians
everybody that's what everybody's
struggling to do right why are you
trying to make money to solve all your
money problems
why are you trying to win a politics
because then you'll be at peace because
your people will have one
it's a daunting task to get your [ __ ]
together it's easier to change yourself
than to change the world
that's true yeah and the best way to
change the world is to change yourself
exactly it's all yeah it's
all these people who are shouting on
social media the best way is just to
actually live the life that you want
other people to live
like i went down to new zealand and
there's this guy
that i met with and
you know everyone's on social media
shouting about environmentalism and
conservative and sustain and i go to
this guy's house and he was doing a
very quietly very gently he was doing a
two week long
zero waste experiment
where he was throwing out nothing so
every package that he opened he would
keep and he would like clean it up so he
would keep his amazon boxes it would
keep the little containers even a tea
bag if you open the tea bag he has to
figure out how to compost the tea inside
how to make the tea itself useful how to
make the tea bag like a little storage
item so there was no trash he was
literally living with zero
trash waste and he was doing it and it
was really inspirational meeting people
like him made me far more
environmentally conscious than you know
any amount of people yelling at me on
social media ever will how long did he
do that for i think it was two weeks it
was hard
what the [ __ ] are you gonna do with tea
bags
he had quite the collection
he was filling them with little things
he sounds like a crazy this hoarder like
a hoarder person with stacks of tea bags
in his house a very impressive guy yeah
that's a strange way to go about things
i i appreciate that i mean
look it is entirely possible to somehow
or another engineer all of our cups and
all of our things and all our about to
be biodegradable
you know the struggle with the modern
environmental movement is that they
identify the correct problem which is
finite earth spaceship earth this is all
they got don't ruin it but they don't
have the solution so what they say is no
growth no growth no growth well the
problem is you got three billion indian
and chinese who aren't going to stay in
poverty they're going to grow whether
you like it or not so you can yell at
them you can scream at them you can yell
at us and scream at us but that's not
going to happen so the only way out
unfortunately is again through
technology which is you have to build
green technology and i give musk a lot
of credit you know for being one of the
few people who's out there trying to do
that so you build things that are
biodegradable and good for you and
healthier and everybody wants to be
healthier chinese want to be healthier
indians want to be healthier they want
to be cleaner if you say i can clean up
your rivers i can clean up your forests
i can have your children not get sick
with cholera and diphtheria and typhoid
i can cure your diseases i can help make
your immune system stronger i can give
you clean drinking water like that is
what causes people to become
environmentalists not shouting and
screaming at them that they shouldn't
grow and they should stop pumping things
into the sky and you know they have no
concept of that they're just trying to
get out of poverty so i think the modern
environmental movement
identifies the correct problem but then
doesn't come up with the right set of
solutions that are appealing to people
people are not going to give up economic
growth they're going to have to get rich
first hmm that's yeah that's a very good
point but how do you do how do you do
both
you lower the price of clean
technologies massively so you basically
make clean technologies cost competitive
through subsidy technologies
innovation
ideally you can subsidize in the short
to medium term until the innovation
curve is is crossed i mean like tesla
doesn't have any patents right right or
they they freely give away their patents
that's the example of how you can do it
um so you know someone in if you want to
get rid of plastic such straws
yeah you can do it here and there you
can get san francisco to ban plastic
straws but china's not going to blend
ban plastic straws not until you build a
paper straw that is you know same cost
good durability and then you in and then
you educate the chinese like hey this is
petroleum you know this plastic that
you're doing is petroleum this is bad
for you here's the chemical composition
here's the things that are going in your
bloodstream and they want healthy happy
kids also so they're going to have their
kids use paper straws maybe straws
aren't the best example but you can you
know this is true with fossil fuels for
example that's that's probably the best
one or replacing a lot of plastics with
glass and paper and so on
yeah there's a new technology that was
just rhonda patrick had it on her
twitter today about
they're able to convert
plastic uh waste into fuel
and that there's companies that are
actively trying to do that now so then
in that way plastic waste will become
valuable right and it'll become a
commodity it'll become something that
people are resource now there's certain
problems this doesn't solve this doesn't
solve carbon this doesn't solve
deforestation uh you know so there you
kind of have to step in with other means
so for example you look at the amazon
right everyone's complaining about the
amazon being deforested well you're not
the poor brazilian farmer right so
you're you're sitting here in your
comfortable chair like social media
hammering away at you know the evil
brazilians for deforesting the amazon
but the amazon has incredible resources
if we really care about it we should
turn it into an incredible tourist park
and put your money where your mouth is
start doing ecotourism in the amazon
start paying for it and then maybe take
the future rights for all the
pharmaceuticals that are going to come
out of all the incredible plants there
and start selling those off so that
people so that maybe give the
pharmaceutical companies an incentive to
preserve the biodiversity of the amazon
say hey if you buy this patch of the
amazon you conserve it and you can serve
it whatever plant medicines that come
out of there that you can then license
you get the patent for 20 years or 30
years or whatever
so i think there are solutions where we
as the first worlders who have money can
put our
money where where our mouth is and go
and rescue these kinds of properties
that's a very interesting solution but i
could see immediate pushback from people
that don't think the pharmaceutical
company should have the rights to this
natural plan okay or the or the
government does it and then the
government gets the patents and the
government will auction off the patents
later or they'll worse or they'll
license them or whatever it is right
well that's often like just this
the often the problem is there is no
really good solution there's a bunch of
solutions that also have drawbacks
that's life yeah right that's the
trade-off so it's being human very messy
yeah it's a constrained environment
obviously i skew more towards a private
property capitalist type solutions
because even though they're not perfect
they have been proven to actually work
right once something is your property
you take care of it right you're not
gonna you're not gonna crap all over
your own house
um but it should probably be temporary
property not permanent property you see
a lot of countries around the world not
doing this no foreign ownership of land
thing for example or mexico has no
private ownership of beaches right so
you can draw the line at certain points
yeah do you enjoy doing this kind of
thing where you break things down and
give your perspective on things and try
to illuminate certain complex subjects
i'm not trying to illuminate so much as
you know talking to you i learn as much
as i
say and i learn it for myself because
i'm being forced to articulate it right
i can sit around and think my thoughts
all day long but it's a lot of it's
going to be nonsense it's not i'm going
to because there are gaps in thinking
where you make leaps
because you're kind to yourself that you
don't realize you're making but when
you're forced to write it down and this
is why i tweet or when you have to talk
to somebody you have to complete those
gaps and make it a proper logical chain
and the mistake that i made when i was
young was you know i always wanted to
seem like the smartest kid in the room
uh you know like just like you probably
want to seem like the funniest kid in
the room or the toughest kid in the room
right we're all losers starting out we
want to be winners so we pick the thing
we're good at and we double down on it
so i always want to be the smartest kid
in the room so what did i do i read a
lot of books i memorized a lot of things
and then whatever i hadn't memorized is
pre-google i made it up so it sounded
good okay
pre-google after google fact checking
started and i had to get better right so
google improved me that way a lot of
people exactly so
now what i realize is that the biggest
mistake with memorization
right because when you're actually
trying to live your life in congress
with reality
you
you want to have a deep understanding of
what you do and why you do it and so
it's much more important to know the
basics really well then is to know the
advanced knowing calculus wouldn't help
you today it doesn't help you in
business doesn't help you in most things
but knowing arithmetic really will help
you really
whether it's at the corner grocery store
counting change to figuring out the
value of your podcast business to
figuring out how to do the probability
math on you know some action that you
want to take so understanding basic
mathematics cold is way more important
than memorizing calculus concepts and
the problem is and this is true of i
think all reasoning it's much better to
know the basics from the ground up solid
foundation of understanding a steel
frame of understanding than it is to
just have a scaffolding we're just
memorizing advanced concepts this is why
there are a lot of people i'm sure that
you listen to who are really smart they
use a lot of jargon and you can't quite
follow their reasoning you don't know
how they're putting things together and
you this deep down suspicion they don't
even really understand right
so if you look at the the most powerful
thinkers especially the ones where money
or life is on the line
they have to understand the basics
really really well richard feynman the
physicist was able to
he had this piece in one of his lectures
where he takes you from counting numbers
on your hand all the way to calculus in
four pages of text orally but written
down is four pages of text and it's a
complete unbroken logical chain that
takes you through geometry trigonometry
precalculus analytic geometry graphs
everything all the way to calculus he
understood numbers at a core level he
didn't have to memorize anything when
you're memorizing it's an indication
that you don't understand
you should be able to rederive anything
on the spot
and if you can't you don't know it
so do you apply that to
things other than mathematics everything
everything you don't even make attempt
to memorize things just make an attempt
to understand them you can't help but
memorize things but if you can't and
this is where twitter is great for me is
i try to understand something and then i
try to write it down in such a way that
i can remember it just the basic hook
that'll point towards the deeper
understanding and i'm forced to explain
it to people and that's how i know i
understand something so this is what i
meant originally we talked about reading
a good book i'll read one page in a
night and then i spend the rest of night
thinking about it or i'm chasing down
references on wikipedia or weird blog
posts trying to understand it
you know so for example
there was a
i was dealing with this is a few months
back i was dealing with a question of
stupid topic but the meaning of life
right what's the meaning how could that
be stupid though well it's just trite
it's right you're not supposed to think
about it it's something you ask your
parents when you're young they tell you
don't worry about it or they'll get a
job yeah exactly good job you freaking
hippy or here's god god is the meaning
of life right and so i was just trying
to resolve for myself like
what could the answer be right not what
is the answer but what could the answer
be
and so at a core level i was forced to
kind of hunt down all these weird little
things and really understand for myself
and it's got to be personal right but i
have to establish for myself what it
could and could not be
and that gave me some level of peace
so now i have to keep asking that
question what is the meaning of life
i mean you you sh i think the question
is more interesting than the answer
everyone should explore this on their
own but let me just explore a few parts
with you right
so first is if i gave you an answer if i
said the meaning of life has to please
god well which god okay judeo-christian
god well okay why that one why this
thing the problem is it's a why question
you can keep asking why forever right
any answer i give you you'll just ask
why again why again
that's right and you end up in a place
called agrippa's trilemma okay this is a
philosophical exercise but i i kind of
thought it through then googled around
and there's a thing called agrippa's
trilemma
and agrippa's trauma says that any
questioning like this
y will always end in one of three places
okay first is infinite regress
right why because of this why that what
and just keep going forever the second
is circular reasoning well a why a
because of b or why b because of a right
you get trapped in that or the third is
an axiom and the most popular axiom is
god but it could be anything because of
math because of science because the big
bang because the simulation right these
are all axioms these are all just
stopping points
saying simulation we're in a simulation
or saying it's the big bang is just
another way of saying god it's just
god's a dirty word so we don't use it as
much anymore but same thing so you end
up in one of these three dead ends
essentially right so there is no answer
uh the real answer is because
right what is the meaning of life yeah
you get to make up your own answers the
beauty if there was a single answer we
would not be free we would be trapped
because then we would all have to live
to that answer then we'd be bored like
robots each one competing with each
other to fulfill that single meaning
more than the others back to signaling
like i'm better at it than you are but
luckily there is no answer so you just
do whatever you want
the meaning of life
it's funny that
that what that's the basis of all
existential angst that you don't
you don't know why you're here and you
have this feeling that it could be
meaningless
it is i mean if you
when you start pondering the
the multiverse the universe the galaxies
the solar system the planet the organism
the cells inside the organism the
bacteria the parasites right the
symbiotic relationship we have to our
environment and you start going jesus
christ what am i just a little piece of
this thing it's like well the answers to
all the great questions or paradoxes
yeah so for example you're asking like
do i matter that's like really the
question you asked right well how do i
matter in this infinite universe well
you know on the one hand you're separate
no two points are the same every point
is every two points are infinitely
different you're completely separated no
one will have your thoughts your
emotions your feelings your experience
so your life is a single player game
you're trapped inside your head and
you're just aware of a bunch of things
going on and that's it
on the other hand
i cannot say the word joe rogan without
invoking the entire universe joe alien
comes along says what's that joe rogan
what's joe rogan's a human what's a
human bipedal ape what's an ape on the
earth what's the earth planet what's a
planet solar system where was the carbon
made inside stars right instead i have
to create the entire universe
to just say the words joe rogan so in
that sense you're connected to
everything it's inseparable so
the answer to that question of do i
matter is i am nothing and i am
everything and you'll find this with all
the great questions the answers are all
paradoxes which is why at some level
it's sort of pointless to pursue them to
find a trite answer like i'm giving but
the act of pursuing them is actually
really useful because then it gives you
certain intrinsic understanding in your
life that brings a level of peace
i feel like there's with many people
this
stress of this question is also
accentuated by unhappy lives it's
actually accentuated by unhappy choices
by being trapped there's a big
difference between not knowing what the
meaning of life is and
god i gotta get the [ __ ] out of this job
i have to i can't live my life this way
what's the meaning of life if this is my
life which is why i always start with
let's get you rich first
right that's why i'm very practical
about it because look the you know
buddha was a prince okay he started out
really rich and then he got to go off in
the woods
and in the old days what happened was if
you wanted to be peaceful inside you
would become a monk you would renounce
everything you would become an ascetic
you would give everything up you
renounce women men you'd renounce
children you'd announce money you'd
renounce politics science technology
everything and you would go out in the
woods by yourself you could give
everything up to be free inside
well today we have this wonderful
invention called money where you can
just store stuff up in a bank account
okay and you can basically
save up you can you can work really hard
you can do great things for society and
society will give you money for giving
it things that it wants and it doesn't
know how to get
and then you can save that up and you
can live well below with your means and
you can find a certain freedom in that
and that will give you the time and the
energy to pursue your own internal peace
and happiness
so i believe the solution to making
everybody happy is to give them what
they want let's get them all rich let's
get them all fit and healthy and then
let's get them all happy
is are those things even possible
everyone can be rich everyone can be
rich everyone here's my thought exercise
for you now it seems like we're in an
infomercial
everyone can be writing not selling my
home this is my rolls royce yeah no so
that's a good point so everything that
i've ever created on this topic of how
to make money i will never charge a
dollar for
because that would ruin it that would
show that i'm just another huckster
who's trying to get rich off of you
there are no get-rich-quick schemes
that's just somebody else trying to get
rich off of you right so it's so to me
it's more of a philosophical
contribution where for it to have
meaning and to be legit i can't charge
you anything for it but yes everybody
can be rich and let me give you a
thought exercise okay
imagine if tomorrow we could wave a wand
and everybody was trained
as a scientist or an engineer everybody
even if you weren't very good you had
enough understanding of computers you
could write some code you could build
some hardware and don't tell me people
can't do it because they can that's just
the tyranny of soft expectations that's
just you looking down on somebody else
they can't do it they just have to be
educated now if they're educated all as
hardware software engineers scientists
biologists technicians hard sciences not
the social sciences we would all be done
within five years robots would be doing
everything from cleaning toilets to
cooking food to flying airplanes to
driving ubers and what would we be doing
we would be doing all creative jobs to
entertain each other and researching
science and technology we would have
wonderful lives so it is really just a
question of education nothing else
is this a scale issue though i mean
you're talking about it as if this would
work with 300 million people it'll work
with 10 billion people it'll work with a
spacefaring race with 100 trillion
people just we have the resources we
have
the ability the universe is infinite
resources you build it you know have you
heard of a dyson sphere
you know you pull the dyson sphere on a
star and you gather all its energy like
that there's so much energy out there
one asteroid's got all the minerals that
we need one sun one solar system has got
all the power we will need for a long
long time uh you know we can extract it
out of nuclear fusion you know we're
we're not that far from those kinds of
technologies working
uh it's just a question of guts and uh
you know and interest like we should be
building nuclear fusion test plants on
the moon the moon should be littered
with them it's no downside right
yeah
if you could
how would that work well it doesn't send
a bunch of people up there to work oh
the problem robots the problem with
fission nuclear fission is that you know
nature
creates energy through nuclear energy
right like the sun creates energy
nuclear energy now for transmission we
use photons because photons don't
interact and so photons are great for
information transmission but they're
actually not great for energy
transmission for energy creation
you want nuclear to work and the problem
is because nuclear energy you know we
built it with a bomb we have dirty nukes
all those kinds of problems with
fukushima three-mile island chernobyl
we don't innovate anymore on nukes
imagine if when the first steam engine
blew up we said oh
no more steam engines for a while or
very carefully regulated billion dollars
of regulation you can't innovate that
way when the first airplane crashed we
said no more innovation in airplanes
right
so we need a way to iterate on nuclear
fission and eventually fusion and get
them working safely cleanly passive say
failure etc if we're going to find our
way out of the energy trap and the best
place to do that is someplace like on
the moon or mars
do you think that it's actually a
possibility that they could
get nuclear power to the point where
it's not a detriment because what
everyone's worried about is a meltdown
right yeah and we do have these old
plants that are running that are running
on this this is 50 years old technology
it's crazy because there's no ability to
shut them off right very old technology
they do now have gen 4 nuclear reactors
that are passive fail safe so in other
words when they fail they fail into us
when you pull the plug on them they fail
into a state where there's no leakage
there's no problem right their default
is a positive outcome as opposed to the
current ones the old ones where if you
unplug them like and these even these
gen four are just gen four they're not
gen five they're not gen eighty gen
hundred where we're in microprocessors
right and that should be something that
people are working towards i hope so i
mean in an ideal world we would now the
problem is if you have nuclear energy on
the moon how do you get it home right so
what you actually got to do is you got
to
rev it on the moon and you're using it
there maybe to launch more satellites
more rockets further out into the solar
system and that's the initial use case
um but then eventually the technology
gets so good you can bring it home
now i want to go back to this idea of
getting people rich that somehow or
another that's going to make people
happy how do you stop the the
natural progression that people have of
you know oh you know i have got a nice
chevrolet yeah but i really want a bmw
i've got a nice bmw but now i want a
mercedes i have mercedes i want a
ferrari
how do you stop that material
possession
trap because you can't at some level but
i think most smart people over time
realize that possessions don't make them
happy right it's just you have to go
through that you have to buy your stupid
car to realize that it doesn't attract
attractive girls it actually just
attracts other dudes who are like hey
i like that car man right like like you
have some expensive cars out there some
fancy cars tell me how you know how much
that attracts women versus men well i'm
married those are for me
i just enjoy machines yeah so for me
they're toys that's a particular thing
where you enjoy machines but i think
very as you get older
you just realize that there's no
happiness in material possessions now
lack of material possessions can make
you very unhappy so being poor can make
you unhappy but being rich is not going
to make you happy
and what happens unfortunately a lot of
people struggle through their whole
lives to make money they make some
they're exhausted and then they're like
well now why am i not happy i guess i'm
just not a happy person and smart people
aren't happy that's like a great little
way to people feel better about it they
say well if you're smart you're not
happy right where's i positive the other
way if you're smart you should be able
to figure out how to be happy otherwise
you're not that smart yeah that is an
offensive statement that if you're smart
you're not happy i've heard that before
and i just do not understand the logic
of that other than self-justifying i
understand where it comes from it comes
from if you're smart it's usually
because you thought things through and
you have a very busy mind yeah and so
busy mind can often rob you of peace of
mind
because what
the peace that we seek is not peace of
mind it's peace from mind
right so if you look at all the crazy
activities you do to be happy right
whether it's like trying to get laid and
have an orgasm or you know extreme
sports or looking at something beautiful
or taking a psychedelic you're trying to
get out of your own mind you're trying
to get your monkey mind to stop
chattering at you for a moment you're
trying to get peace from the mind
and there are other better ways to do
that most of the ways we try to get
peace from mind are indirect
whereas if you understand things if you
see things properly you will naturally
slowly develop peace from mind
sorry if i went on a tangent there no
it's a good tangent it's a good tangent
because i think that oftentimes
the pursuit
is
what's thrilling to people and the
possibility that one day they'll be able
to rest and that they'll reach this goal
that's the fundamental delusion that
there is something out there that will
make me happy and fulfill forever yeah
golden years there is it's called death
oh i'll take care of everything that's
the great leveler but when people look
at particularly social media bring it
back to that when you see someone who
you know you see them posed in front of
their mansion with their beautiful car
and they're leaning against it with
their designer clothes on their
expensive watch
you go i want that right that's what i
want
what you really want is freedom you want
freedom from your money problems right
and i think that's okay so people once
someone can solve their money problems
either by lowering their lifestyle or by
making enough money
and you know
essentially what you want to get
everybody to the retirement but not
retirement in the i'm 65 years old
sitting in a nursing home collecting a
check retirement different definition
retirement is when you stop
sacrificing today for some imaginary
tomorrow
okay yes when today is complete in and
of itself you're retired yeah and so how
do you get there well one is you can
have so much money saved up that just
your passive income off of that without
you having to lift a finger covers your
burn rate keep your burn rate low right
a second is you just drive your burn
rate down to zero you become a monk
a third is you're doing something you
love you enjoy it so much it's not about
the money right so there are multiple
ways to that path but the most common is
people just say i need to make more
money and the kind of wealth creation
that i talk about is about creating
timeless principles and adapting
yourselves that making money won't be an
issue and you can do it by doing what
you love right like we get into this
model of i must work for other people
work my way up the ladder
i must like do what that person is doing
to make money but really today in
society you get rewarded for creative
work for creating something brand new
that society didn't even know yet that
it wanted it doesn't know how to get
other than through you so the most
powerful money makers are actually
individual brands people like yourself
or elon or kanye or oprah or trump right
these are individual brands eponymous
name brands who themselves are leveraged
like you're leveraged you have podcast
media going out to everybody that's
leveraged the podcasts work for you when
you sleep they have knowledge that
nobody else has which is your knowledge
is the knowledge of being joe rogan i
mean who else is a ufc fighter and a
commentator and a podcaster and a
comedian and you know interested in all
these things and those all these people
can't replace you
um so we have to pay you what you're
worth and who's i never fought in the
ufc though
oh you didn't okay sorry
um or you know you're whatever you're
you're involved in that whole scene you
just have a unique set of skill sets
um so because of this unique what i call
specific knowledge because of the
accountability that you have with your
name because the leverage that you have
through your media you're a money-making
machine you're
i'm sure at this point i could make you
start over tomorrow wipe out your bank
account you'd be rich again in no time
because you have all the skill sets so
once people have those skill sets and
the beauty is the way you've done it is
you don't have any competition there's
no substitution if joe rogan were to
disappear off the air tomorrow it's not
like random podcaster number 12 would
step in and fill that thing no it's it's
just gone so the way to get out of that
competition trap is actually to be
authentic the way to retire is actually
to find the thing that you know how to
do better than anybody and you know how
to do that better than anybody because
you love to do it no one can compete
with you if you love to do it be
authentic
and then figure out how to map that to
what society actually wants apply some
leverage put your name on it so you take
the risks but you gain the rewards have
ownership and equity in what you do and
then just crank it out i think people
have to be very careful to not get
trapped along the way with
things that you can afford with your
current lifestyle like the way you're
living and the way you're earning but
they're also imprisoning you and the
fact that you are now going to have to
work this 40-hour a week job in order to
get this thing that you can't afford but
now you you're saddled down to this job
you've no you're not saving you're not
you're not putting things in a good
place and you're working for these
things
working for things as rewards is a real
trap that a lot of people fall into it's
the biggest one you know naseem tell
that also says that uh you know under
two great addictions heroin and a
monthly salary
right
and and that's why you can't get rich
writing out your time because even when
you start charging more and more for
your time it's a slow upgrade loop and
then you upgrade your house at the same
time you break your car at the same time
you move in the neighborhood you really
also have to get used to ignoring your
peers
or upgrading or changing the definition
of your peers
a lot of people here who are poor here
but they would be rich if they were
living in thailand and bali and if they
have the luxury of a remotely doable job
they may want to be living there
and saving up money but the ignoring the
peers is an issue because the keeping up
with the joneses is a real phenomenon
yeah envy makes the world go around
right yeah
and then there's a there's another thing
that people have to avoid even allowing
their mind to think when they're hearing
what you're saying and all this
logical fantastic advice
there's these six dirty words that's
easy for you to say yeah that is a
terrible trap i mean look i grew up as a
first generation immigrant uh in jamaica
queens uh with zero money single mom two
kids working day and night going to
school
uh you know i washed dishes uh i was k i
was working catering jobs i was mowing
lawns i was working since the age of 11
on and off here and there um
didn't have two cents to rub together
you know
i had to borrow 400 to go to college
like literally i was short 400 dollars
400. i had to find 400 i didn't have it
um you know got rejected from a job at
dunkin donuts so like okay
it's not to say that it's easy it's not
easy it's actually really freaking hard
it is the hardest thing you will do but
it's also the rewarding thing you know
look at the kids who are born rich no
meaning to their lives you're a terrible
place yeah your real your real resume is
just a cataloguing of all your suffering
right if i were to ask you to describe
your real life to yourself when you look
back on your deathbed you're going to go
back and say what are the interesting
things i've done and it's all going to
be around the sacrifices that you made
and the hard things that you did
anything you're given doesn't matter
you know you you have your four limbs
you have your brain you have your head
you have your skin that's that's all for
granted so you have to do hard things
anyway to create your own meaning in
life
um
making money is a fine one yeah struggle
it is hard i'm not gonna say it's easy
it's a really hard but the tools are all
available it's all there there's also
these these traps that people
sort of establish in their own mind
of
giving themselves excuses or giving
themselves in insurmountable
obstacles insurmountable
paths victorian victim mentality yes
it's somebody else's fault it's my skin
color's fault it's the system's fault
yeah those people are sinking i feel bad
for them i want to shake them out of it
and say actually you can get out of it
you just have to stop thinking it's
everybody you have to alter the
perspective yeah but it's so difficult
for people to do it's one of the most
difficult things for people to do is to
change the way they approach approach
reality itself
at the end of the day i i do think even
despite what i said earlier life is
really a single player game it's all
going on in your head you know whatever
you think you believe
will very much shape your reality both
from what risks you take and what
actions you perform but also just your
everyday experience of reality if you're
walking down the street and you're
judging everyone you're like i don't
like that person because their skin
color i don't like that oh she's she's
not attractive that guy's fat this
person's a loser oh who put this in my
way uh you know the more you judge the
more you're gonna separate yourself and
you'll feel good for an instant because
you'll feel good about yourself i'm
better than that but then you're gonna
feel lonely and then you're just gonna
see negativity everywhere the world just
reflects your own feelings back at you
reality is neutral
reality has no judgments to a tree
there's no concept of right or wrong or
good or bad right you're born you have a
whole set of sensory experiences and
stimulations and lights and colors and
sounds and then you die yeah and how you
choose to interpret that is up to you
you do have that choice so this is what
i meant that happiness is a choice if
you believe it's the choice then you can
start working on it and i can't tell you
how to find it because
it's your own conditionings that are
making you unhappy so you have to
uncondition yourself it's just like i
can't fix your eating habits for you can
give you some general guidelines but you
gotta go through the hard habit forming
of how to eat right but you have to
believe it's possible and it is
absolutely possible i was miserable i'm
happy as a clam it's not just the money
i got there before the money you got
happy before the money mostly yeah how
did you get happy before the money i
started getting older you know i just
realized like life is short i'm going to
die
again trite right try it in 20 ways yeah
well confucius had a great saying that
uh you know every man has two lives and
the second starts when he realizes he
has just one
wow
and i read that it was one of those book
dropping lines you know it's like mic
drop confucius had a lot of mic drops
fuchsias was a bad [ __ ] he was
that's a crazy one that was a great one
um or another one is next time you get
sick you know because everybody gets
sick every now and then it's like a
happy person
wants 10 000 things a sick person just
wants one thing
right so it's your it's your unlimited
desires that are clouding your peace
your happiness
have desires your biological creature
stands up and says i can do something i
i move i resist i live
but
just be very careful of your desires
this is the oldest most trite wisdom
desire is suffering that's what it means
right every desire you have is an access
where you will suffer so just don't
focus on more than one desire at a time
the universe is rigged in such a way
that if you just want one thing and you
focus on that you'll get it but
everything else you gotta let go
did you make a gradual shift to
happiness or was it a radical change
it's ongoing it's gradual every day so
you're happier today than you were a
month ago yeah allegedly yeah
yeah i'm i'm very happy these days
deliriously so it's actually hard for me
to hang out with normal people really
yeah so you you've made a significant
shift
over the period of like how many years
about eight years eight years yeah
wow and
is this something that you've pursued
through certain books or is it just like
you you've made an understanding or
gained an understanding in your own mind
and then started pursuing it based on
that understanding yeah it's very very
personal uh it's basically you have to
decide it's a priority and then i tried
every hack i possibly could i used to
you know i tried all the i tried
meditation i tried witnessing uh you
know i even tried an ssri just to see
what it would feel like how did it feel
uh it was it turned me from a pessimist
to an optimist but i didn't like the
physical side effects nor did i want to
be on a drug for a sustained basis
so i dropped it and i did turn you into
an optimist yes at the time i used to be
a pessimist yeah
um i started doing things like i would
start looking at the you know in every
moment and everything that happens you
can look on the bright side of something
right and so i used to do that forcibly
and then i trained it until it became
second nature so for example like a
friend of my wife's was over and she
when we were dating and she took all
these photos she took like hundreds of
photos and then she sends them all to us
and my immediate reaction was like why
are you dumping hundreds of photos of my
phone i don't need hundreds of photos
have some judgment that's my immediate
reaction and then i could say actually
how nice of her she sent me hundreds of
photos i can pick the one that i like
right there are two ways of seeing
almost everything there are a few things
that are like high suffering so you
can't do that other than just saying
well this is a teacher right but i
slowly worked through every negative
judgment that i had until i saw the
positive end now it's second nature to
me i also realized that like what you
want is you want to clear minds you want
to let go of thoughts
happy thoughts disappear out ahead
automatically very easy to let go of
them negative thoughts linger so if you
interpret then the positive and
everything very quickly you let it go
right you let it go much faster
simple hacks get more sunlight right
learn to smile more learn to hug more
these things actually release serotonin
in reverse they aren't just outward
signals of being happy they're actually
feedback loops to being happy
spend more time in nature you know these
are obvious watch your mind watch your
mind all day long watch what it does not
judge it not try to control it but you
can meditate 24 7. meditation is not a
sit down close your eyes activity
meditation is just basically watching
your own thoughts like you would watch
anything else in the outside world and
say why am i having that thought does
that serve me anymore is that
conditioning from when i was 10 years
old like for example
getting ready for this podcast you got
ready i didn't but good i did but i did
but i did i couldn't help it and what
happened was the few days leading up to
this my mind was just running and
normally my mind is pretty calm and it
was just running and running and running
and every thought i would have i would
imagine me saying it to you my brain
couldn't help but rehearse
what what it's doing it's just
rehearsing all the time to talk to you
and then i was even rehearsing rehearse
telling you about the rehearsal right so
it was all playing all these meta games
and i was just like shut up stop it what
is going on and it took me a while to
figure out oh yeah you know what it is
when i was a kid in queens and i had no
money and i had nothing and i needed to
save myself the way i got out was by
sounding smart not being smart sounding
smart that was the skill i perfected so
i am hardwired to always rehearse things
so i will sound smart it's a disease it
keeps me from being happy so but when
you see that when you realize that when
you understand something then it
naturally calms you down so after that i
stopped rehearsing as much
wow but it's still a train habit
that is a really interesting point that
you
want to sound smart
that that many people do that and
especially young people when you you see
someone who is smart or someone who
appears smart they say smart things oh
god i want to sound smart i want people
to think about me the same way i think
about that person that that is my
disease that is my feeling it is what
clutters my mind i the the thing i have
to ask myself now is
if i can
would i still be interested in learning
this thing if i couldn't ever tell
anybody about it
that's how i know it's real that's how i
know it's something i actually want to
know that's a common thing though i know
i suffered from that when i was young
the desire to sound smart
that's it's very
it's very common well all of us start
out
you know
every everything you're a winner now in
your life you were to lose because you
were a loser at some point right if if
you had gotten all the girls if you had
all the money if you had everything you
want you were good looking and in junior
high or high school uh you wouldn't have
done anything with your life
and you would have peaked early it's
like the bruce springsteen glory days
song right you would have married your
high school sweetheart you'd be living
in your hometown you know you'd be a
manager at the local mcdonald's whatever
the first dream job you had thank god we
didn't all get what we wanted when we
were young right or we would be trapped
in that so you have to be able to break
out of where you came from i don't know
where i was going that is interesting
too about people who peak too early yeah
or maybe those people that peak too
early can do the elon musk thing and
just abandon it and start something new
and then learn the the the joys of
sucking at something yeah and actually
though
in our professions especially when
you're high visibility the problem with
peaking is that you then get drowned in
death of a thousand cuts people have
expectations of you hey joe can you come
to my event hey joe can you look at my
business plan hey joe can give me advice
on this can you you know talk to my
friend can you come in this podcast
you're just being assaulted all the time
with inbound opportunities so you have
no time to start over with anything so
you have to ruthlessly ruthlessly
disappoint everybody eliminate and clear
your schedule drop all the meetings not
even respond to the emails the only way
you're gonna be able to start over with
anything
yeah and i we talked about this that i'd
love your approach to meetings
if they're not meeting life or death i'm
the same way
i avoided a good one recently and this
was someone that was just
tracking me down as a high-profile
person in a big organization and i'm
like can we just talk on the phone and
then we talk on the phone there was
nothing to say it was just they wanted
to get me in the office and yeah and the
meetings should really be phone calls
phone calls should be emails and emails
should just be text
right
many of them right with meetings i i
mean i i despise meetings i used to own
the domain i don't do coffee.com i
eventually let go but i used to respond
from the wallet i don't do coffee you
know oh that's hilarious but it was a
little bit of a jerk move but really
where it comes from is when i was young
one of my principles was i knew i had to
make money it was my overwhelming desire
and
one of the things i did was i said okay
i'm never going to be worth more than
what i think i'm worth okay no one's
going to pay me more than what i think
i'm worth so what am i worth so i i
picked an hourly rate for myself that i
was worth and i said i'm never going to
squander my time for less than this so
if
originally there's 500 bucks an hour
then i upgrade to 5000 bucks an hour and
it's ludicrous but
pick an aspirational hourly rate
aspirational it has to be a little
ludicrous and then what i would do is if
i have to return something i'm standing
in line to return something and it's
below my hourly rate i'll throw it away
if i have to if i or give it away if i
have to do some tasks and i can hire
somebody to do it for less than my
hourly rate i would hire them and so i
just became extremely jealous of my time
which doesn't mean you can't have fun
rest leisure spending time with your
friends and family that's all great
don't count that but if you're doing
anything you don't want to do which is
the definition of work it's a set of
things that you have to do that you
don't want to do if you're working it
better be for your hourly rate otherwise
don't do the work and so
once it came out of that then i just
realized the cost of meetings the cost
of meetings is so high especially given
all the people who are in there right
one person is talking seven people
listening you're literally just dying an
hour at a time
so you have to just
drop non-urgent meetings or figure out
how to be more efficient with them if
you're gonna do anything great
the extreme example is business travel
getting on a plane to fly halfway around
the world for one meeting which never
amounts to anything
and then like wasting your whole little
life there and then flying back so about
five years ago i resolved i am never
going to travel for business
wow and i haven't tried for business
since i only travel
if the travel experience will be so
entertaining and joyous because i have
friends or it's a place i want to see or
whatever that it will be complete in and
of itself because i know that whatever
the business meeting i came from is
never worth it
wow
and actually that principle applies
larger than just travel it applies to
life in general the this one of the
secrets to happiness is to really
embrace what you're doing in that moment
that's trite but where that where that
comes from is saying i only want to do
actions that are complete in and of
themselves right if i'm looking for some
ulterior motive down the line
it's not going to materialize
and and if you think it is maybe even if
it does it'll be very short-lived
anything you wanted in your life whether
it was a car or whether it was a girl or
there was money
when you got it a year later you were
back to zero your brain had hedonically
adapted to it and you were looking for
the next thing
that's a great statement hedonically
adapted
that's that is what happens to people
you get accustomed to whatever it is i
realized that when i first got a new
apartment it was a nice apartment after
a while i got used to it i was like oh
okay this is just an apartment it's just
where i live i'm used to it's nice but
i'm used to it yeah we all go through
this learning it's it's you know it's
riding the ferris wheel of life it's
like you get at the bottom like i want
to get the top this is so exciting you
ride it up you get a little dopamine
rush and get a little serotonin then you
ride it back down as that wears off then
you need another high then you ride it
back up and write it back down in fact
the more highs you get the harder it
gets to go around the wheel and the more
board you get it the harder it goes to
go back up
so what lights your fire now like what
what gets you motivated to do things and
to act art art this is art oh okay art
is just creativity it's just anything
that's done for its own sake
so what are the things that are done for
their own sake there's nothing beyond
loving somebody
uh creating something
playing
art to me creating business is play i
create businesses early stage because
it's fun because i i'm into the product
even when i invest it's because i like
the people i like hanging out with them
i learn from them and i think the
product is really cool
so these days i will pass on all kinds
of great investments because i'm like i
just the product's not interesting it's
boring i'm not gonna learn anything
that's a beautiful luxury it is a luxury
art and learning yeah it is a luxury
these are not 100 or zero things right
you can in your life start moving more
and more towards that right but that's a
goal it's a goal when i was younger i
used to be so desperate to make money
that i would have done anything right if
you'd shown up and said hey i got a
sewage trucking business and you're
going to go into that i said great let's
do it i'm going to make money
thank god no one gave me that
opportunity
i'm glad that it went down the road of
technology and science which i genuinely
enjoy
and so i got to like combine my vocation
and my advocation i mean what are you
doing you're playing you're having fun
you're doing art you're not you're not
working no that's what i always say when
people say i work hard i'm like sorta
not really i'm always working but it
looks like work to them but it feels
like play to me and that's how i know no
one can compete with me on it
because i'm just playing 16 hours a day
and if they want to compete with me and
they're going to work they're going to
lose because they're not going to do it
16 hours a day seven days a week
well listen man there are some gems of
wisdom in this conversation and i hope
people pull things out of this and apply
them to their own life and i'm certainly
going to listen to you again and and and
try to apply some of this to my own life
stuff that i'm not already applying but
i really appreciate your time and i
really appreciate you coming in here
thanks for having me and um please tell
people you those small little podcast
it's just the naval podcast right yeah
best way to find me is on twitter
actually okay just at naval then i have
a website at nav.al i have a youtube
channel neval and i have a podcast in
the world that's it well thank you very
much thank you really appreciate it
thank you
bye everybody
[Music]
[Applause]
i