[Music]
hey it's Shane Parrish and welcome to a
new episode of the knowledge project
where we deconstruct actionable
strategies that you can use to make
better decisions learn new things and
live a better life this time around we
have the amazing navall raava kaan
navall is the CEO and co-founder of
angel list he's invested in more than
100 companies including uber Twitter
Yammer and so many others don't worry
we're not going to talk about her early
stage investing involves an incredibly
deep thinker who challenges the status
quo on so many things he's thought
deeply about stuff that's near and dear
to us like reading habits
decision-making in life just a heads up
this is the longest podcast I've ever
done our conversation lasted over two
hours and if you're like me you're going
to take a lot of notes a complete list
of books and sites mentioned is
available in the show notes at Furnham
street blog.com slash podcast that's f
Arna M Street blog comm slash podcast a
transcript is available for members of
our Learning tribe if you want to join
head on over to Burnham Street blog comm
slash tribe in addition to transcripts
we have the world's best online reading
group and a host of other goodies
without further ado here's navall
before I get started here's a quick word
from our sponsor I believe in full
disclosure so I want to point out that
not only do I use this sponsor
personally for my weekly meal planning
but I'm also one of the owners me lime
is one of the most downloaded food apps
in the world everybody eats some just do
it better than others if you've ever had
trouble sticking to a diet or wandered
the grocery store endlessly with no real
menu in mind meal one gets you organized
with quick and easy meals matched up to
your personal dietary preferences just
pick the recipes for the week Uline
builds you a shopping list with all the
ingredients you need and helps you cook
once you try it you'll see it's crazy to
grocery shop any other way you save time
and money reduce stress and eat well
download the free meal I'm app for your
Android or iPhone or check them out on
the web at Milan comm that's MEA al I M
e-comm develop welcome to the show I am
so excited to get to talk to you today
and you know ask you a whole bunch of
questions that I have on my mind oh
thanks for having me I'm excited to be
here I've been a longtime fan of your
work thank you let's get started with
something simple can you tell me a
little bit about what you do it's
actually not that simple I have a hard
time saying what I do my day job is that
I am CEO of angel list the company that
I started almost seven years of though
now an angel this is sort of this
platform for startups in the tech
industry and we help entrepreneurs raise
money we help entrepreneurs recruit
talent into their startups and we also
help people find jobs into startups and
now recently we acquired producthunt so
we also help companies launch to
customers so it's basically a one-stop
shop for the early-stage tech ecosystem
whether you're raising money or you're
investing money with the largest online
platform for that whether you're
recruiting Talent or whether you're
being recruited with large online
platform for startup recruiting and then
whether you're looking for a new product
to try out or whether they're looking
for customers for your product we're
also the largest online platform for
launching that so it's sort of become
this this bigger thing and that's sort
of my day job but I'm also involved in a
bunch of other things I mean
Buster pushed lien about 200 companies
advisor to a bunch and a bunch of boards
occasionally belonging tweet I'm also a
small partner and a cryptocurrency fund
because I'm really into these coins that
Bitcoin athelia Minzy cash and so forth
and I'm always cooking up something you
always have a bunch of side projects
that I forget I hate you keep track of
that all like what is your typical day
look like well that's the good part I
don't have a typical day in or do I want
a typical day you know if there is a
typical day I'm usually inside my office
at angellist but I'm basically just
operating mostly on email or phone or
meetings or or squirreled up at home so
there are days where I just work
completely from home their day that I
don't work I'm actually even trying to
get rid of this concept of having to be
in a specific place at a specific time
you know all I care about is am i doing
what I want to do and being productive
and am I happy and I really want to
break away from this idea of 40 hour
weeks or 60 hour weeks with 80 hour
weeks or nine-to-five or roles or jobs
or identities it just all feels like a
straitjacket you're one of the best four
ratios readers I know you've called
yourself a conscious bookworm and you've
read a ton how did you first get
interested in reading reading was my
first love you know I know that in my
childhood when I was around 9 10 11
years old I was a latchkey chick my mom
was working multiple jobs and then she
was going to school at night we were
raised by a single mother my brother and
I were in New York City and we were in a
part of New York City that has been very
safe
so I basically the library was my was my
after-school center so effort and come
back from school I just go straight to
the library and I just hang out there
until they closed and then I'd come home
so that was just my daily routine but I
think even by that point in time I'd
already loved books I was reading books
the child I remember my grandparents
house in India I'd be a little kid on
the floor going through all of my
grandfather's readers digests which is
just all year to read there I mean now
of course there's a smorgasbord of
information out there everybody can read
anything all the time but back then it
was much more limited so I would read
comic books every Reader's Digest I
would
storybooks you know whatever we can get
my hands on mysteries I was big into
mysteries so I think I just always love
to read because I've actually antisocial
introverted and I was just lost in the
world of words and ideas from an early
age I think some of it comes from the
happy circumstance that when I was young
nobody forced me on what to read I think
there's a tendency among parents and
teachers to say oh you should read this
but don't read that the reality is that
it's read a lot that by today's
standards would be considered mental
junk food but eventually you just get to
like reading you run out of the junk
food and then you start eating the
healthy food all right oh your taste
kind of gradually so I think to some
extent that's what happened with me
because I started from comic books and
then went from that into mysteries and
went from that into fantasy that the
sci-fi and then from science by
admitting to science and then
mathematics and then philosophy so it
just kind of kept climbing up the stack
but I'm lucky that there was no one
around when I was seven years old or 16
saying oh you shouldn't read that you
should be dissing stuff it's most of
what you read today physical or on a
computer or Kindle for convenience it's
mostly Kindle it's not the Kindle device
it sucks on an iPad and but for books
that I really really like I will also
buy a physical copy so I have books so
there's no excuse not to read it you
know a really good book cost 10 or 20
dollars and can change your life in a
meaningful way so it's not something I
believe in saving money on and this was
even back when I was broken I had no
money I always spend money on books I
never viewed that as an expense that's
an investment to me and I probably spend
ten times as much money on books as I
actually get through so in other words
it's like for every two hundred dollars
worth of books i buy actually end up
making it to ten percent so I'll read 20
dollars worth of books but it's still
absolutely worth it
you and I in common yeah and anything
that's one of the grapes like if I read
a book and I know that it's amazing I'll
buy multiple copies partially to give
away partially because I have the volume
around the house and these days I find
myself reading as much or more as I do
read
because I think this was a tweet from an
account on on Twitter that I saw this
guy illah service and he basically said
you know I don't want to read everything
I just wanna read the 100 great books
over and over again and I think there's
a lot to that so it's really more about
identifying what are the great books to
you because different books speak to
different people and then really
absorbing those because I don't know
about you but I don't I have very poor
attention I have to you know I scare my
speed-read I jump around and I could not
tell you specific passages or quotes
from books but I but if some deep level
you do absorb them and they become part
of the threads of the tapestry of your
psyche so they do kind of weave in there
there are there are books that I'm sure
you've had this feeling where you pick
up a book you start reading like oh this
is pretty interesting this is pretty
good and you're getting this increasing
sense of deja vu and then about
two-thirds or half way through the book
you realize over this book before and
that's perfectly fine it means you were
ready to reread it what are the books
you're rereading new good question I'll
pull up my Kindle app as we talk but
usually I'm always reading some books
and science like I just reread a 7 brief
lessons in physics I think that was the
name of it
I read that one at least twice I'm
rereading sapiens again I love that book
so much I'm pretty much always reading
we reading something by either Jiddu
Krishnamurti or Osho those are kind of
my favorite for other philosophers I'm
reading a book on Rene Girard mimetic
theory it's more of an overview book
because I couldn't make it to his actual
writings I'm reading tools for tightened
tools of tightness Tim Ferriss is
somebody Brooke of what he's learned
from a lot of gay performers I'm
rereading stories of your life and
others by Ted Chiang it's one of my
favorite sci-fi novels I'm reading a
book on called thermal info complexity
it's actually by a friend of mine it's
not published yet I just finished
reading pre suasion
or I should say I finished giving
persuasion Robert Kennedy I don't think
I needed to read the entire book to get
the point but it was still good to read
it to me but I did
I recently reread the lessons of
streep I will in Ariel Durant it's a
great little look true bug yeah I am
currently reading a story of philosophy
also by will Doron I have a young kid
now so I've got a lot of child rated
books that I use more as reference
material than anything else recently
read so Emerson Chesterfield you've got
a Leo Tolstoy book here I've got another
Osho book of a delusion damage or since
blog that I use in love I have pieces of
it saved up Alan Watts see Scott Adams I
reread cards debris recently doubt
etching a friend of mine is rereading it
so I picked it up again
there's tons maybe just go out and hunt
little von mises book here there's a the
undercover economist the Richard Bach
book there's some Jed McKenna books
I was recently trying to reread Moby
Dick and Hamlet just to try and get back
into fiction but I didn't make it to
either why do you set aside time in your
day to reread or like to read it all or
is it like a consistent thing or do you
fit it in when you have time I read what
I'm bored of everything else but the
good news is I get bored very easily so
there's always a book to capture the
imagination usually at night time before
I go to bed ugly but it's not it's not a
flawless thing when I'm on vacation I'll
read but if I'm sitting in a lifter and
uber of read sometimes in the morning at
home after I've worked out I'll just
read sometimes when I wake up I'll just
grab my phone and read I just I don't
set I'm not a very disciplined person so
I don't really set these hard fast rules
for myself because I'm but the good news
is I just love to read and because I
love to read I whenever I'm bored and I
have time I just do it and thanks to the
the iPhone and the Kindle and the iPad
you know they just make it really easy
oh I've got two books here in Fineman
perfectly reasonable deviations is by
him and then genius which is the J
McCloy book about fine men so this is
they're talking I'm flipping
human-looking more evolution of
everything when Matt Ridley is one of my
favorite authors I read everything that
there's reread everything that there's
little Dale Carnegie in here the
three-body problem man's search for
meaning
there's lots sexy dawn and a lot of
books out there you can tell sounds like
my dream well I'm going to right now
it's hundreds and hundreds and hundreds
of books are downloaded it's not even
like I mean we could sit here the entire
podcast I do you like people you've said
before you think of books as throwaways
how did you come to think about books
like that and what impact has that had
on what you read I mean that's really an
impact of the internet once the internet
came along I think it's destroyed
everybody's attention span because now
all of humanity's works are available to
you at any given time and you're being
interrupted constantly so just our
attention span goes down or bit of focus
goes down but at the same time we just
become more judicious we also want we
want the meat and the the problem with
books is that to write a book to publish
it publish a physical dead tree book
just takes a lot of work and effort and
money so sometimes people start putting
long wrapping long books around simple
ideas those are probably my least
favorite books it's kind of why I avoid
the whole business and self-help
category because you generally have one
good idea and it's buried in hundreds or
thousands of pages and lots of anecdotes
so what happened was I just noticed that
sometime in the late 90s I stopped
reading as much as I used to and I
started reading more blogs that's a
reading less bugs and more blogs and
great blogs like Farnum Street you know
Kevin similars blog melting asphalt and
so on you you get incredibly smart
people die justifying simplifying and
and writing these great things but it's
only a page or two or three pages so I
got really into blogs but then I'd
stopped reading books and a lot of the
oldest wisdom is actually in books and
with books you're now talking about it
combined works of all of humanity as
opposed to just who happens to be
blogging right now so I realized I
missed that and then with the Kindle and
iBooks coming along that allowed me to
start treating books like I treat blogs
which is when I go to a blog I'll
actually skim through lots of articles
until I find one that looks really
interesting I'll read that whole article
all the way to do it maybe take notes so
now I treat books the same way which is
I'll skim through a large number of
books I'll put
down I'll jump around back forward
middle until I find a part that's
interesting I'll just consume that piece
and I won't feel guilty about having to
finish the entire book because there's a
view and it's a blog archive right it's
like a like a blog might have 300 posts
on it and you can read just 235 that you
need right now
and I think you can think of a book the
same way and then that opens the world
and web of books back open to us instead
of it being buried somewhere I think you
know like many people I know of a lot of
friends who are currently stuck on a
book somewhere and if you ask people if
they read everybody says they read
everybody says they're reading a book
they can answer which book they're
reading the reality is very few people
actually read and actually finished
books yeah and I think yeah and I think
that's probably because of all these
societal and personal rules that we've
put up like you must finish a book and
you must read books that are good for
you and you can't read junk food books
and this is the hot book right now and
so on the reality is I don't actually
read that much compared to what people
think like the reason I probably read
one to two hours a day which and that
puts me in the top point oh one percent
I think that alone accounts for any
material success that I've had in my
life and the intelligence that I might
have because real people don't read an
hour a day real people I think read a
minute a day or less so making it an
actual habit is the most important thing
and how you make it a habit doesn't
matter it's very much like exercise of
working out do something every day it
almost doesn't matter what you do so the
people who are obsessing over like
should I be weight training or should I
be doing tennis or should I be doing
Pilates or I should I be doing the
high-intensity training method versus
the happy body which is whatever they're
missing the point the important thing is
to do something every day it doesn't
matter what it is so the same way I
would argue the important thing is to
read every day and it's not it doesn't
matter it almost doesn't matter what you
read because eventually they'll read
enough things and and your interest will
lead you there that will dramatically
improve your life so just like the best
workout for you is the one that you're
excited enough to do every day the same
way I would say the best books to read
are the ones that
books or blogs or Twitter or whatever
anything with ideas and information and
learning the best wants to read it are
the ones that you're excited about
reading all the time this the people
that I knew that read quite a bit that
they have a reading habit like you
you're described is a very visual person
where did that come from oh then I might
have come from the Tim Ferriss podcast I
I don't think I'm more habitual anybody
else I think human beings are entirely
creatures of habit you know as a young
children were born with no habit loops
they're essentially born as blank slates
and then they habituate themselves the
thing to learn patterns and they get
conditioned and they use that to get to
everyday life and habits are good you
know habits can allow you to background
process certain things so that your your
neocortex your form your frontal lobe
stays available to solve brand-new
problems but we also unconsciously pick
up habits in the background and we keep
them for decades and we may not realize
that they're bad for us so we're going
to move on from them to some extent
you know our attitude in life our mood
our happiness levels depression levels
these are also habits do we judge people
how often do we eat what kinds of food
do we eat do we walk or do we sit do we
move do we exercise do we read these are
habits as well and we you absolutely
need habits to function you cannot solve
every problem in life as if it's the
first time what's thrown at you but but
what we do is we accumulate all these
habits we put them in the bundle of
identity ego ourselves and then we get
attached to that I'm Shane this is the
way I am I'm the ball this is the way I
am and it's really important to be able
to uncondition yourself to be able to
take your habits apart and say okay well
that's that's a habit that I probably
picked up from when I was a toddler and
I was trying to get my parents attention
and now I'm just reinforced it and
reinforced it and reinforced it and I
call it part of my density but is it
serving me anymore is it making me
happier is it make me healthier they're
making me accomplish whatever I want to
set out to accomplish right now so I
don't think I'm anymore in fact I would
argue am less habitual than most people
like I don't like to structure my day
but to the extent that I do have habits
I'm trying to make them more deliberate
rather
accidents of history so what's a habit
that you're trying to change right now
what are you working on well IIIi did a
lot of habit changes over the last few
years so I've now got a daily workout
that I do which is a great habit I cut
down heavily on drinking it's not fully
eliminated but it's mostly gone
I dropped caffeine I'm not on the Paleo
diet although elected II so I'm at a
variation of it that I call the Paleo
diet which is I try to be paleo but I
fail to constantly but I don't beat
myself up over it because I feel that
even approximating towards it is better
than where I have been historically so
you know like that I tried to build a
meditation habit but i but I failed but
I have made a habit of being meditative
so I've gone through lots of habits
probably the one that I'm currently
would like to cultivate is doing yoga
more regularly but I haven't really I
haven't formed a plan around that and by
the way I reject a lot of the stuff
that's the peddled around today about
how you perform in break habits I know
there's this very popular book one that
I even recommended which talks about the
science behind habits and one of its
depression conclusions I think this came
out of Stanford but that you can't break
habits you can only replace them and
that's BS I've definitely broken habits
completely and so I think you can
uncondition yourself you can't untrained
yourself it's just hard so it just takes
work it takes effort and usually the big
habit changes come when they're strong
desire motivators attached to them so
the you know the yoga one I'm gonna work
on I don't yet have a great plan on that
one I haven't tackle that one properly
yet a big habit that I'm working on
which is gonna be really hard to explain
in any way that any normal human being
will understand this but I'm trying to
turn off my monkey mind that's I like I
think we are when we were born as
children were pretty blank slates we're
living very much in the moment and we're
essentially just reacting to our
environment through our instincts and
we're living in what I would call the
real world and then when puberty comes
along that's the onset of desire it's
the first time you really really want
something and you start long-range
planning for it and then because of that
you
start thinking a lot and start building
an identity and ego to go and get what
you want and this is all normal and
healthy it's part of being the human
animal but I think at some point it gets
out of control
and then we are constantly just talking
to ourselves in our heads we're playing
little movies in our heads walking down
the street but no one's actually there
now of course we started voicing this
thought in your head that you're always
having you'd be a man man and then lock
you up but the reality is if you walk
down the street no 2,000 people in the
street I think all thousand are talking
to themselves and their head at any
given point they're constantly judging
everything that they see they're playing
back movies of things that happened to
them yesterday they're living in fantasy
worlds of what's gonna happen tomorrow
and they're just holed out of base
reality and that could be good when
you're doing long-range planning you can
be good when you're solving problems
it's good for the survival and
replication machines that we are but I
think it's actually very bad for your
happiness and so in my mind the mind
should be a servant their tool my master
it's not something that should be
controlling me and driving me 24/7 so
I've taken on this idea that I want to
break the habit of uncontrolled thinking
which is hard because the five sanity
you don't think of a pink elephant I
just put a pink elephant in your head so
it's it's it's an almost impossible
problem so it's more something that has
to be guided by feel than guided by
actual thinking or thought process but
I'm deliberately cultivating experiences
states of mind locations activities that
will help me get out of my mind and I
know you know all a society does that to
some extent in some sense the people
chasing thrills and action sports or
flow States or orgasm or any of these
states that people really strive to get
to a lot of these are basically just
trying to get out of your own head
they're trying to get away from that
voice in your head and this
overdeveloped sense of self and their
very least i do not want my sense of
self to continue to develop and become
stronger as I get older I want it to be
weaker and more muted so that I can live
much more impressive everyday reality
and accept nature and the world for what
it is and appreciate it very much
I would and then not have to seek
happiness through external circumstances
chasing two fits a preconceived notion
that I have while there's a lot that I
want to ask questions on is there yeah
that's really a tough one that'll take
years that's that's not a six month
habit doesn't end your habit do you
think there's a difference between
turning off or subversive suppressing
your monkey mind absolutely
yeah suppression doesn't work because
when you try to suppress that's the mind
suppressing the mind that's just you
playing games with yourself so I think
it's it I think it's a very hard problem
and I want to go back to kind of
unconditional you you basically stop
drinking alcohol how did how did you
work on deep programming yourself form
from the social settings and
environments that you're in where
alcohol is probably available all the
time and what benefits have you seen as
a result of like are you isolating these
habits when you're changing them so you
know oh I sleep better because I'm not
yeah you know it'd be the alcohol one is
an interesting case study because the
alcohol have it came from two things one
was availability just being in
situations where alcohol is available
and accepted and something you're
supposed to do and then the second is
the the desire right you want to do it
because you're trying to accomplish
something else so when I unpacked that I
realize a couple of things the
availability came from I'm just out if
I'm out at night in an environment where
alcohol is being served that's the
availability so if you want to avoid
that stay in not staying in is not fun
so what do you do well I started this
daily workout regimen in the mornings if
you're working out in the mornings and
you can't stay up too late at night he
can't stay up too late at night you
can't be drinking too much you screw up
a few times and your morning work that
is terrible you have a headache you feel
bad you don't feel as and when you're
working out every day you can checkpoint
yourself very easily like oh well this
exact thing that I do every single
morning is suddenly harder so therefore
I'm weakened from the alcohol from last
night so the morning workout checkpoint
really helped me understand the
consequences of consuming alcohol before
and then the more interesting question
is well why am i doing it and that's
basically boiled down to I was doing it
to survive longer in social environment
that I wasn't particularly happy in I
essentially had the stun
my brain into submission so there are
better ways to do that one of those is
only associate with people where you
don't have to drink to be around them
and that really narrowed my friend
circle and narrowed the kind of events
that I go to there's a little bit of a
substitution effect and some of what the
substitution effect was I was drinking
so that I wouldn't be thinking because
and so what I went back to is like what
can i cultivate these states of not
thinking too much and if I can get there
another way then that will take away
some of the urge to drink and then
there's some substitution for example a
switch from hard alcohol to red wine and
red wine is inherently self-limiting you
know know you have two cocktails the
next thing you want is another cocktail
you have two glasses of red wine at
least for me I usually have a headache
so I'm done at that point it's very
self-limiting but some of it is this
function of age I mean I'm 42 B now I
don't know I can make it through a
single glass of wine without having some
negative consequence build-up so I still
I still drink I don't I don't believe in
the words like never and always because
I think that's that's a way of limiting
yourself and self-discipline yourself
makes you less free and less happy at
some level but I just want to be
naturally in a position where I don't
need it and I don't desire it it's about
kind of what I've been working more on
what happened would you say most
positively impacts your life
I think it's the daily morning workout
that has been a complete game-changer
it's made me feel healthier younger it's
made me not go out late and it came from
one simple thing which is everybody says
I don't have time right basically
whenever you throw any so-called good
habit at somebody they'll have any
excuse for themselves and usually the
most common is I don't have time and I
don't have time it's just another way of
saying it's not a priority so what you
really have to do to say is it a
priority or not and if something is your
number-one priority
then you will get it that's just the way
life works but if you've got a fuzzy
basket of ten or fifteen different
priorities you're gonna end up getting
none of them so what I did there was I
basically just said my number one
priority in life above my happiness
above my family
above my work is my own health and it
starts with my physical health and then
second is my mental health and then
third is my spiritual health and then
it's my family's health that is my
family's well-being and then after that
I can go out and do whatever I need to
do the rest of the world so there's a
series of concentric circles starting
out from me and so because my physical
health became my number one priority
then I could never say I don't have time
so in the mornings I just work out and
however long it takes is how long it
takes and I do not start my day and I
don't care if the world is imploding and
melting down taking wait a minute 30
minutes until I'm done working out and
do you take any breaks from that or is
that everyday it's pretty much every day
there are a few days where I've had to
take a break because I'm traveling or
I'm injured or sick or something but I
can count on one hand the number of
breaks I take every year you mentioned
happiness being one of your top
priorities what is happiness to you it
what does that mean what does that word
mean can you unpack that yeah it's a
very evolving thing I think like all the
great questions you know when you open
you're a little kid and you go to your
mom and you say what happens when we die
is there Santa Claus there God should I
be happy you know who should I marry
those kinds of things there are no glib
answers to that because there are no
there are no answers that apply to
everybody so these these questions the
search for truth you know these kinds of
questions they ultimately do have
answers but they have personal answers
so the answer that works for me is gonna
be nonsense to you and vice versa
so whatever happiness means to me it
means something different to you and it
means something different to the
listener but I think it's very important
to explore what it is and for some
people I know it's a flow state for some
people satisfaction for some people it's
a feeling of contentment the best my
definition keeps evolving so the answer
to giving you a year ago been different
than what I tell you now but today I
believe that happiness is it's really a
default state it was there when you
remove the sense that something is
missing in your life and we are highly
judgmental survival and replication
machines we're constantly walking around
thinking I need this I need that trapped
in the weather because
and happiness is that state when nothing
is missing and when nothing is missing
your mind shuts down and your mind stops
running into the future or running into
the past they regret something or to
plan something and then in that absence
for a moment you have internal silence
and when you have internal silence then
you are content and you're happy
I think people believe mistakenly you
know feel free to disagree because again
it's different for everybody but people
believe mistakenly that happiness is
about positive thoughts and positive
actions but the more I read the more
I've learned the more of experience
because I verify this for myself every
positive thought essentially holds
within a negative thought it's a
contrast to something negative the
daodejing says it's more articulately
than I ever could but it's all it's all
duality and polarities so if I say I'm
happy that means that I was sad at some
point if I say he's attractive and that
means that somebody else is unattractive
so every positive thought even has a
seed of a negative thought within it and
vice versa which is why a lot of
greatness and life comes out of
suffering you have to view the negative
before you can aspire to and then
appreciate the positive so all that said
long-winded to me happiness is not about
positive thoughts and stuff but not
about negative thoughts it's about the
absence of desire especially absence and
desire for external things and so the
fewer desires I can have the happier I
can order more than except the current
state of things the less my mind is
moving because the mind really exists in
motion towards the future of the past
the more present I am the happier and
more content I will be but if I latch on
to that if I say oh I'm happy now and I
want to stay happy then I'm going to
drop out of that happiness because now
suddenly the mind is moving is trying to
attach to something it's trying to
create a permanent situation out of a
temporary situation so happiness to me
is mainly not suffering not desiring not
thinking too much about the future in
the past really embracing the present
moment and the reality of what is the
way it is because nature has no concept
of happiness or unhappiness to a tree
there is no right or wrong there is no
good or bad
you know nature follows unbroken
mathematical laws and a chain of cause
and effect from the Big Bang to now and
everything is perfect exactly the way it
is it's only in our particular minds
that we're unhappy you're not happy and
things are perfect or imperfect because
of what we desire but I think I've also
come to believe in the complete and
utter insignificance of the self and I
think that helps a lot like for example
if you thought you were the most
important thing in the universe then you
have to bend the entire universe to your
will because if you're the most
important thing in the universe then how
could it not conform to your desires and
if it doesn't conform to your desire
something's wrong however if you view
yourself as a material and amoeba
or if you view all of your works as
riding on water or building castles in
the sand then you have no expectation
from how life should actually be life
it's just the way it is and then you
sort of accept that and you have no
cause to be happy or unhappy those
things almost don't apply and what
you're left with in that neutral state
is not neutrality I think people think
oh that would be a very bland existence
no this is the existence the little
children live and if you look at little
children on balance they're generally
pretty happy because they're really
immersed into the environment in the
moment without any thought of how it
should be given their personal
preferences and desires so I think the
neutral state is actually a perfection
state and one can be very happy as long
as one isn't too caught up in their own
heads
what is your internal monologue go like
when you find yourself of trying to
attach to something by default
yeah I try to keep an eye on my internal
monologue it doesn't always work but in
the in the computer programming sense I
try to run my brain in debugging mode as
much as possible and when I'm talking to
someone like I'm talking to you right
now or when I'm engaged in a grouped
activity it's almost impossible because
your brain has too many things to handle
but if I'm by myself like just this
morning you know I'm brushing my teeth
and I starts thinking forward to the
podcast and I started going to this
little fantasy where I imagine you
asking me a bunch of questions and I was
fantasy answering them and then I caught
myself I put my brain in debug mode and
just watch every little instruction go
by and I said why am i fantasy future
planning why can't I just stand here and
brush my teeth
right and it's just just the awareness
that my brain was running off in the
future in planning some fantasy scenario
out of ego that that I was like well do
I really care if I embarrass myself in
Shane's podcast who cares I want to die
anyway this is not gonna go to 0 and I
won't remember anything pointless so at
that point I shut down I went back to
brushing my teeth and then I was
noticing how great the toothbrush was
and how good it felt
and then next moment I'm off to thinking
something else and then I think that
look at my brain again say do I really
need to solve this problem right now and
the reality of that 95% of what my brain
runs it off and tries to do I don't need
to tackle at that exact moment
in fact if it's like a muscle then I'll
be better off resting it being at peace
and then when the particular problem
arises immersed myself in it so what I
would rather dedicate myself to is for
example right now as we're talking to be
completely lost in the conversation and
to be 100% focused on this as opposed to
thinking about oh when I brush my teeth
didn't do it the right way or you know
planning something else in my mind so I
think the ability to singularly focus is
related to the ability to lose yourself
and be present happy and actually
ironically more effective that's fast
and it's almost like a relativity issue
or you're taking yourself out of a
certain frame and you're just moving
over to another frame and watching
things from a different perspective even
in that you're in your own mind yeah I
think that a lot of the things have a
like Buddha stalk about is awareness
versus the Eco what they're really
talking about is you can you can think
of your brain your consciousness as a
multi-layered mechanism and there's kind
of a core base kernel-level
OS that's running and then there's
applications that are running on top and
I like to think of it as you know
computer geek speek I'm actually going
back to my awareness level OS which is
always calm all is peaceful and
generally happy and content and I'm
trying to stay in that mode and not
activate the monkey mind which is always
worried and frightened and anxious but
serves incredible purpose but I'm trying
not to activate that program until I
need it because when I need it
I want to just focus on that program but
if I'm running it 24/7 all the time I'm
wasting energy
and it's just it and it becomes me and I
am more than that right I think like
another thing that spirituality or
religion or Buddhism or any anything you
follow will teach you over time is that
you are more than just your mind you are
more than just your habits you're more
than just your preferences you're your
level of awareness you're a body and you
know modern humans we don't live enough
in our body we don't live enough in our
awareness we live too much in this
internal monologue in our heads all of
which by the way is just programmed into
you by society and by and by the
environment from a newer younger you're
basically a bunch of hardware DNA
written that then reacted to
environmental effects when you were
younger then you recorded the things
that were good and bad and we use that
to prejudge everything that's gonna be
thrown against you and then you're using
that to constantly try and predict and
change the future but as you get older
and older the some of these preferences
that you've accumulated it's very very
large there's some of these reactions
habitual reactions that you that it's
very very large and then they end up as
runaway freight trains that control your
mood well we should control our own
moods
why don't we study how to control our
moods what a masterful thing that would
be if you could say well right now I
would like to be in a curious state and
then you can genuinely set yourself into
the curious state or you say I want to
be in a mourning state I'm mourning a
loved one and I want to grieve for them
but I really want to grieve I really
want to feel that I don't to be
distracted right now by mad computer
programming problem let's do tomorrow so
I think that the mind itself is a muscle
and it can be trained and it can be
conditioned it has just been haphazardly
conditioned by society out of our
control
and if you look at it with awareness and
intent and it's 24/7 job you're working
at every moment of every day I think you
can unpack your own mind and your
emotions and your thoughts and your
reactions you start reconfiguring you
can start rewriting this program to what
you want you mentioned before one of
your interviews that you have
foundational values but you didn't
elaborate when so I'm curious what are
those yeah it's a
question I've never actually listed them
or articulated them but to define values
first of all as a set of things that you
will not compromise on upon so
foundational values to me are things
that I've looked at very very carefully
about myself and I've deliberately
chosen and said you know what this is a
habit this is a way of life and I'm not
gonna compromise that I'm going to stay
this way forever I just don't want to
live life any other way now I've never
fully enumerated them but you know
examples of them like I think honesty is
a core core core value to give you
examples of what I mean by honesty is I
want to be able to just be me I don't
want to I never want to be in an
environment around people who have to
watch what I say because if I disconnect
what I'm thinking from what I'm saying
that creates multiple threads in my mind
that means that I'm no longer in the
moment that means that I now have to
work future planning or past regretting
every time I'm talking to somebody so
anyone around whom I can't be fully
honest I don't want to be around another
example of foundational value is I don't
believe in any short-term thinking or
dealing so if I see anybody who's even
around me like let's say I'm doing
business with somebody and they think in
a short-term manner with somebody else
then I don't want to do business with
that person anymore because I think all
the benefits in life come from compound
interests whether in money or in
relationships or love or health or
activities or habits so I only want to
be around people that I know I'm going
to be around with for the rest of my
life and I only want to work on things
that I know have good long-term payout
another one is like I only believe in
pure relationships I don't believe in a
hierarchical relationship so I don't
want to be above anybody another one be
below anybody if I can't treat someone
like a peer and if they can't treat me
like a peer then we have then I just
don't wanna interact with that human
another one is I don't believe in anger
anymore
I mean that was something that was good
when I was young and for testosterone
but now I was like the Buddhist saying
that anger is a hot coal that you hold
in your hand while we do it at somebody
so you know I want to be angry and I
want to be around angry people so I just
cut them out of my life
and I'm not judging them I mean I went
through a lot of angular2 and so you
know they have to work through it on
their own but go be angry at someone
else
else so i don't know if that nestle
falls into the classical definition of
value but it's a set of things that i
won't compromise on and that i just
lived my entire life by and I think
everybody has values and a lot of
finding great relationships great
co-workers great lovers wives husbands
is finding other people where your
values just line up and then the little
things don't matter generally I find
that if people are fighting or
quarreling about something it's because
their values don't line up their values
lined up the little thing wouldn't
matter how is radical honesty like how
radical is your honesty and how is that
kind of impacted your life I mean it's
pretty honest I'm not like I think Ray
Dalio from Bridgewater is same as
theoretically honest so I'm not gonna go
and call somebody ugly to their face
like I'm not trying to make a big show
of it and they're trying to say hey I'm
so honest and I'm gonna shock you what
what radical honesty just means that I I
want to be free part of being free means
that I can say what I think and think
what I say they're highly congruent and
integrated and it also means you know
Richard Fineman famously said you should
never ever fool anybody and you were the
easiest person to fool
so the moment you tell somebody else
something that's not honest you've lied
to yourself and then you'll start
believing your own lie and then that
will disconnect you from reality and
take you down the wrong road so it's
really important for me to be honest but
I don't go out of my way
volunteering negative or nasty things I
would combine radical honesty with an
old rule that Warren Buffett has which
is pretty specifically criticized
generally and I try to follow this I
don't always follow it but you know I
think I followed enough that it made a
difference in my life
which is if you have a criticism of
someone then don't criticize the person
criticize the general approach or
criticize kind of that class of
activities but if you have to praise
somebody then always try and find the
person who best who's the best example
of what you're praising and praise that
person specifically and that way
people's egos and identities which we
all have don't work against you they
work for you having
values changed at all or have you given
more thought to them since becoming
married and becoming a parent
I mean how has that changed you values
almost by definition don't change that
much over time but they take some it
takes some time for you to figure out
your own foundational values I think
everybody has them it's just that maybe
we're not that aware of them until later
and so mine have changed a little bit
but not a lot I mean my love my wife is
an incredibly loving family-oriented
person and so I and so that was one of
the foundational values that brought us
together the moment you have a child
it's this really weird thing but it's
sort of it answers the built-in meaning
of life's purpose of life question all
of a sudden the most important thing in
the universe and moves from being in
your body and to being moving into the
child's body so that that changes you
and your values inherently become a lot
less selfish you know I would say that
like probably the biggest such change
was when I was younger I really really
really valued freedom freedom was one of
my core core values and ironically it
still is it's probably one of my top
three values but it's a different
definition of freedom did my old
definition was freedom to freedom to do
anything I want freedom to do whatever I
feel like whenever I feel like and now I
would say that the freedom but I'm
looking for is internal freedom so it's
freedom from its freedom from reaction
it's freedom from feeling angry it's
freedom from being sad it's freedom from
being forced to do things but I'm
looking for freedom from internally and
externally whereas before I was looking
for freedom - I like that a lot what's
the the biggest mistake you've ever made
in your life and how did you recover
I've made a class of mistakes that I
would summarize in the same way and I
made this Clapp mistakes and it was
obvious to me looking to mistakes we're
only in hindsight through one exercise
which is you probably heard the you know
when you're thirty what advice would you
give your 20 year old self
yeah I mean you're 40 like what advice
would you give your twenty or thirty
year old self so if you do that exercise
decade by decade or maybe if you younger
you can do it in five really sit down
and say
okay you know 2007 what was I doing how
was I feeling 2008 what was I doing how
was I feeling 2009 or was a-doing how
was I feeling and at least for me that's
remarkable consistency emerged and that
consistency was that everything that I
was doing I should have still done but
with less emotion and especially less
anger because I used to be very angry
when I was younger but especially it's
less emotion life is gonna play out the
way it's gonna play out some good some
bad but most of it is actually just up
to your interpretation and you're born
you have a set of sensor experiences
then he died and how you choose to
interpret those sensory inputs is up to
you and different people interpret them
in different ways but really I wish I
had done all of this things but with
less emotion and less anger like the
most celebrated example would be you
know when I was younger I started a
company and the company did well but I
didn't do what else I suit some of the
people involved and it was a good
outcome for me in the end and everything
worked out okay but there was a lot of
angst and a lot of anger and really
today you know what I would do is I
wouldn't go down the angst in the anger
I would have just walked up to the
people and said look this is what
happened this is what I'm gonna do this
is I'm gonna do it this is what's fair
this is what's not but I would have
realized that the anger and the emotion
themselves have this huge consequence
it's just completely unnecessary so now
I'm just trying to learn from that and
to do the same things that I think are
the right thing to do but to do them
without anger and to do them with a very
long term point of view so I think if
you take a very long term point of view
and if you take the emotion out of it
then I wouldn't consider those things
mistakes anymore other than that I mean
there was a you know the perspective I
like to adopt is that everything that I
did and everything that was done to me
and you know there's some impossible to
separate combination brought me to this
exact moment here today talking to you
and this is a good moment surf the gram
or whatever so whatever set of
circumstances conspired to bring us here
we're good because here I am was there a
moment you would say when you realize
that you could control how you interpret
it I mean I think what
the problems that a lot of people have
is they don't recognize that they can
control not what happens to them per se
but how they respond and how they
interpret a situation I think everyone
knows it's possible and the reason we
know it's possible is there's a great
osha lecture that he calls the title the
attraction of drugs and spiritual it
talks about what do people do drugs
everything from alcohol psychedelics to
cannabis so you name it
and they're doing it to control their
mental state and they're doing it to
control how they react and sometimes
it's worse and sometimes it's better but
some people drink because then they
don't care as much or they they're
potheads because they can zone out or
they do psychedelics so they can feel
you know very present or connected to
nature or what have you but the
attraction of drugs are spiritual so to
some extent we already know that we can
control our internal state we just use
external bioactive substances to do it
and now there are a lot more techniques
that are out there the public domain
many of them dug up from older times but
you know these ones from cognitive
therapy and behavioral psychology to
meditation to taking a long walks in
nature you can control your mental state
it's just we're used to doing it by
hacking our external circumstances to
then come back around and control our
mental state and for example sitting on
a there's a famous line that says that
all of man's problems arise because he
can't sit by himself in a room for 30
minutes plaster women - yeah exactly so
you know if a man or a woman can sit by
themselves on a cushion for thirty
minutes and that's hard it's really hard
to do that's meditation you are
essentially struggling with in
controlling your internal state and the
first thing the first thing to realize
is that you can actually observe your
mental state so just the advantage of
meditation is not that you're something
gonna gain a superpower to control their
internal state it's that you will
recognize just how out of control your
mind is it is like a monkey flinging
faeces that's running around the room
making trouble shouting breaking things
it's completely uncontrollable it's an
out-of-control mad person and you have
to see this mad creature in operation
before you feel a certain distaste
towards it and you start
separating yourself from it and in that
separation is liberation when you
realize that oh I don't want to be that
person why am I so out of control just
that awareness alone calms you down so
there are there are many techniques one
can use another one example that I think
a lot of smart people say is if your aim
about something or if you get an unhappy
email and you want to respond don't
respond for 24 hours right what does
that do it just you're you calm down
you're the emotions subside the hormones
go down and your mental stir in a better
mental state 24 hours later so I think
people already know this but we just
don't act on it because socially we're
not conditioned to act on socially we're
told go work out go look good because
that's a multiplayer competitive game
other people can see if I'm doing a good
job or not or we told go make money go
buy a big house again
external multiplayer competitive game
but when it comes to learn to be happy
train yourself to be happy completely
internal no external progress no
external validation 100% you're
competing against yourself single player
again and we're such social creatures
we're more like bees or ants that were
externally programmed and driven that we
just don't know how to play and win at
these single-player games anymore we
compete purely on multiplayer games but
the reality is life is a single-player
game you're born alone you're gonna die
alone all your interpretations are alone
all your memories are alone and you're
gone three generations nobody cares
before you showed up nobody cared it's
all single-player I think Buffett has a
great example of that when he gives the
do you want to be the world's best lover
and known as the worst or the world's
worst lover and known as the best in
reference to an inner or external score
current exactly right I mean all of your
scorecards are internal and the sad
thing is you know we sit there like
jealousy jealousy was a very hard
emotion for me to overcome when I was
young I had a lot of jealousy in me and
by and by you know I learned to get rid
of it and it still crops up every now
and then but it's such a poisonous
emotion because at the end of the day
you're no better off you're unhappy and
the person you're jealous of is still
successful or good-looking or whatever
they are
but the the real breakthrough was for me
was when I realized at a personal
fundamental level I mean I the problem
with these kinds of podcasts is I can
get glib answers all day long but you
have to discover your own personal
answer because your personal answers
gonna be different than mine I'll speak
to you but the one that I discovered
that spoke to me was a day I realized
that all these people that I was jealous
of I couldn't just cherry pick and
choose a little aspects of their life I
couldn't say I want his body I want her
money
I want his personality you have to be
that person do you want to actually be
that person with all of their reactions
their desire their family their
happiness level their outlook on life
their self-image and if you're not
willing to do a wholesale 24/7 hundred
percent swap with who that person is
then there's no point in being jealous I
think that's and so I got it once I came
to that realization jealousy just sort
of faded away because I don't want to be
anybody else I'm perfectly happy being
me and by the way even that is under
control to be happy being it's just
there's no social rewards for it but
there's a lot of internal rewards yeah
there's it's almost anti-social rewards
because when you're when you're working
on your inner stuff people don't love
that it's not they don't dislike it your
friends of course support you but
they're not getting anything out of it
and even when I look at my own peer
group and to the extent that they're
working on themselves and everyone their
forties at some level is most ever
engaged in grouped activities hey let's
do a group meditation hey listen this
group of that hey let's thought of this
group lecture and I keep coming back to
this one line that I read like
everything I just read but which was
said only the individual transcends
nobody reaches enlightenment or soar or
internal happiness or does serious
internal work in group settings it is a
very lonely kind of task so to some
extent I think that people who are
constantly looking for social
affirmation in their internal work
aren't that serious about it what they
did and it's fine I'm not judging but
just they're craving more social
interaction than they're really craving
internal work
what big ideas have you changed your
mind on in the last few years
there's a lot on kind of a life's level
there's a couple obviously in the
business level I think on a more
practical basis I just stopped believing
in macroeconomics thinking that Gregor I
studied I studied economics in school
and computer science and there the time
when I thought I was gonna go be a a PhD
in economics and all that but the
further I get the more I realize micro
economics the combination of hoodoos
complex systems and politics and you can
find macro economist to take every side
of every argument so I think that
discipline because it doesn't make
falsifiable predictions which is the
hallmark of science because it doesn't
make falsifiable predictions it's become
corrupted because you never have the
counter example on the economy you know
you can never take the US economy and
run two different experiments at the
same time and because there's so much
data people kind of cherry-pick or
whatever political narrative they're
trying to push so to the extent that
people spend all their time watching the
macro economy or you know the Fed
forecasts or you know which way the
stocks are gonna go to the next year
it's gonna be a good year of value
that's all junk it's no better than
astrology in fact it's probably even
worse there's less entertaining it's
more stress inducing so I just think of
macroeconomics now junk science and all
apologies the macro economists that said
micro economics and game theory are
fundamental I don't think you can be
successful in business or even
navigating through most of our modern
capitalist society without an extremely
good understanding of supply and demand
and labor versus capital and game theory
and tit for tat and those kinds of
things so that but macroeconomics in the
religion that I gave up but there are
many others I mean I've changed my mind
on death on the nature of life on the
purpose of life on marriage you know I
was originally that's someone want to be
married and have kids so there have been
a lot of fundamental changes but the
most practical one is I gave up macro
and I embrace micro and I would say
that's just not true in macro economics
that's true in everything I don't
believe in macro environmentalism I
believe in micro environmentalism I
don't believe in macro charity I believe
in micro charity I don't believe in
macro improving the world
there's a lot of people out there who
get really fired up about gonna change
the world I'm gonna change this person
will change the way people think I think
about micro it's like change yourself
then maybe change your family and your
neighbor before you get into abstract
concepts about it and change the world
well part of your your base knowledge
that you have today that you believe do
you consider the least solid or most
likely to change over the coming years
good question I mean I try not to have
too much that I've pre decided upon I
think that creating identities and
labels locks you and it keeps you from
seeing the truth so I used to identify
as libertarian but then I have to find
myself defending positions that you know
I hadn't really thought through just
because they're a part of libertarian
Canon and the reality is that if all of
your beliefs line up into ten neat
little bundles you should be highly
suspicious because they're pre packaged
and put together so I don't like the
self identify and almost any level
anyone that keeps me from having too
many of these so-called stable beliefs
so it's hard for me to point to
something that I think is shaky because
if I thought it was really shaky then
then I wouldn't I wouldn't stand on it I
guess the the the areas were in becoming
least certain is kind of all the I
called the grande category of how should
we organize society beliefs everybody
has them you know some people think we
should be communists some people are
capitalist some are an RTS some say we
need a larger welfare state we need
universal health care and basic income
and others say no we needs it all I
think the entire class of beliefs
they're unfalsifiable they're based
they're almost religious you know there
are things that people got into when
they were young nobody actually knows
which system is the better one nobody
actually knows which one maximize
happiness versus output which is
whatever I know there's a lot of smart
economists and people studying it
there's a lot of good data and science
but the end of the day I just and the
more I look into it the more I come away
saying well maybe I don't know how best
to organize society maybe Society you
know should not have just one
organization but should have multiple
organizations so you can choose you can
go into which our society where you were
most bound to thrive
but I don't think there is a single
right answer for human culture in
society anymore except to the extent
that given the increasingly destructive
or technology you know along a timescale
a longer time scale you can 3d print a
nuclear weapon long a time scale you can
create a singularity in your backyard
it's part of your high school physics
project so I think as a human race we do
have to sort of get past this idea of
that we're separate organisms and kind
of almost getting some kind of a
multicellular organism situation
otherwise we'll just destroy ourselves
it'll just be too easy to blow ourselves
up and that obviously runs very very
counter to my libertarian instincts of
everyone should be free and whatever
they want cetera et cetera
so I just don't know how to organize
society anymore and I think any beliefs
that I have any remnant beliefs that I
have from being younger about the
optimal way to octave to only high
society probably wrong and the future
thriving society that we end up with
maybe a thousand years from now will
probably look like something that I
would argue very strongly against today
because they will have no room for the
individual maybe you can explain for
listeners the singularity and kind of
what your thoughts are around that yeah
the singularity is this idea that
technological change is accelerating and
at some point the acceleration gets so
great that there's massive change in our
lifetimes we create things like general
AI we start living forever and just the
the nature of who we are as humans
change the consequence of that it's most
associated with a general AI we produce
a general purpose artificial
intelligence that artificial
intelligence could then hack its own
code make itself smarter and out of all
of us the point where we are either
obsolete or immortal or something in
between my thoughts I I think it's
fanciful to say the least
Nick Bostrom wrote a very famous book
called super intelligence which lays out
the past did it there are good rebuttals
to super intelligence so I wouldn't just
read that book you know breathless and
wide-eyed and believe everything and
there are people like in a singularity
Institute who are looking forward to
this coming but I I think is religion
for nerds you know it's got all the same
characteristics it's unfalsifiable until
it happens it basically says the chosen
we'll be saved the world's gonna end you
know we will be immortal it's very hard
exactly it's very hard to part from a
biblical kind of story and I find the
people who are pushing it the most or
what I would call sort of armchair
technologists like they might understand
a little bit of science but these are
not the PhDs in physics who are pushing
this it's not like though fields
medal-winning mathematicians pushing
this you know I was trained and a little
bit of science and I consider myself an
amateur scientist and I know just enough
to know how little we know
you know physics still can't solve the
three-body problem collide three
billiard balls together can't tell you
what happens we cannot properly model
complex systems we can't tell the
weather next week
we still can't solve the vast majority
of chronic diseases we're just starting
to connect the gut and the brain and
bacteria in our system together there is
so much complexity in nature and humans
have just begun to scratch the surface
that to believe that we are going to
sort of go into this world of perfection
through technology I think it's
far-fetched look there's an AI
everyone's talking about AI none of
these people have written real code we
are no closer to creating a general AI I
think that we were twenty years ago now
there are actual huge advances that were
made specific AI but these are data
processing problems basically if I dump
huge amounts of real-world images into a
neural network then I can do better
image recognition no question that is
real that is a data-driven solution the
algorithms haven't gotten any better and
a structure of how the human brain works
and how the human body works is still so
far advanced beyond our machine
capabilities that certainly if there's
gonna be singularity it's not gonna
happen in my lifetime and I think in
that sense some things like the
singularity are pernicious their
pernicious for the same reason that the
afterlife is pernicious because it takes
you out of the moment it gives you hope
for the future so you stop living for
today and you start living for tomorrow
and I know that doesn't sound like much
but it's actually a big deal any given
time when you're walking down the street
a very small percentage your brain is
focused on the present the rest is
future planning or a great
passed and that's keeping you from an
incredible experience it's keeping you
from seeing the beauty and everything
and for being grateful for where you are
and I think it can literally destroy
your happiness if you spend all your
time living in delusions of the future
so I do think the singularity thing is
good in the sense that it pushes forward
technological advancement we put more
resources on it we spend more time
develop and some of the great things
that the human race that so the great
technologies we're gonna take advantage
of so in that's an agent and pushes
science forward is a good thing but I
think it's delusional to think that
you're somehow gonna be saved before you
die but it's some combination of AI and
magic science you just have to live the
life you have that's pretty profound
even when you're you're living backwards
you're not really living right you kind
of have to be in the moment to have any
sort there is nothing there there is
actually nothing but this moment you
know one has never gone back in time and
no one has ever been able to predict the
future successfully in any way that
matters and so literally the only thing
that exists is this exact point where
you are in space at that exact time that
you happen to be and it's like all the
great profound truths it's all paradoxes
so any two points are infinitely
different any moment is perfectly unique
but that moment itself slips by so
quickly that you can't grab it what's
your opinion on the current education
system when I ask people on Twitter what
they wanted to ask you this question
came up a couple times which was you
know how would you fix it what's your
opinion on the education system what are
your thoughts are on that I think
there's no question it's completely
obsolete the education system is a path
dependent outcome from the need for day
care from the need for prisons for
college aged males who would otherwise
overrun society and cause a lot of havoc
the original medieval universities had
guard towers that face inwards for
example yeah because you you have to put
a curfew in there and you can lock up
the young 18 year old males before they
go out with swords and daggers and you
know create trouble so call it a college
and schools and what were the way we
think about them they come from a time
period when books were rare knowledge
was rare
babysitting was rare crime was common
violence was prevalent there was no such
self-guided learning so I think schools
are just byproducts at these kinds of
institutions and now we have the
internet which is the greatest level of
knowledge ever created completely
interconnected so it's very very easy to
learn if you actually have the desire to
learn everything is on the Internet
you can go on Khan Academy get MIT and
Yale lectures online you can get all the
coursework and get interactivity you can
read blogs by brilliant people you can
read all these great books so it's so
the ability to learn the the means of
learning the tools of learning are
abundant and infinite it's a desire to
learn that's incredibly scarce so I just
don't think that schools matter for
self-motivated students but the schools
matter for is wanted to keep the kids
that are the parents here while the
parents that'll work
it creates socialization because kids
want to be around their peers and they
want to learn how to operate society of
their peers but I think if it's purely
learning you're after that learning can
be done much more either on your own or
through the internet or by uniting
through the internet with like-minded
groups so I think that's one problem
with the current educational system the
second problem is what do you choose to
learn and the current educational system
has to have a one-size-fits-all model
has to say well you have to learn X now
and then you have to learn why and you
know to give you examples of witnesses
obsolete memorization right in a day and
age of Google and smartphones
memorization is absolutely why should
you be memorizing the Battle of
Trafalgar why should be memorizing what
the capital of this or that state is but
we still put undue weight on that just
because that's the way it's always been
done and we did a pre Google world
another example is how when we're moving
along at a certain pace I'm sure not
everyone but I'm certain 90% of your
listeners have had this happen to them
which is they were learning mathematics
and at some point they were they were
keeping up they were doing arithmetic
than they were doing geometry
trigonometry do they precalc them in the
account and somewhere in there they got
lost somewhere in there while building
the massive edifice a logical structure
that mathematics is they missed one
lesson they missed one concept in this
five classes or they just didn't they
just
brain couldn't think a certain way that
something was being explained to them
and should have been explained visually
but it was being explained numerically
or it should have been explicit
symbolically and it was being explained
in cartography but what have you but
they were not able to keep up and the
moment you lose that rung in mathematics
normally you miss that rung in the
ladder you can't go to the next one
because not on the next one the teachers
like okay we're done with precalculus
and now we're moving on a calculus
you're saying wait I didn't understand
precalculus and I understand how
precalculus leads from trigonometry to
calculus and missed that whole part so
now I get the calculus you don't
understand the fundamentals and now you
reduced it memorization so now I got
okay dxdy when I see that symbol I do
this yeah but now you've lost the actual
learning you've lost the connection to
the underlying principles if so I think
learning should be about learning the
basics in all the fields I'm learning
them really well over and over because
life is mostly about applying the basics
and only doing the advanced stuff in
things that you truly love and where you
understand the basics inside out but
that's not how our system is built we
teach all these kids calculus and they
walk out not understanding calculus at
all when really they would have been
better off serve just doing arithmetic
and basic computer programming the
entire time so I think there's a there's
a pace of learning issue and then
there's finally a what to learn and
there's a whole set of things we don't
even bother trying to teach we don't
teach nutrition we don't teach cooking
we don't teach how to be in happy
positive relationships we don't teach
how to keep your body healthy and fit
you know we just say sports we don't
teach happiness we don't teach
meditation
maybe we shouldn't teach some of these
things is different kids will have
different aptitudes but maybe we should
maybe we should teach practical
construction of technology and and you
know like maybe everyone in their
science project instead of building a
little chemistry volcano maybe it should
be building a smartphone so we just
haven't kept up and I have to believe
that we can change the system but we're
not but you never you never change a
system by taking the existing thing and
reworking it I don't believe a bit of
certain value in tech business
enough to know that you're better off
changing it just by creating something
brand new
so one fantasy idea I've had is you know
after I'm done with angellist or if I
have more time in my hands I would like
to create a successor to the One Laptop
project in MIT Nicholas Negroponte he
had they one laptop per child project
but then I saw this fascinating right up
this is really long time ago maybe in
five years ago maybe it was in the
Economist or somewhere it was a story
about how they left a box full of
unopened Android tablets in a little
village in Pakistan and when they came
back months later the kids have opened
at the Box they've all figured out and
booted the tablets they're hacked them
they've gotten passed through the user
administration login they've installed a
whole bunch of apps they've got a little
economy set up the older kids are
teaching the younger kids they're
teaching their grandmothers how to run
businesses they're surfing the web
they've taught themselves in English you
know kids are learning Sheens they just
need the tools so to that end what I
would love to do is create a very
low-cost very rugged easily powered
cheap Android tablet that's hard to
destroy and basically distribute them
around the world with pre-built learning
applications so that you can literally
fire one up and it works with you
interactively in 30 seconds that figures
out what language do you speak you know
if any you're going to speed symbolic
and what level of aptitude are you at or
your second grade or third grade fifth
grader and of course invariance by a
different discipline and then lets you
dive into and let you learn anything you
want that will make your life better
just don't think about is my original
patent see exactly and it always keeps
you on the edge and always keeps pushing
you and then you can network in all the
teachers of the world so anyone who
wants to be teachers and contributes not
just Salman Khan building Kahn Academy
but essentially you could Network
connect all the teachers of the world
and all the students of the world using
tablets and do it at a pace and level
where it's essentially customized for
each child and they're learning the
things that have a practical outcome in
their life I know there's advantage to
liberal arts education pushing things
that people aren't gonna sleep on to
learn on their own but they have to have
some desire for it it's better to wait
until they're think they're ready and
then give it all
because I think that's the way that
learning sticks so that that's the kind
of project I like to work on but I don't
I don't think it's solvable with the
current school system I hope you get a
chance to work on that I think that'd be
a phenomenal impact to the world yeah I
think I think it would be fun and I'm
thinking about this now more because I
have a young kid sided honestly I don't
want to send in this cool how do you as
an era I mean you mentioned a couple of
physics books in in the start of the the
interview here how do you as an adult go
about learning new subjects you
specifically in yeah mostly I just stay
on the basics so even when I'm learning
physics or science I'm sticking to the
basics so I'll read concepts for fun but
I'm more likely to you know do something
that is arithmetic in it than calculus
I'm not going to be a great fit at this
point maybe in the next lifetime or when
my kid will be like but it's too late
for me so I have to stick to what I
enjoy and what I love about science is
mathematics is the language of nature
sciences to me the study of truth it is
the only true discipline because it
makes falsifiable predictions actually
changes the world and applied science
becomes technology and technology is
what separates us from the animals and
allows us to have things like cell
phones houses and cars and eat
electricity so science to me the study
of truth and mathematics is the language
of science and nature so in that sense
I'm not religious but I'm spiritual and
to me that is the most devotional thing
that I could do to study the laws in the
universe and so the same kick that you
know some guy might get out of being in
Mecca or Medina and you know bowing to
you know the Prophet I get that same
feeling of awe and that same small sense
of self when I study science so for me
it's you know it's it's unparalleled and
I'd rather stay at the basics and start
at the and this is the beauty of reading
so one thing I don't like to do by the
way when I do my books on the Kindle I
skip two thirds of them and the reason I
skipped two thirds is because they're
kind of embarrassing they won't sound
like good books you read they'll sound
like trivial or silly or
whatever but who cares I mean I don't
have to tell everybody everything I read
I read all kinds of stuff that other
people consider chunk or even
reprehensible I read all kinds of stuff
that I disagree with because of mind
bender yeah I found myself and some
random dark hole in Twitter the other
day where I was reading this guy's
tweets like wow he's really smart
I was really interesting I was very
clever the queen of it this guy the
full-blown white supremacist I mean he's
not even like mildly a white supremacist
he just thinks like everyone in the
white race should be guarding people
like me shouldn't be allowed on the
streets but it was still fascinating and
he's still really smart and I can't
reading it and I read it and read it
read it after a while I built up my own
sense of his coherent view of the world
and where he was coming from but to do
that I couldn't have judged too much and
I'm certainly not gonna go around
bragging to my friend hey I learned this
from a white supremacist the other day
right so to some level you almost have
to read the stuff you're reading because
you're into it and that's it if you
don't need any other reason there's no
there's no mission here to accomplish
yeah just really because you enjoy it if
you read what everybody else is reading
I mean there's wisdom that you're gonna
think what everybody else is thinking so
you need the diversity and almost like
an index fund approach right where
you're gonna catch the winners but you
can't really identify a lot of them
beforehand that are gonna change you as
a person because so much about is
contextual yeah I think almost
everything that people read these days
is designed for social approval hmm you
know all the bestsellers are about
social improvements social conditioning
if you really want it to be successful
happy blah blah blah all those external
metrics you're looking for a non average
outcome and so you can't be reading the
average thing to your point and all
these things are actually old as the
hills you can go read Adam Smith from
The Wealth of Nations you go read
Benjamin Franklin and his aphorisms
understand how to live your life you
could read Charlie Munger you could read
you could read Charles Darwin understand
evolution the source you could read
Watson and Crick understand structure
double helix and DNA but instead what we
choose to read are just you know
whatever is number one at the airport
bestseller or whatever if friends are
reading or we read I know people who
have read a hundred regurgitated books
of evolution and they've never read
Arwen or they've they've got or taking
the number of macroeconomists they're
out there I think this is most of them
who have read tons of treatises in
economics that haven't read any Adams
net yeah okay so at some level you're
doing it for social approval you're
doing it to fit in with the other
monkey's you're fitting to get along
with a herd but that's not where the
returns are in life the returns in life
are being out of the herd social
approval incent inside the herd so if
you want social approval definitely go
read what the herd is reading but it
takes a level of contrarian ISM and
saying no I'm just gonna do my own thing
regardless of the social outcome to
learn anything I think that's
interesting do you think there's some
sort of loss aversion there because once
you diverge you're pushing out say
there's a Gaussian distribution you're
pushing it to one of the tails and if
you feel that you're gonna lose out on
that you would rather just stay in the
middle if there's a chance that you're
not gonna be in the in the fat tail for
a positive absolutely I think that's
what the smartest and most successful
people I know started out as losers
if you view yourself as a loser as
someone who's been cast up by society
and has no role in almost a society then
you will do your own thing and you're
much more likely to find a winning path
so it helps to start up by saying oh I'm
never going to be popular and I'm gonna
be accepted I'm already a loser I'm not
gonna get but all the other kids have
I'm just gotta be happy being yeah I
think that's true um when you're reading
do you just readin it sticks in your
head or is it more like you take notes
to have a system for how you keep track
of that or review them I'm both lazy and
I'm really focused on being present so I
think taking notes is the same as taking
photos when you're on a trip all this
doing is taking you out of the moment
and then who really sits there you know
years later and goes back and looks at
all their trip photos and gets nostalgic
just go take your next trip okay so I
just don't believe in anything from the
past
anything no memories no regrets no
people no trips nothing because a lot of
our unhappiness also comes from
comparing things from the past to the
present
first time you saw a sunset it was
amazing was jaw-dropping you forgot
yourself the second time you saw it is
cool you know the hundredth time you say
it's nothing a thousand times you're
saying it someone shows you a sunset
you're like well actually I saw this one
sunset in Mexico this time that was
really cool
you're not even there so I just don't
believe in clinging too much to memories
and that includes in reading so I I do a
highlight I catch myself doing that but
I do it more because it's just kind of a
way of rereading and rereading that
particular paragraph at that moment in
time and then once in a blue moon for my
especially favorite books I want to
reread the book but I'll be short on
time so I'll just read the highlighted
passages until something catches my eye
and then I got sucked back into the book
but the reality is I could stop
highlighting tomorrow and it would make
no difference and note-taking is even I
think harder than that so I do not take
notes but everyone's brain works
differently now some people love to take
notes
actually my note-taking is Twitter so
what I do is I really read read and if I
have some fundament haha insight or
concept then what I like about Twitter
is it forces me to distill that into 140
characters and then I try and put it out
there as an aphorism and then I get
attacked by all kinds of random people
and the point on all kinds of obvious
exceptions and jump down my throat like
why do I do this again you have one of
the most thoughtful Twitter feeds that I
know of so I don't I hope nobody jumps
down your throat too bad there thank you
yeah when you first pick up a book are
you skimming for something interesting
like how do you go about reading it or
do you just flip to a random page and
start reading or what's your process for
that yeah I'll start at the beginning
but I'll move fast so if it's not
interesting I'll just start looking
ahead
I'll start skimming or speed reading if
it doesn't grab my attention within the
first chapter and a meaningfully
positive way I'll either drop the book
or I'll skip ahead a few chapters I
don't believe in delayed gratification
when there's an infinite number of books
after their read there's so many great
books and there's so many of them that
are so well written that you know it
just can't spend my time on these one
thing I will do those if I find that
early on in the book the author starts
making statements that I think are just
factually untrue and one should always
be open to new ideas but if they're
starting to make contradictions were the
epistemological load of acknowledging
that contradict sorry use that 50 cent
word but they just just I would have to
read
my entire lifetime of learning and undo
it and start over the truest yeah yeah
exactly or like you know I had a very a
conversation recently with a guy who
sounded really really smart and was
throwing all kinds of science at me and
my head was spinning and then he
basically said and as we know you know
thermodynamics isn't really true it's
fundamental so the undo by yeah that is
not even a theory it's a law it comes
from the mathematics so that out then we
just have to we have no basic
conversation so if I find something like
that in a book which someone says oh yes
I cleared my mind and I watched my
thought process then I was able to
levitate then I have to put the book
down because now I don't know what is
true and what is false basically what
I'm looking for it is the author
knowingly lying or completely deluded if
they are then I can't fill my brain with
that junk because I can't separate truth
from fiction
so generally I'll skim I'll fast forward
I'll try and find a part that catches me
usually though what happens in most
books those most books have one point to
make and obviously nonfiction not time
my fiction but they have one point to
make they make it and then they give you
example after example after example
after example and they apply it to
explain everything in the world and you
once I feel like I've gotten the gist of
it I feel very comfortable putting the
book down so there's a lot of these what
I would call it pseudoscience
bestsellers that are all over you know
everyone's always meeting and people
like oh did you read this book and I
would say yes but the reality is I read
maybe two chapters of it but I got the
gist I want to switch gears and talk a
little bit about decision making which
is kind of what you get paid to do both
as an investor and the CEO of angellist
you're kind of paid to be right when
other people are wrong do you have a
process or and how you make decisions
yeah so decision-making is everything
and in fact someone who makes decisions
right 80% of time so 70% of time will be
valued and compensate in the market
hundreds of times more and I think
people have a hard time understanding
that but that's a fundamental fact of
leverage if I'm managing a billion
dollar
and I'm right you know 10% more of the
time than somebody else and that's a
hundred million dollars worth of value
on a judgment call and with modern
technology and large workforces and
capital our decisions getting leverage
more and more so if you can be more
right more rational and that's one of
the reasons why I love your blog because
it's really focuses on helping you be
more right better decision make them
more rational then you're going to just
get nonlinear returns in your life so
decision making is everything and
decision making what what was going on
we're basically what the brain is a
memory prediction machine out of the
memory of things that work in the past
and what it's red and it's trying to
predict the future and a lousy way to do
memory prediction is X happen in the
past therefore X will happen in the
future it's - based on specific
circumstances so what you want is you
want principle you want mental models so
the best mental model that I have found
have come through evolution game theory
and Charlie Munger who I'm sure you
quote a lot on your blog but Charlie
Munger was Warren Buffett's partner very
good investor but he's tons and tons of
great mental models Nassim Taleb has
great mental models the Benjamin
Franklin had great mental models so I
basically load my head full of mental
models but then different ones apply to
every situation so I don't really run a
checklist but for example I stayed a lot
of complexity theory when I was younger
it's a it's a feel that I got into I got
and occasionally just getting these
things that I just learned a lot about
that field and my most recent ones
cryptography but I was really into into
complexity theory back in the mid 90s
and the more I got into it the more I
understand the limits of our knowledge
and the limits of our prediction
capability and that's been super helpful
to me so that has helped me come to the
system that operates in the face of
ignorance and I believe that
fundamentally we are ignorant and very
very bad at predict in the future so I
don't look for and I I don't believe
that I have the ability to say what is
going to work so rather than what I try
to do is I try to eliminate what
not going to work so I think being
successful is just about not making
mistakes it's not about you know having
correct judgments it's about avoiding
the incorrect judgments so I have mental
models around how do I determine if I
can trust somebody around you know what
what are the actual odds this is gonna
work how much margin of safety do I have
if it works out you know the angel bets
and venture bets are great because
they've mehlman your outcome in the
positive but on the downside you can
only lose 1 X but on the upside you can
make 10,000 X so I tried to rig the game
so I don't believe in specific goals
it's got out i'ma see also set of
systems my goals so use your judgement
to figure out what kinds of environments
you can thrive in and then build a
system to create that environment around
you that you're statistically likely to
succeed I don't going to be the most
successful person on the planet nor do I
want to be I just want to be the most
successful version of me while working
the least hard possible right I want to
be in a thousand universes navall is
successful 999 there that he's not a
billionaire but you know he's done
pretty well in all of this right
so whatever the metric is or he's
happily married in most of them he may
not have you know nailed it in every
regard but he's set up systems such that
he's failed in very few places so so
basically I just try and set up good
systems and then the individual
decisions aren't that don't don't matter
that much because I think our ability to
make individual decisions is actually
not great so for example an investor I
would rather invest I would rather my
system is I want to see 10,000 companies
and I want to pick 500 that have a shot
of being huge and then I want the option
to double down in the five winners I
don't want to just look at a hundred
companies and pick ten that I think are
winners and go all-in on those right
because I don't think I had that
capability and I think there's a lot of
ex post facto reasoning and and sort of
origin stories that people make up about
why they were successful but the real
separation here is you look at which
people are consistently successful
especially in Silicon Valley there are
lots of one-hit
but how many people consistently seems
to do something interesting build
something interesting make money and do
something new I'm not I'm not in this to
make money money is just a piece of
paper and every time I see one of these
building our founders you know giving
away to a hospital or whatever you know
they overshot they didn't need that much
money so there's a huge diminishing
returns the money after a certain point
especially now that I'm going to freedom
from rather than freedom to their thing
all I do that I can't do so literally
money in that sense is a boat anchor
around my neck because it is something
that I've been fearful of losing
something I'm getting it jealousy
debates about so many people want from
me so I'm not even in for the money it's
like can I do something interesting and
new can I create something brand new the
world has never seen that it gets value
out of that it uses that it's congruent
with my morals so I never had problems
sleeping at night and I never have to
worry about selling something that I
wouldn't buy so much more into that but
I don't I don't have a checklist system
for decision making I know that's like a
big thing recently
Atul Gawande wrote the checklist
manifesto and there's good for pilots
and surgeons I don't think it's
necessarily great for investors or he
totally misses the decision-making I
agree and by the way that's another one
of those books where you just read the
first chapter and you're done it a great
blog post but yeah so III also don't
think you need to be that hard on
yourself right a lot of a lot of what
goes on today a lot of your listeners
right or right now like beating
themselves up and scribbling notes and
saying I need to do this and you can do
that no you don't need to do anything
you know all you should do is what you
want to do and if you stop trying to
figure out how to do things the way
other people want you to do them then
you get to listen to that little voice
inside of your head that wants to do
things a certain way and then you get to
be you and no one in the world is gonna
beat you at being you you're never gonna
be as good at being me as I am and I'm
never gonna be as good at you being you
as you are so certainly listen absorb
but don't try and emulate it's a fool's
errand instead each person is uniquely
qualified of something they have some
specific knowledge capability and desire
that nobody else
that's just purely from the
combinatorial of human DNA and
development and so because so your goal
in life is to find out the people who
need you the most to find out the
business that needs you the most to find
out the project in the art that gives
you the most because there's something
out there just for you but what you
don't want to do is be building
checklist and decision frameworks built
on what other people are because you're
never going to be there you'll never be
good at being somebody else yeah and
you're inevitably gonna miss stuff too
and checklist you mentioned kind of like
how you determine if you can trust
somebody and I know you said in the past
these kind of used buffets criteria for
evaluating people which is the
combination of intelligence energy and
integrity
what purchase it what predictive signals
do you pay attention to for each how do
you determine if you can trust someone a
large part of you just the hardest one
yeah integrity is the hardest one and
integrity is a it usually comes out in
two ways one is long term which is just
you've known somebody for a while and
you kind of know you know how to think
about things but the most the more
interesting one and there's a short-term
one which is just kind of see how they
treat other people so there are lots and
lots of people who will you know not
screw over square root is a strong word
but they will do something that is self
feeling or slightly unethical relative
to another business partner when the
whole time bails they'll say to you
tonight and I should wink wink I you
know I'm taking advantage that person
cuz they deserve it but you're my friend
I would never do that to you and the
thing is yeah exactly it's very easy to
change your definition of who friends
are yeah I find the people who really do
it things out of integrity they have an
internal moral compass so they don't
they don't do unfair or unethical or bad
deals with other people because it would
soil their own view of themselves and
they wouldn't be able to sleep with
themselves at night so some of the
highest integrity people I know the
worst thing you can do is you consider
them well I think yourself feeling on
that one and they will get so unhappy
because they'll be like oh no no no
that's not who I am I can't be that
person and they'll bend over backwards
yeah usually I find that people that are
negotiated with who are high integrity
deal they're very easy to negotiate with
they'll give you things that they don't
need to give you because they think it's
fair
vice versa so negotiations with high
integrity people are usually very easy
giving each other things to make sure
the other person is happy enough the
deal survives because unhappy deal get
unwound and they become short-term
relationships which don't have any
compounding benefits and then finally if
someone is going around and talking
about how honest they are they're
probably dishonest just like a little
telltale indicator I've learned when
someone spends too much time talking
about their own values or talking
themselves up they're covering for
something so there's actually a good
book it's kind of out of print I think
it's hard to track down maybe find it
online somewhere and it's not the
obvious one the name of the book is
called the art of manipulation and I
found it because of a tweet that I
followed from illah service and it was
really good it was because the sky
basically goes undercover that lives
with con men and he spends time with him
running cons and learning all about cons
and he's just very without judgment he
just lays down how con con men work and
he puts down there how to spot them when
they're being dishonest and some of the
tell-tale signs are they will they'll
push the deal a little bit too hard
they'll sell just a little bit too hard
they'll talk about how honest they are
but I have great people in my life who
are extremely successful very desirable
like everybody wants to be their friend
very smart and yet I've seen them do one
or two things that are slightly not
great to other people and the first time
I'll tell them I'll go but I'll say hey
look I don't I don't think you should do
that to that other person not because
you won't get away with it you will get
away with it but because it'll hurt you
in the end not in some cosmic karma kind
of way but just I believe that deep down
we all know who we are
mm-hmm you cannot hide anything from
yourself and so your own failures are
written within your psyche and they're
obvious to you and so if you have too
many of these moral shortcomings you
will not respect yourself and the worst
the worst outcome in this world is not
having self-esteem if you don't love
yourself who will so I think that you
just have to be very careful about doing
things that you were fundamentally not
going to be proud of because they will
damage you so the first time around I
warned them by the way nobody changes
and then I just kind of distance myself
from that it sort of you know cut them
out of my life but guy I just had this
saying inside my head
The Closer you want to get to me the
better your values have to be example
lament like yeah when I met my wife it
was a great test because I really wanted
to be with her and she wasn't so sure at
the beginning and so in the end we ended
up together because she saw my values
and I'm lucky I had developed them by
that point because if I hadn't I
wouldn't have gotten her not that I own
her anything there's no attachment like
that but but I wouldn't have deserved
her that's like as Charlie Munger says
to find a worthy mates be worthy of a
worthy mate so I think it you know
working on your values is long-term
selfish although a short-term it's
absolutely involved sacrifices if being
ethical were profitable everybody would
do it you wouldn't have to have a
separate concept you want to talk about
it there would be no books on it there'd
be no no one would ever tell my values
gonna be profitable but it's not it's
obviously unprofitable involves
sacrifices but like everything in life
if you're willing to make the short-term
sacrifice you'll have the long-term
benefit my physical trainer Jersey
Gregory really wise brilliant guy he
always says you know easy choices hard
life hard choices easy life so basically
if you're making the hard choices right
now and what to eat
you're not eating all the junk food you
want mean the heart tries to work out
then your life long-term will be easy
you won't be sick you won't be unhealthy
I'm saying is true of value same is true
of saving up for a rainy day save it's
true of how you approach your
relationships but if you make the easy
choices right now your overall Mike will
be a lot harder I like that I want to
dive into intelligence a little bit
there - like how do you separate the
people who know what they're talking
about from these people who pretend they
know what they're doing I mean we're
full of a world where it's so easy to
pretend you have knowledge that you
don't actually have real knowledge is
intrinsic and that and it's built on the
ground up so going back to my math
example earlier you can understand
trigonometry without saying arithmetic
or geometry so basically someone is
using a lot of fancy words
and a lot of big concepts they probably
don't know what they're talking about I
think the smartest people can explain
things to a child and if you can't
explain to a child and you don't know it
and I think that's very true and at the
common saying but Richard Fineman you
know very famously if you go into his
lecture six Easy Pieces where his early
physics lectures he has one where he
basically explains mathematics and three
pages he starts from number line
counting and then he goes all the way to
precalculus and he just builds it up
through an unbroken chain of logic
he doesn't rely on any definitions you
know for example if somebody says like
oh that bird is called this or you know
the rule for this thing is that they're
not very telling you they fundamentally
tell you about humans they're telling
you about naming systems true
understanding
it's about algorithms about
understanding how things connect to each
other so if I think if the mark of a
charlatan to try and explain simple
things in complicated ways as the mark
of a genius to explain complicated
things and simple ways so really they
should be able to do it very very very
very simply and I have to catch myself
on this because I have a big vocabulary
because I read a lot so I can sound
smarter than I am just by using big
words but in the process I'm being
dishonest with myself it's ok to use
more precise words you know English is a
big language with a lot of words and so
that allows for a lot of precision but
if you're deliberately using words that
your audience doesn't know or if you
even think you're using a word that your
audience doesn't know and you don't
catch yourself and correct that then
you're essentially being dishonest
you're just trying to show off you're
trying to pull one over their eyes
there's a great book by Randall Munroe
who who is the creator of xkcd that very
science oriented comic and it's called
up go or five it's a reference to Saturn
five rocket that took the Apollo
missions into space and what he's doing
in that book is he explains all these
very complicated concepts all the way
from climate change to physical systems
to submarines and so on but he does it
using only the thousand most common
words in the English language
yeah so that's why he calls the Saturn
five rocket up go or five because it's
called a rocket you can't define a
rocket as a spaceship or a rocket it's
enough referential
he says up goers this thing that goes up
and kids get that right away that's the
thing I read the book I think oh yeah
I'm sorry you're right but maybe the
book is thing explainer yeah and up Cora
five is one of the pages there's another
great book that I'll call thinking
physics I opened this one all in time
and I loved on the back cover it has
this great little pitch it says the only
book that's used in both grade school
and graduate school it's true it's all
simple physics puzzles that can be
explained to a twelve-year-old child
they can puzzle over and it can be
explained to a 25 year old grad student
in physics and they all kind of have
fundamental insights and physics they're
all kind of tricky but anyone can get to
the answer through purely logical
reasoning
I love reading the history of how
scientists came up with their various
breakthroughs and if you have ever gone
like with general relativity relativity
is a fascinating thing it's a very
advanced concept but in a way it's very
simple because Einstein came up with it
with what are called get duncan fancy
word for thought experiments this means
thought experiment in german so he was
able to basically just do logical
thought experiments in his mind until he
came up with relativity and then he
formalized that mathematics and with a
prediction that he made that were later
unfalsifiable so really brilliant
physicists like that they get there by
pure reasoning and pure logical
reasoning it's not like he had to go
draw a lots of complicated diagrams and
so on he just understood things at a
very basic fundamental level so again
this goes back to I think the really
smart thinkers are clear thinkers and
they understand things that they
understand the basics at our very very
fundamental level and I would rather
understand the basics really well
then have memorized all kinds of
complicated concepts but then I can't
stitch together and I can't read arrive
them from the basics if you can't read
arrive it from the basics that you need
it you're lost using them right yeah
yeah exactly
it seems like a large part of making
effective decisions kind of boils down
to dealing with reality how do you make
sure you're dealing with reality when
you're making decisions by not having a
strong sense of self or judgments or or
mind presence the monkey mind will
always respond with regurgitated ammo
response to what it thinks the world
should be and that will cloud your
reality this happens a lot of times and
people are mixing politics and business
like for example in January this year a
little piece on the election that kind
of predicted that Trump or Bernie is
gonna win one of those two characters
gonna win that's not what I wanted to
have happen necessarily I'm an elite my
life is pretty good right I'm not
looking for rabble rousers to change
everything but I wanted to see a reality
the way it was as opposed the way I
wanted it to be so I think the number
one thing that clouds us from being able
to see reality is just that we we just
have preconceived notions of the way it
should be there's a one definition of a
moment of suffering is that at that
moment when you see things exactly the
way they are so this whole time you've
been convinced your business is doing
great and really ignore the sign that's
not doing that well then your business
stale then you suffer well it's just
because you've been putting off reality
even hiding it from yourself so the good
news is that when you're suffering when
you're in pain that's a moment of truth
there's a moment where you're forced to
embrace reality actually the way it is
and then you can make meaningful change
in progress because you can only make
something you can only do that when
you're starting with the truth so I
think the hard thing here is seeing the
truth and you see the truth you have to
get your ego out of the way because your
ego doesn't want to face the truth
so the smaller you can make your ego the
less conditioned you can make your
reactions the less desires you can have
about the outcome you want the easier it
is to see the reality the clearer
example of this is when we're going
through difficult things like a breakup
or a job loss or business failure or
health problem and our friends are
advising us right well when we're
advising them the answer is so obvious
it comes to us in a minute and we tell
them exactly oh that girl get over her
she wasn't good for you anyway you'll be
happier trusting you'll find someone you
know what the correct answer is but that
person can't see it because in that
moment of suffering and pain and they're
still wishing that reality was different
so the problem is in reality the problem
is their desire colliding with reality
it's preventing them from seeing the
truth no matter how much you say it's
the same thing happens when I'm making
decisions the more of a desire that I
had that it worked out a certain way the
less likely I am to see the truth so
especially in business if something
isn't go
well I try to acknowledge that publicly
and I try to acknowledge publicly in
front of my co-founders and friends and
co-workers because that way then I'm not
hiding it from anybody else if I'm not
hiding it from anybody else then I'm not
gonna basically delude myself and what's
actually going on
you won't said anything you can think of
it's been thought of and tried the only
way you're gonna find something is if
you stick to it at an irrational level
and try a whole bunch of things this
kind of makes an idea commodity but the
judgment and execution incredibly rare
how do you evaluate if someone is
picking the right idea and if they have
the capacity to execute on that idea the
the best founders I've found are the
ones who are very long-term thinkers so
even decisions that maybe they shouldn't
care that much about early on they fix
it on because they are not building a
house they're putting bricks in the
foundation of a skyscraper at least in
their minds and so what you're looking
for is looking for someone who knows the
space well who understands how difficult
it's gonna be but doesn't care because
they're they just love whatever they're
doing they're into it and they commit to
it for the long haul so you know passion
and vision alone or not enough yeah and
I think Steve Case said that vision
without execution is a hallucination
execution alone isn't enough and then
unfortunately at least on technology
business there's a lot of luck required
right place right time market forces
timing you know regulatory action
against or Pro so there's a lot of
things that we control where the
platforms are sitting what open source
efforts shadow up so you can never
predict the outside successes but what
you can't predict you the failures you
can say oh this person doesn't know this
field at all that we are their depth or
this person they're short term thinker
they're not gonna last the game they're
gonna go as far as needed because as I
was saying there are no new ideas all
the ideas have been thought but it's
about the combination of the idea plus
the execution plus the passion like
Steve Jobs was a visionary and a great
designer not because he came with the
idea to build a smartphone many people
had tried to build a smartphone but it's
because he had a very high bar for the
design
he understood the manufacturing
tolerances and what the technology was
cable and what it was and he could rally
the people and the resources to get it
done he actually didn't care about the
finance
outcome he took $1 and salary from Apple
he just wanted to see it done and he was
willing to do it for as long as it takes
until it work
so it's kind of it's magic counts of
factors and then the timing in the world
happened to be right the technology was
around and Johnny I was there and who
knows how many other factors intersected
to make it happen but just as many
factors intersected on his side there
one that intersected against him you
know for example he had taken or Apple
which was a horribly failing company at
the time he poor guy died of pancreatic
cancer right he got taken out early
think about what more he could have
created what more he had done for the
world he probably wasn't happy in the
whole process you know he drove himself
to ruin so I I think you do have to be
irrationally optimistic to succeed and
passionate but you also have to really
know your stuff and I meet a lot of
entrepreneurs where their short-term
thinkers in which case that's okay it
just means this is not the thing for you
right go find the thing you can commit
to for 10 years because that's how long
it's going to take minimum to get a good
outcome and you have to enjoy the
journey because there's no guarantee on
the outcome and you have to be really
really good at it which means that you
probably love it so much that you
willing to put in the time before
there's even any return on it so I think
the best founders they have a deep
understanding of the space and going
into enough to be contrarian and they
have a deep passion for it so that
they'll just keep working on it and they
have execution skills they just get
things done they solve problems they're
capable I love that yeah I don't get to
invest with angel founders so I don't
but we all deal with people with similar
you know in business or life if we're
establishing a partnership whether it's
with a customer supplier you know a
relationship we have similar concerns
about their short-term thinking and will
take advantage of us and how should we
go about entering that relationship and
is this relationship fragile I think
that's a good way to think of it one
thing i figured out kind of late is that
generally at least in business in
Silicon Valley and great people have
great outcomes use and be patient every
person that I met at the beginning of my
career 20 years ago where I looked and
said wow that guy or that girl is super
capable there's so
smart and dedicated in blah blah blah
now we'll just be friends or hang out or
whatever forgot about them all of them
almost without exception became
extremely successful you just had to
give them a long enough time scale it
never happens in a time scale you want
or they want but it does happen I want
to circle back and ask you a few more
questions about life before we wrap up
you've kind of called your philosophy
rational Buddhism how does that differ
from traditional Buddhism and what type
of exploration did you go through to
arrive at that yeah the rational part
means that I have to reconcile with
science and evolution so and I have to
reject all the pieces that I can't
verify for myself so for example is
meditation good for you yes it's
clearing your mind a good thing yes is
there a base layer of awareness kind of
below your monkey mind yes all these
things I've verified for myself and some
of the beliefs that come out of Buddhism
I believe and follow because again I'm
verified or reasoned with thought
experiments there myself
but what I will not accept is things
that are written down it's just so like
oh you're this in the past lives that
you were paying off the Karma for where
I haven't seen it I don't remember any
past lives I don't have any memory so I
just have to not believe that or when
people say you know your third chakra is
opening and your second chakras and I
don't know this is fancy nomenclature
right I have not been able to verify or
confirm any of that on my own so if I
can't verify it on my own or if I cannot
get there through science then I just
then it may be true it may be false but
it's not falsifiable
so I cannot view it as a fundamental
truth on the other side I do know that
evolution is true I do know that we are
you know evolved survival and
replication machines I do know that we
have an ego so that we get up off the
ground and worms don't eat us we
actually take action so what rational
budem to me means understanding the the
internal work that buddhism espouses to
make yourself happier and better off and
more present more in control of your
emotions and being a better human being
but I don't subscribe to anything
fanciful just because it was written
down in the book I don't think I can
levitate I don't think that meditations
didn't give me superpowers and those
kinds of things
so it's you know it's basically try
everything test it for yourself
be skeptical keep what's useful and
discard what's not so I would say my
philosophy falls down too and on one
pole is evolution and the binding
principle because it explains so much
about humans and the nearside is
Buddhism which is the oldest most
time-tested spiritual philosophy on the
internal state of being inside each of
us and I think those are absolutely
reconcilable I actually wanna write a
blog post at some point about how you
can map the tenets of Buddhism
especially the non fanciful ones
directly into a virtual reality
simulation what I mean by that is if you
believe we're living in a VR sim which I
know some people are spouting
or you believe the Buddhist view of the
world with samsara and Nirvana and all
that you would actually come to the same
conclusions on how to move your life
what are the areas of your life right
now that you'd like to change the most
and why
I would like to be less I'd like to be
less time bound and I'd like to be less
greedy about signing up for things I
don't how to describe it you know what
it really is
I had a tweet recently where I was going
back and forth with somebody and they
came up with this concept of there
should be a two-factor authentication
under calendar all right exactly there's
two-factor authentication when you're
logging into a websites that if your
password gets stolen the attacker
doesn't the the thief or hacker doesn't
have your phone so they can't login
because the phone that's generate a
unique code well I wish through the
two-factor code against my calendar
because current me present me is always
making promises for future more current
me is tired and exhausted hungry wants
to go home let's go to sleep wants to be
the book wants to hang out with the wife
and baby but future me is this dynamic
high-energy individual who always show
up to every meeting and will have a lot
of energy and we want to get a lot of
things done so I commit myself to all
these commitments in the future that
when the future me arrives actually it's
presently this isn't best to being lazy
and hungry and tired so I wanted to
factor against myself and the way I
would like to do that is I think every
time I make a commitment
anything I should instead just write it
down and then check back in 48 hours
later and then clear mine say do I
commit to doing this or even better
would be saying if I commit doing
something that I could commit to doing
it right now
yeah I think I'm not willing to do it
right now but don't do it don't commit
to it yeah that's the Derek Siver's
approach right like if you're not saying
hell yes right now then you should just
be saying no I think yeah so I think
this is this is something of every busy
person I just want to be much better at
managing my own time could you go
through life through an exploration
phase and then you switch to an
exploitation phase and I'm very much the
exploitation phase I'm not looking for
more exploration but that all that said
I have a hard time saying no if I mean
if I had one wish the most important
thing to me would be I would constantly
be running my mind in debug mode I would
literally be watching every single
thought I have and letting no no
reaction pass without a living stock
inspected stripped searched examined
understood and then let go but the
reality that there's a lot of time and
with just highly conditioned creature so
I I do you a lot of my goals over the
next few years of unconditional earned
responses or habituated responses so
that I can make decisions more cleanly
in the moment without relying upon
memory or or prepackaged heuristics and
judgments what's the most common mistake
you see people make over and over I
think the most common I mean it is a
very tough question so contextual right
it really depends on the context I think
the most common mistake if I look at out
there in on planet earth like for
Humanity is the idea or the belief that
you're going to be made happy because of
some external circumstance and and I
know that's not original that's not new
that's fundamental Buddhist wisdom so
I'm not taking credit for it but I think
I really just recognize it now the
fundamental level including in myself
like we just bought a new car with a
baby so we need a sacred car we would
driving a little Mini Cooper before not
enough room in there so we bought a new
car and now I'm waiting for the new car
to arrive and then of course every night
I'm on the forums reading about the car
why am I doing this is it still the
object sleek car it's not going to
change my life that much or
and I know that the instant the car
arrives I won't care about it anymore
yeah but what it is is I'm addicted to
the desiring I made it big I'm addicted
to the idea that this external thing is
going to bring me some kind of happiness
enjoy and this is completely delusional
so I think just looking outside for
anything I think it is the fundamental
delusion I would not just say you
shouldn't do think me outside you
absolutely should your your living
creature you you know there are things
that you do you locally reverse entropy
that's why you're here you're meant to
do something you're not just meant to
lie there in the sand and meditate all
day long so you should stop actually you
should do what you're meant to do but
the idea that you're gonna change
something in the outside world that is
going to bring you the peace and
everlasting joy and the happiness that
you deserve that is a fundamental
dilution that we all suffer from
including me and so the mistake over and
over and over is to say oh I'll be happy
when I get that thing whatever that is
that's the fundamental mistake that we
all make including me 24/7 all day long
I definitely see myself from that answer
because you're human you're human all of
us do it I want to end with a really
unbounded big question which is what is
the meaning and purpose of life yeah
it's a big question I just give you
three and because there's a big question
I'll give you three answers one is it's
personal you have to find your own
meaning any piece of wisdom that anybody
else gives you whether it's Buddha or
you or me it's gonna sound like nonsense
so I think fundamentally you just have
to find for yourself so the important
part is not the answer it's the question
you have to sit there and dig with the
question that it might take you years or
decades but when you find an answer
you're happy with that that would be
fundamental to your life the second
answer I would give is there is no
meaning to life there's no purpose to
life osho says it's like riding on water
or building houses in sand the reality
is you've been dead for the history of
the universe whereas ten billion years
or more you will be for the next 70
billion years or so until the heat death
the universe and anything you do will
fade it will disappear that's like the
human race will disappear the planet
will disappear it
my leaving that group will disappear so
no one's gonna remember you past a
certain number of generations whether
you're an artist or a poet or a
conqueror or a popper or nothing so
there's no meaning so you have to create
your own own meaning which is what about
until you have to decide it is a play
that I'm going through that I'm just
watching is there a self-actualization
dance that I'm doing is there a specific
thing that I just desire just for the
heck of it but these are all meanings
you are making up there's no fundamental
intrinsic purposeful meaning to the
universe because if there was then you
would just ask the next question
yourself well why is that demeaning all
right so we just be as Richard Fineman
said it'd be Turtles all the way down
the wise we just keep accumulating there
is no answer you can give that question
that wouldn't have another why and I
don't buy the everlasting afterlife
answers because it's insane to me with
absolutely no evidence to believe that
because of how you could live 70 years
here on this planet then you know spend
an eternity which is a very long time in
some afterlife what kind of silly God
judges you for eternity based on some
small period of time here so I think
that after this life it's very much like
before you were born
remember that it's gonna be just like
that and and but before you were born
you didn't care about anything or anyone
including your loved ones including
yourself including humans including
whether we go to Mars or whether we stay
on planet earth and whether there's an
AI or not you just don't care so like I
met this entrepreneur who was obsessed
with Steve Jobs and he was making all
these sacrifices try and be like the
next Steve Jobs and I said Tim do you
want to be exactly like Steve Jobs right
now he said yes so Steve Jobs is dead
I care about anything you've got like
zero he's not registering at all so if
you want to be Mike's new job you don't
want to be like Steve Jobs just be you
right now
he would trade places with you right now
in an instant if you could so I don't
think there's any real meaning or
purpose to life and in the last answer
I'll give you is a little more
complicated than that from what I've
been reading in science friends of mine
have written books on this a kind of
stitched together theories and maybe
there is a meaning to life but it's not
a very satisfying purpose basically in
physics you know the arrow time comes
from entropy second law of
thermodynamics is that entropy only goes
up which means disorder in the universe
only goes up which means concentrated
free energy only goes down
and if you look at what living things
are living systems humans plants
civilizations what-have-you they these
are systems that are locally reversing
entropy humans locally reverse entropy
because we have action but in the
process we globally accelerate entropy
until the heat death of the universe so
you could come up with some fanciful
theory which I had which I like that
we're headed towards a heat death the
universe where there's no concentrated
energy where everything is sort of at
the same energy level and therefore
we're all one thing we're essentially
indistinguishable and what we are doing
is living systems we're accelerating
getting to that state so the more
complex of a system you create whether
it's through computers and civilization
or through art and mathematics or just
to creating a family you're actually
accelerating the heat death the universe
so you're pushing us to at this point
where we end up as one thing but I think
that's the kind of an unsatisfying
answer if you're looking for personal
meeting today in your life that was
phenomenal listen about thank you so
much this was just absolutely
mind-blowing I really appreciate it
where can people find you twitter at my
ball or on my blog at startup boy calm
and thank you so much thank you
it's been great hey guys this is Shane
again just a few more things before we
wrap up you can find show notes at
Furnham street vlog comm slash podcast
that's f AR n a.m. st r e ET b l OG comm
slash podcast you can also find
information there on how to get a
transcript and if you'd like to receive
a weekly email from me filled with all
sorts of brain food go to Furnham Street
blog comm slash newsletter this is all
the good stuff I found on the web that
week that I've read and shared with
close friends books I'm reading and so
much more
thank you for listening
[Music]
[Applause]
you