uh well thanks for joining me no all
thank you for having me let's talk about
the four strands of the fabric of
reality theory of epistemology evolution
by natural selection quantum theory and
computation um before we get into the
specifics of each one what do these four
theories broadly offer to the average
person and what should they care about
incorporating each one into their World
Views so I'm going to be paring David
deuts this is not my original
contribution in any way but uh you know
he sort of wanted to have a theory of
everything he wanted to understand
everything that could be understood not
in the sense of where every particle in
the world ends up or what's going to
happen but just the underlying
explanation to the best of our knowledge
as to what was causitive what or how it
happened and he landed upon these four
theories as being the deepest strands
they have the furthest reach so the most
applicability um they have the deepest
most underlying explanations at the
right level not just purely at the level
of you know particles hitting each other
but at the level where you can actually
use it in everyday life and then I think
if you were to talk to David or if you
were to read his books carefully you
would realize that even splitting these
into four theories is kind of splitting
hairs because knowledge is a crystal
it's a single thing uh nature hath no
boundaries as the famous saying goes and
uh everything connects to everything
it's a nature of creativity you can get
from A to Z not just from A to B to C
you don't have to pass every point in
between in idea space to get from one
idea to another so these are deeply
intermeshed and what I find fascinating
fascinating about his work is that
understanding any one of these theories
not only helps you in that theory not
only actually helps you in everyday life
in some cases not all um but they also
connect to each other in very deep and
interesting ways and so it's one of
those World Views that has to be
absorbed as a whole although even
calling it a worldview is is doing it a
disservice because A worldview is often
just an opinion you know whether I'm a
communist or a capitalist or a Democrat
or a Republican these are worldviews but
these are grounded in our best theories
in physics mathematics computation
Evolution biology uh Etc and so
economics philosophy sociology politics
whatever but so so to contradict uh a
piece of what you're saying in what he's
saying in one place often means that you
have to then go ahead and explain
something that you thought was unrelated
but it's actually deeply related and say
well then how do you explain that um so
I I find his worldview is a framework
and it's a framework that's rooted in
fundamentals and Sciences uh which is
not to say it's impossible to challenge
one should always feel free to challenge
any part of it it's just the way to
challenge it is to have a better Theory
not just to say well that doesn't quite
work because well that explains
something and then there are other
things that explain that thing and there
other things that that explains so you
have to look at it as a web and it's
it's hard to absorb absorb that it's
hard to take that from another person uh
especially when your ego steps in the
way and says well how did this guy
figure it all out so I think you have to
remove the person from the theories you
have to read um both of his books I
would argue um and you would have to
absorb them fairly well it's not a small
Endeavor but on the other hand it can
give you a framework for better
reasoning and better thinking that can
make you smarter there not a lot of
things in this world that can make you
smarter is that how you pitch Do's books
to people unfamiliar with his work yeah
I don't really even care about pitching
but yes that that is how describe it I
would say that uh it's the only thing
that I can point to in my adult life
that has improved my thinking decision-
making and fundamental Outlook now there
are other people who have been
incredibly influential there was a time
when I went through um Nasim taleb's
work for example and I found it very
useful um so it's not to say it's the
only useful thing out there but I think
his uh framework has the deepest
explanations and the furthest reach so
you will find yourself applying it all
over the place place that said I think
it's a mistake to apply it dogmatically
or to say oh I believe that because you
know David Deutsch said so or because
it's part of critical rationalism or
even to ask like what does David think
about this I think that is a mistake uh
instead you just have to absorb the
ideas and some of these ideas I've
absorbed and some of them I haven't I'm
not an expert in quantum physics even
the computation and mathem mathematical
Parts I struggle although I gave it a
good effort um and I learn something a
little bit more every time but I I think
the at the end of the day it's about the
ideas you have to take each idea you
have to evaluate it on its own merits uh
and then if you can you have to absorb
it into your framework of thinking until
the next better idea comes along and if
you can't figure it out then you should
reject it the mistake would be to
memorize it let's dig a bit into
epistemology because this documentary is
primarily about that subject and that
strand of the four strands of his fabric
of reality which as you mentioned is H
it's kind of a mistake too um I mean
think of them separately but rather as a
whole world viewer framework um so fism
right it's the the opposite of dogmatism
and relativism in a sense and that it
says you can be you can be wrong there's
something objective to be wrong about
and um both cultural Rel both relativism
and dogmatism reject that in the sunset
dogmatism says you can't um you can't be
wrong if you've read the script this
what came from God and you necessarily
can be wrong and with relativism it's
like everyone is uh everyone has their
own truth and again you can't be wrong
so uh I guess what how have you applied
epistemology to your personal or um
professional lives yeah so let me start
off by saying I don't like words like
epistemology and fallibilism because I
think they take things that are very
simple and they over complicate them and
I understand why they exist they exist
as a jargon for philosophers and
logicians to communicate more
efficiently and more precisely but I
think for the everyday person they just
put up a barrier between the thing and
the the knowledge and the person and
it's actually very simple epistemology
is just the theory of knowledge which is
another way of saying how do you know
what's true versus how do you know
what's false and this is something that
you have to do every day as you go
through all of life how do you know
what's true how do you know what's
likely to be true how do you know what
someone's telling you is the truth or
not how do you know if uh some Theory
you have is correct or not and how do so
how do you know something is true and
then fism just means you not only can
you always be wrong you probably are
always wrong and you should always be
trying to correct your mistakes you
should always be trying to get closer
and closer to the truth and as you
pointed out people can cons confuse that
with relativism which which is very
different relativism is just saying well
everyone has their own truth and so
we're all correct well that's obviously
not true like not everybody has their
own view of the steam engine or the
electric motor and how those work uh in
the same way not everything is correct
like for example we know that you know
command and control top- down
organization doesn't work well for for
economy
right so there are absolute truths there
are moral truths like slavery is wrong
or just the simple uh Golden Rule you
know do one to others as you'd be done
by or the silver rule that uh don't do
things to uh others that you wouldn't
want done to you right uh so there are
even there's even moral progress so we
do have things that are more true than
other things so just because we can
never know the ultimate truth and we
should always be open-minded AKA
fallible or be a fist
um again I don't like that word but just
just you can you you you're always in a
state of uncertainty but yet there are
things that have a greater truth
composition than others you just have to
get away from this binary thinking of
true and false so there are things that
are more true and there are things that
are less true and the nice thing is that
this uh coincides with common sense you
pointed out that uh groups often search
for consensus and individual search of
Truth um and that making something
social dist the truth of it and nowadays
in the social sciences you know
political influence seem to motivate a
lot of what's happening there and I
often feel like when people claim that
they're doing science it's often to tell
of the opposite with political science
and climate science uh nobody really
says physical science or chemical
science right it's just physics and
chemistry and biology um so I'm curious
how you think individuals can
independently um pursue the search for
Truth uh when there are such strong
incentives to um just conform and be a
sheep yeah um I'm deeply suspicious of
groups of people coming to the truth in
anything because it's not to say groups
are bad humans are Cooperators by Nature
we need groups to get things done but
groups need consensus a group that does
not have consensus will fall apart so a
group will not admit its mistakes it
will not admit that it was wrong it will
not pivot it's not a truth seeking
entity individuals can seek truth and
then based on that they can choose to to
cooperate with others for limited
periods of times to effectuate that
truth or to have something come out of
it but if you're really looking for
truth it's the opposite of looking for
social approval uh truth comes from
truth requires feedback it requires
error correction where does that
feedback come from well there are three
sources of feedback in reality there's
uh two that are very uh natural and one
that we've invented in modern times the
two that are natural are nature uh you
know if I drop drop an apple it falls to
the ground there's a truth there of
Gravity I can't deny it that's nature
giving me feedback so as a scientist uh
that I will physical scientist I would
naturally gravitate towards that truth
haha no pun intended um but there's also
a uh a truth of social approval which is
if I want to if I want to get along with
my group then I can take feedback from
people like did you like that did you
approve of what I did and then the one
that we've invented as a truth seeking
mechanism is free markets where in a
free market it's not a mob it's actually
the opposite the Applause comes from the
mob which is a group of people who are
thinking the same and trying to
coordinate a free market is where
individuals are voting differently and
they're voting on a merit basis and
they're being punished for bad out for
bad predictions and they're being
rewarded for good predictions so free
markets are also a source of Truth
seeking in that for example if I think
that there's a if I think alphabet is a
great stock and I buy it but I turn out
to be wrong then the truth of the market
will punish me as the feedback comes in
and I will lose my money so these are
sort of the three mechanisms you have
for getting feedback from the
environment they're not all equal um
there's actually a fourth um which is
the part of nature which is just
survival but we break that out into its
own thing called Evolution survival of
the fittest right
um I think the natural truth seeking
mechanisms will lead you to truth the
social one will lead you to social
approval but will not lead you to truth
it can lead you into all kinds of dead
ends and unfortunately most people not
only get their feedback from there they
actually get their theories from there
um so that's what I call a difference
between reasoning from first principles
versus reasoning by proxy if you're
reasoning for first principles which is
what you should do for things that you
really care about then you would examine
the truth of the statement for yourself
you would be skeptical you would test it
uh and then if it if it turns out to be
true you would know that because you get
feedback from the right places uh and if
and if it turns out to be false you get
punished but if you're getting your
feedback from other people uh you're
usually going to end up with a wrong
answer so examples of this like there
entire professions where all your
feedback comes from other people um Pol
politics is a prime example of that
anything political um social sciences
you know I'm deeply suspicious of
anything that starts with the word
social uh social sciences socialism
social engineering social justice you
name it because this is all about group
think um so it's not a mechanism for
truth is a mechanism for coordination or
cooperation often it means we're going
to beat the truth into you or you better
get along with us in our truth or
else right and uh de has this idea of
the principle of optimism that all evil
is due to a lack of knowledge and
anything not forbidden by the laws of
physics is possible given that right
knowledge and so uh we should try and
organize society and coordinate Society
in a way that maximizes the growth of
knowledge which doesn't which the social
approval aspect doesn't really fulfill I
guess yeah in fact it's almost
oxymoronic you don't organize Society
you almost have to disorganize society
it's not that you reward people you just
stop punishing people uh for truth
seeking but we do need certain rules of
cooperation to get along if we don't
have some minimum amount of rules
there's always cheaters in any system
and those cheaters will overwhelm the
system it doesn't take a lot it just
takes a few people you know committing
crimes or driving on the wrong side of
the road you know or um you know just uh
taking everything and running or tragedy
of the commons whichever whichever uh
model you want to use but uh the history
of the human species is figuring how to
cooperate while keeping the cheaters out
from breaking the system otherwise the
the parasites overwhelm the host and the
system dies MH and a lot of people
nowadays are concerned about us running
out of resources and uh they propos the
solution is degrowth um can you make the
case for a greater population and that
uh the idea that our resources are at
any given point of time are only limited
by our knowledge and U obviously the
laws of physics well there's two
different issues here one is
uh you know are we running out of
resources and what is a resource and all
that and then the second is are we
destroying the environment the biosphere
as we replicate you know are we an
invasive species that's taking out the
Earth um the first one is easier are we
running out of
resources no we've never run out of a
single resource ever there's not a
single resource you could point to that
was a resource in the classic commodity
sense that had any real value where we
ran out in some harmful way because
technology is the uh is the act of
substituting away from one resource to
another um as we ran out of uh burning
wood uh we started burning coal we ran
out of coal we we didn't actually didn't
run out of coal but we went from coal to
oil and before we could even run out of
oil despite all the peak oil nonsense
around the year 2000 um we uh have
gotten we've gotten nuclear we've got
solar we've got wind um the universe is
full of unlimited resources the universe
the Multiverse whichever version you
take is staggeringly large Way Beyond
your ability to CA toon our resources we
haven't even wrapped a Dyson Sphere
around the Sun and extracted all of that
energy there is unlimited energy even in
the so-called empty cubic meter of space
there's plenty of energy um it's
literally just a question of knowledge
Dark Matter Dark Energy equals MC s
nuclear fusion there's unlimited energy
the only thing that's holding us back is
knowledge the same way the same is true
of any resource um you know are we
running out of wood no we can grow wood
um you know we can grow unlimited trees
we can plant unlimited trees So
eventually we'll we might find a future
civilization may be able to synthesize
trees may be able to synthesize long
dead trees so it is always a question of
knowledge so so that that is that should
put the resource argument to rest
although it won't because there are
people who are dogmatically committed to
the idea that we're running out of
resources and you know they're not fists
to use your earlier phrase and they're
not going to revise their worldview um
based on M logic
um but then the question is like are we
destroying the Earth well that's a
little more subtle uh the Earth is a
little hostile to us to begin with like
the the actual uh natural state of the
Earth would would support a population
of hunter gatherers that numbers in the
millions not the billions so we're
already well past that um and we might
actually save the Earth in that long
term we might stop the next heavy
bombardment we might stop the next
asteroid from hitting the Earth um
humans through the creation of knowledge
the only ones who can save the Earth but
you could argue that we're moving too
fast we are destroying the Earth so
quickly our knowledge and using up the
Earth and destroying it and consuming it
um is outstripping our ability to uh
rejuvenate it and to replenish it and I
think there there's a debate but I think
the people who tend to win that debate
are uh kind of they're just looking at
the things that are right in front of
their face and not paying attention to
the larger picture and they tend to be
rather dogmatic or religious in their
beliefs but I think the the reality is
mixed like yes of course species have
gone extinct due to humans species go
extinct not due to human activity
whatsoever all the time the vast vast
majority of species that have ever
existed are extinct um because they did
not adapt humans can actually resurrect
species we're bringing back the woolly
mammoth anything we D DNA signature of
we we can resurrect as uh yeah we're
cutting down forests we're also planting
forests North America is now a net
carbon sink we've added so much Forest
cover um because as people get richer
they plant Gardens and trees now are
these old growth forests no but they
will be someday we're probably going to
terraform Mars at some point you know
that'll be a lot more life than was
there before um so I think these things
are more arguable but as long as the
technology is there we can always kind
of earn our way out of it um if climate
change is an issue and it's hard to
discuss because it's become so
politicized um you know we we can carbon
capture out of the environment but I
think I think there are people who view
the world as like this idyllic perfect
place and that we just can't came along
and ruined it and anything we do in any
direction ruins it whether we try to
save it or whether we try not to save it
and I think that's just a fundamentally
anti-human philosophy they just want us
to go back to 5 million people living in
the Garden of Eden and there was no such
thing um and to that I just say you
first yeah uh Marxism right like you uh
you started with oh we already have
everything but some people have more
than their fair share and so what we
really need is just we redistribution
and for everybody to um you know share
and like Marxism besides denying human
incentives also has a problem where it
just assumes that everything is finite
and we're all just dividing up the same
small set of things well the cavemen
didn't have color TVs and computers and
cars and antibiotics and Medicine you
know they they we not sitting around
dividing up the same few things the
knowledge grows we create more it also
tends to assume that we can freeze frame
at some point in society and say well we
have enough different kinds of sneakers
and we have enough different kind we
have enough housing we just need to
allocate it better and that is not how
anything works uh deuts has a great
definition of wealth which he says
wealth is the set of uh physical
Transformations that we can affect or
not even physical it's a set of
Transformations that we can affect
although every transformation is
physical ultimately um and so when you
think about it that way you realize that
knowledge is not just stored of capital
in the classic Marxist sense you know
Capital versus labor but it's also
knowledge on what to do with that
Capital the cavemen or the Paleolithic
ancestors had access to all the same
resources we did they they were living
on the same Earth and by the modern
environmentalist arguments they had a
better Earth they had more to do things
with um but yet they couldn't do
anything they were not Wealthy by any
stretch of the imagination and why it
was because of knowledge so life is not
a zero sum game it's a positive sum game
but we are hardwired to think it's a
zero sum game because for millions of
years or billions of years there was no
such thing as wealth there was no such
thing as persistent knowledge Creation
in the environment and so what you had
was you just had a small amount of
resources being divided up and most of
the games were status games whereas
which monkey outranks which other monkey
and that decides which monkey gets to
eat first and we played that game for a
billion years so now we come on to a
recent game where actually we can all
eat and the big problem is obesity it's
no longer starvation um and the big
problem is boredom it's not actually
work there's enough work um so in this
environment switching your your evolved
mindset from a uh Zero Sum game to a
positive sum game where we can all win
if we create knowledge together and if
we use the resources that we have to
create more resources and more wealth
that's that's the game that we all need
to be playing now inequality is an issue
and it's going to be a bigger issue
because technology creates leverage and
leverage creates the gap between the
halves and the Have Nots just by the
nature of the choices they make and what
they choose to do so that drives people
into thinking that things are really
unfair but you know in the the reality
is the opportunities have never been
more equal than than now uh Elon Musk
and Jeff Bezos have the same iPhone you
do they don't have some better version
of an iPhone they're eating food that
might be marginally better than yours
but it's basically the same you might
even have a better diet than them you
probably have more time to go to the gym
than them they're not Immortal and
they're not going to be most likely not
at this time scale so you have more
youth than them um you have a lot of
advantages over them so the wealth gaps
are actually much smaller than people
think uh and a lot of that is due to
just mass production uh which comes from
specialization labor and capitalism um
but it's very easy to overlook that and
agitate because that gets you high in
the status hierarchy with other monkeys
because it makes you look like you're
you know fighting for Noble causes and
um gives you status which is really what
people are craving these days they're
craving status not money or wealth and
status is a zero sum game so it's kind
of an evil game to play because there
have to be losers for every winner and
the only way to win is by crushing
somebody else down AI is all the buzz in
the world right now and uh people uh
have this uh people are afraid that it
might kill us all and so they proposed
that we regulate the free exercise of
mathematics as you put it and let the
good guys ensure that the technology is
used for the right purposes why do you
think this is such a bad idea first of
all I don't think we know how to make
AGI I think we what we have is natural
language Computing um which is a
tremendous breakthrough uh we can parse
natural language data sets instead of us
having to learn how to speak the
computer language like python or C we
can speak English the computer will
speak English back to us that's a
tremendous Innovation so let's not take
away from AI AGI is a different thing
AGI is something that is capable of
creativity which I haven't seen much
evidence of and I don't mean creativity
like taking a whole bunch of images and
drawing a new image that's large data
set interpolation extrapolation
impressive but not the same thing at all
um creativity is is having a problem and
solving it completely out of left field
and jumping huge boundaries cutting
through huge swats of search space to
find the correct answer and to test it
and all keep revising it um I don't
think that necessarily the current uh
batch of uh Computing algorithms will
get us there although we're always one
breakthrough away from the future um
whether nuclear fusion or rocketry or
immortality or or fighting viruses or or
um or Computing
um almost all the innovation of the last
50 years has come in the unregulated
industry if you go to the regulated
Industries like healthcare it's a
nightmare because there's just too many
bureaucrats where they're saying no and
you can't actually do anything
interesting um so it's not a coincidence
that most of the innovation has happened
in the world of bits versus Adams Peter
teal lamented you know dude where's my
flying car well it's because you're not
allowed to take a car and put it in the
air because if it falls down and hurts
somebody God forbid nuclear nuclear
power has been frozen and the human race
has been deprived of cheap and free
energy because we haven't been allowed
to innovate on nucle nuclear power uh I
get it it's nuclear weapons are scary
but it's a conflation in the monkey mind
of the two things nuclear power doesn't
necessarily need to lead to nuclear
weapons and they don't necessarily go
together um just like uh you know
exploding a fuel and a fuel air
explosive is not the same thing as a
gasoline engine um so we've been held
back through regulations and most of the
Innovation that we've seen in the last
few decades has been on the internet in
Mobile Computing um uh and software has
been AI has been in crypto cryptography
and
cryptocurrencies uh what is the common
thread between all of these things it's
all software it's all in bits what is
software is thinking it's speech it's
mathematics so people who are trying to
regulate AI out of this doomsday fear
from having watched the Terminator
movies one too many times they're
regulating the free exercise of math
mathematics this is completely
innumerate people which is the modern
version of illiteracy who literally do
not know how anything Works they don't
know how the computer works they don't
actually understand how you know they
don't understand mathematics they're
scared of it these are the same kids who
are scared of math in high school
they're now writing regulations to
prevent other kids from doing math that
are actually going to make the human
race better off if you limit computers
you have literally removed and
computation you literally removed the
last source of innovation that we have
in our society you're freezing Us in
place don't think you're going to make
advances in biology or rocketry somehow
magically while you've stopped the
Improvement in mathematics and Computing
you've also fundamentally limited speech
so what are these I'm sorry this is the
one place where I get worked up what are
these idiots going to actually do are
they going to show up and say you can't
run this computation this many time you
can't solve this math problem this many
times well all knowledge is connected to
all of the knowledge what if I come up
with a different way to solve the same
thing what if I don't have to do matrix
multiplication but I do a different
transformation are you going to ban that
too are you going to prevent me from
doing what about if there's 100 of us
doing them INS What if the Chinese are
doing it and they're building an AI to
power their drone swarms what do you
want us to do just get blown up by them
no so they always make an exception for
the military so we end up in the worst
of all possible worlds no private sector
Innovation is allowed human freedom is
curtailed completely in oppressively you
have to arrest people for doing
mathematics which is insane um you have
to prevent new forms of mathematics from
emerging yet somehow you have to
miraculously hope that your military
sector will keep up even though it has
no support from the private sector and
they're mostly incompetent building
things themselves and now you're
competing head on against the Chinese
and whoever else who you consider your
enemies who are going to go full full
well into it so to me this is just
innumerate people writing legislation
yeah and anytime you add a regulation it
can be in any sector you uh entrench an
infinite amount of error because like
this you cut off One path and you don't
see that that path is sort it branches
out as a tree and like those branches
keep on growing and keep on growing and
this infinite paths that the that um if
that regulation weren't in place could
have uh led to and that would possibly
be maximal uh value creation because
that's where uh all the people are
willingly spending their money um so
once you cut off that path you're
basically you've stopped knowledge
Creation in that space correct and and
you know to give an example like let's
take the most horrific example what was
the most horrific invention of the last
100 years probably nuclear nuclear
weaponry nuclear power well um this same
group would have happily banned nuclear
weaponry and nuclear power and they
would have had a much better argument
for doing so and if that was and if they
had done that we would all be speaking
Russian or German right now people often
talk about the good old days that never
even happened and one of Spain's top
ranked universities now has a master's
degree in degrowth and I wonder who's
going to hire anyone with a degrowth
degree uh even the people who want
degrowth right they aren't willing to
start loss making businesses that's they
don't want feedback from free markets
because nobody would hire them um but
they will get hired by academics which
is feedback from people exactly why do
you think there's such a growing
interest um an academic growing interest
in degrowth and maybe talk a bit about
the the fall of Western
universities well you can look outside
the window it's perfect out here you
know it's beautiful and it's the quality
of life is incredible for a student and
they have no real responsibilities and
they get fooled in thinking that's how
the entire world works but this is a
controlled environment of low ENT
and very high resources being pumped in
from the outside from the state from
their parents from uh all kinds of uh
wealth creation that was done outside
that is coming into the university and
it's an institution for knowledge which
is fantastic but it's not how the real
world works it's a small game inside the
larger World um and I think they just
lose sight of that so they just have too
many resources and too little feedback
from nature and so that's going to lead
you to a lot of bad ideas and that's
fine I mean it's the nature of the
University come up with that ideas good
and bad and then eventually they get
tested in the real world but when the
bad ideas start eating the good ideas
that's when you have a problem when the
bad ideas start forbidding the good
ideas the whole concept of degrowth is
nonsense uh nobody actually engages in
degrowth in their actual everyday life
nobody lowers their standard of living
nobody wants to be less fit nobody wants
to be less healthy nobody wants to be
less knowledgeable nobody wants less of
anything um so the idea that society as
a whole is going to go through degrowth
is just
it's it's just suicide of A Sort now
these bad ideas they're basically
attacks on the good ideas but uh any
society that degrowth itself will simply
get outc competed by the societies that
don't degrowth themselves and there are
plenty of societies that are not going
to degrowth themselves you can go to
rural India or rural China or anywhere
in that part of the world to see what
degrowth society looks like it's the
pregrowth society it's the same thing
it's high infant mortality it's
malnutrition it's lack of Access to
Health Care uh and again it's the
fundamental mistake of saying oh we're
done we've figured everything out and
we're gonna stop here and now we're just
going to divide up the loot um complete
nonsense would you even go back 10 years
in time and lose out on all the
medicines and all the Computing and all
the knowledge and all the travel that we
have invented in the last 10 years
absolutely not I wouldn't even go back
to iPhone 14 right but maybe have an
extreme case but everybody wants the
latest and greatest of everything it
completely flies in the face of degrowth
so degrowth might be fun at cocktail
parties and you know impress people and
make you sound like you're looking out
for the future of the human race I I
don't know why maybe it's built into the
human species in evolutionary context
but there there is a place for a person
who says stop we're all going to die
right and uh that's been around since I
think the dawn of humanity there's
always been someone saying stop we're
all going to die and we keep those
people around because once in a while
they're right it's like okay don't don't
insult the king we're all going to die
uh don't go over there and don't eat
that bat you know we're gonna we're all
going to get a virus right so in some
sense they must have been correct Once
Upon a Time because we keep them around
but at this point it's almost become
performative there are too many people
around there you know carrying around
those the end is near signs just now
they say different things it's like you
know the were population collaps running
out of resources climate change whatever
there's there's a bunch of them every
generation and I I think there's some
small use to having those people around
because yes we there are things we could
do that could kill us all right I don't
think we should be creating many more
Wuhan Institutes of biology for example
nor should we be spreading nuclear
weapons and there's some common sense to
that that we can agree on but in general
I think the whole exercise is becoming
performative and the degrowth crowd is
just a politically correct version of
those yeah with degrowth I guess covid
was a great example right if you were a
proponent if you are a proponent
degrowth you should be able to look back
at Co and say see this is what we need
this is what this is like we need covid
for the next uh I don't know 30 years
until like uh 2050 and then we can go to
zero uh net carbon like will be zero
don't give don't give them any
ideas but but if if we were to actually
reach um you know zero carbon emissions
um I mean in a linear fashion maybe you
know we can predict the growth of
knowledge if we don't know if like we we
actually have like much better
technology tomorrow that uh you know
captures all the carbon in in the
atmosphere and we don't have to use
carbon anymore but obviously that's like
fantasy thinking but if you actually
wanted zero emissions you would have to
have kind of like a covid every year for
the next um I mean until the Paris Co is
a good example because the question to a
degrowth Advocate they're all for
downsizing well it's never them first
you know everybody else start downsizing
they're all for like stopping production
okay how much Healthcare are you will to
give up which health advances you want
to give up you know we got a bunch in
the labs right now now it's O overly
regulated so it's very hard to make
Innovation Healthcare but it still
happens because it's such an important
thing everybody wants to be healthy
everybody wants to live longer so we
grind on where it's great what
Healthcare would you like to give up
you know none they always want the
maximal health care everybody wants the
maximal healthare nobody wants to be
unhealthy but that argument applies at
at infinum so I I just view these as
like uh you know small groups of
misguided people who will cause damage
to their own societies but India and
China are not going to degrowth they're
on the exact opposite trajectory maximum
speed you know pedal to the metal um and
when you know 6 billion hum are voting
this way and you're over
here all all you're degrow are your own
life's prospects I I would argue to the
people who are getting degrees in
degrowth it might make you feel good but
your life is not going to land in a good
place at the end of it you will probably
end up miserable and childless and poor
and everybody else will just be getting
richer and happier so it's not not a
good not a good Fork it's not too late
pick a different direction would be my
advice yeah I've been a Doomer too at
various times in my life so you know
just error correct made a mistake
happens does that make you a bit more
bullish on India and China and some of
these developing countries rather than
uh also like the developing and
developed countries right it's it
doesn't really it doesn't really work
anymore yeah yeah and I mean there there
there are ways in which I go to Asia and
it's far more developed than here in the
UK and there are times when I go to you
know UK in the west and it's far more
developed than Asia but so there are
good ideas everywhere and there are bad
ideas everywhere the the thing that I
worry about is
uh you know the West is a uniquely open
free liberal liberated tolerant Society
with still good rule of law it it's it's
a very unique combination like I I love
the American Bill of Rights for example
you know freedom of speech right to bear
arms right to not have surveillance and
warrants and see you know all that stuff
is slowly being nipped away because the
nature of power to take those things
away but the the incredible amount of
intellectual physical and real Freedom
that's available in the west it's not
really there in the rest of the world
those ideas are spreading but they're
also being constrain you know most of
the world basically does not live in
free countries if you just kind of add
up the sheer numbers they're not free in
the way that people in the west are and
free doesn't mean freedom to you know
live on the streets uh freedom is much
more in the sense of Human Rights um
human rights are taken much more
seriously in the west and things like
Reg getting the free exercise of
mathematics is uh highly limiting human
rights um so that's why I don't think
it's a cultures are not equivalent you
can't just swap one culture for another
and say yeah they're equally good that's
again relativism and assumes that
there's no progress made in knowledge
and there's progress made in all kinds
of knowledge including moral knowledge
um so yeah I don't I don't think they're
the same and I don't think they're
easily swappable I'm I'm just saying
like you're not going to stop and China
from doing what they're doing and India
and China is just shorthand for
basically the rest of the world um but
at the same time I'm not saying that's I
I don't know I don't know which is a
good outcome and what's not I just know
that the freedoms and the rights that we
have in the west get taken for granted
and if we lose them here I'm not sure we
get them elsewhere do you have any
guesses for obviously the enlightenment
happened but do you have any guesses for
what were the circumstances or the ideas
that actually led to that um kind of
rebell Reon against Authority and um
against just worshiping knowledge
instead of now criticizing knowledge and
seeking better explanations I think one
common factor you see in the
enlightenment the free thinking eras
that we know about is a high degree of
federalism and that means like lots of
small city states um next to each other
so for example ancient Greece you had a
lot of little city states um in the era
of the Enlightenment you had a lot of
little city States and and small
municipalities in Europe and uh and
there was also the Age of Exploration
was going on so people were very free to
like go to different places and what you
generally find is like in those kinds of
environments people can sort of Freedom
shop you know they can go to the area
that is most allowing them to be free
and if that starts becoming oppressive
they can just go next door and it's
culturally fairly similar and it's
geographically not very far away but
yeah all the smart people are now
Gathering here right all the thinkers
are now gathering over there so it kind
of gives them an escape valve um from
society not just from the government but
also from cultural uh regulations or
just from being you know too close to
their family and having to like work on
the Family Farm whatever it is high
degree of Mobility um and or and uh
self-organization allows the people who
want to push the boundaries forward to
move around so I think that's been a
common thing the US uh for example still
is but was much more Federalist where it
depend it used to matter much more which
state you lived in rather than the
country itself now the federal
government has a lot of power and chews
up a lot of the GDP so it doesn't matter
what the federal policies are but used
to be able to shop policies state by
state much more and that allows people
who want to innovate to say okay fine
I'm not going to do it in Wyoming I'll
do it in Texas or I can't do it in Texas
I'll do it in California or I can't do
it in California so I'll do it in New
York um that's disappearing so but I
think what's taking its place is the
internet uh combined with a new Mobile
Generation that's coming up that's you
know much more Global so-called
Sovereign individuals who um although
that get hard to do with family and
culture right it's it's all fun and well
hopping airplanes and living out of
airbnbs until you have a family we were
just talking about Healthcare and uh you
know you mentioned that no one wants um
a less healthare no like less healthare
than we have today everyone wants to be
healthy but some people really get riled
up when you talk about U extending
lifespan as if we cannot exceed this uh
a certain natural liit limit that a
supernatural has missed out upon us so
what do you think that is and do you try
to convince people otherwise that that
is evil it's mostly a religious belief
when I when you dig down to it I mean on
the internet people say all kinds of
crazy things but if you sit down with a
normal person over a normal dinner table
and they
say and they express opposition to
Extended lifespan um first notice nobody
is uh opposed to extending Health span
right so nobody's like hey I've got a
way to make you feel 10 years younger
right now right now there's nobody who
will say no to that except maybe a
10-year-old right anyone north of 10
will take the regression in their
feeling they want their body to be
younger okay great so everybody wants
more Health span right and uh nobody
wants to die right now while they're
healthy so de facto you know if a then b
b then C you believe in immortality you
want it to so really it just boils down
to a religious belief of it's unnatural
and and what they're doing is they're
thinking one level higher to one are we
are we killing the Earth again does that
mean there'll be too many of us and then
you know two does that what does that
mean for society and they kind of can't
re them through all of that well we got
millions of times richer we already you
know doubled our lifespan uh the world
didn't end things got generally better
because I know you wouldn't go back and
be in the Paleolithic Era and you know
walking around with a club looking for
dinner so I think deep down there are
very few people who are actually opposed
what they're opposed to is the idea that
we're going to destroy the Earth um or
it's a religious belief that we're being
extremely unnatural and it's always a a
hert issue it's it's it's never a I
don't want to live healthier it's that
what if everybody else does so it's kind
of this amorphous fear but I think it's
largely religious belief I think if you
just start up and and the way that uh
so-called immortality will arrive if it
arrives and you know if we're lucky
enough to see it hopefully soon but I
don't know a little skeptical iCal there
too um but the way it's going to come is
through rej Rejuvenation therapies uh
it's going to come through oh my
80-year-old mom can you know her knees
are better and now she can get up off
her wheelchair and walk around well no
one's going to stop that you know and if
you're hurt like oh my you look at look
at the lengths people go to just to
improve their skin right just to look
younger get rid of the wrinkles you know
get your hair back all those things so
everyone's going to go for that so
everyone's going to improve their health
space
and then no one wants to die when
they're healthy no one wants to be
walking around healthy and fit and
good-looking and then suddenly drop dead
well we don't want that either so what's
left if I can make you younger and if I
can stop you from dying when you're
younger then death is gone yeah often
make the same kind of similar logical
argument uh I say like if you are in
perfectly good health and uh I ask you
the question do you want to die tomorrow
uh what would you say it's like right
and when do you think that answer will
be yes if you're perfectly good you're
never going to say oh yeah I want to die
tomorrow and you can always off yourself
so so it's never about the self it's
always about this uh fretting and uh you
know an anxiety about what happens to
the world what happens to the species
what happens to the race what happens to
the Earth and we've discussed that a
little bit but I would also add that one
of the things that you really learn when
you um read Deutsch's theories and
you you authenticate them for yourself
is you realize humans are Universal
explain ERS what does that mean that
means
that everything that we know in the
universe follows the laws of physics and
there's no reason to believe otherwise
if if you think otherwise then please
present your better theory that explains
the world if you can't do that then you
have to go with the laws of physics well
the laws of physics are completely
computable what does that mean they can
fit inside a touring machine or computer
and a computer can simulate the laws of
physics with arbitrary accuracy limited
only by the specific power of that
computer and if you increase the power
that computer you can simulate them more
accurately so humans already simulate in
our minds we simulate and through our
computers we simulate the weather we
simulate quazars we simulate um you know
even human systems we simulate the
economy we simulate all kinds of things
okay so anything that can be understood
we can understand in our minds this is
something the AGI people get wrong when
they talk about super intelligence there
is nothing out there that can understand
something fundamentally that we can
understand it might be faster it might
have more compute might have more memory
but there's no con that it can
understand that we can ourselves
understand so we are maximal Universal
explainers and that means that every
human is capable of unbounded creativity
anyone could be the next Einstein or
fery or Elon Musk or uh you know Jeff
Bezos or uh Yona sock or whatever so we
can create anything and if we can create
anything every human is a lottery ticket
bet on the future of the
species um you have a great tweet where
you you say the modern secular religion
casts man as the devil and the state as
the Savior um this religion comes in
various shapes and forms But ultimately
they all lead back to Marxism what do
you think that is I don't know I don't
know if it's Marxism per se I I I think
there's a there's a struggle that's been
going on in the human species from the
very beginning uh there are many
struggles but this is one of the more
interesting ones which is between
collectivism and the individual right if
we're all individuals if we're all like
closer to lions and tigers for example
or even more solitary animals um then
yeah you have maximum freedom but you
have no survivability for the species uh
in fact humans uh Homo sapiens I think
you all know of Hari uh talked about
this in his book um humans are
Cooperators and we're Cooperators across
genetic boundaries so you can have uh
you can't have more neanderthals meet in
the battlefield than are related to
their by genes so you know you can get
to your uncles and cousins and go to war
and beat up the monkeys but on the flip
side uh Homo sapiens you can have a
100,000 of them unite on the battlefield
because they're all Christian or they're
all Muslim or they're all Hindu they
have these shared belief system these
shared story systems so humans uniquely
can cooperate across genetic boundaries
ants can't bees can't and yeah people
always find like tiny tiny little
exceptions like the the pigeon on the
wolf's back but these are just like you
know silly little anecdotes uh they're
not true in a broad scale so humans have
this ability to cooperate across genetic
boundaries and that makes them very
powerful but at the same time as we
discussed earlier that's for a form of
group think that's like we're going to
go to war and Destroy everyone we're
going to build this Factory it's not for
creativity and coming up with new ideas
together necessarily uh Al the markets
are good for organizing that and and
this is something that uh you know High
R&D institutions do well like you know
Elon Musk and crew building Dragon for
SpaceX or whatever so in general you
have the cooperator theory of the world
or the collectivist theory of the world
they kind of go together and then
there's the individual free uh free uh
Freedom theory of the world or the great
man theory of History you know where you
have uh and I didn't make that up they
call it great man you can rename it if
you want but uh you know it's like
Einstein and uh you know Fineman or
Caesar like these these individuals took
acts that then forked history and if
they hadn't come along would it have
happened so the debate is like if
Napoleon hadn't come along would there
have been another Napoleon someone with
a different name if Elon Musk hadn't
come along Einstein the answer is
usually yes but a different timing and
the details would have been different
and it's a collection of individuals
that makes history anyway so it's kind
of this Instinct of collectivism versus
individuality so what is collectivism
collectivism is inherently millenarian
it's inherently religious in nature it
kind of says we're all headed towards un
Unity we're all going to be one thing
we're going to go from being unicellular
organisms to multicellular organisms to
being a civilizational multicellular
organism that marches um you know
together
and in its Best Vision it's like you
know Humanity becomes a God and we're
all cells in a giant nervous system of
the brain of this new entity that we're
going to create maybe AGI unites us all
in the hell version is the Borg you know
we're all just like a big fungus and
we're all the same we're all just eating
everything and there's no
differentiation so this is just a
struggle that goes on back and forth and
so Marxism is just an example of this I
don't think anybody would want to live
in a
completely uh individual society that
would be Mad Max okay uh but I don't
think anybody wants to live in a
collectivist society either that's the
borgs that's the struggle you have um
and with uh the new religion you know
the religion is about uniting the masses
religion is about bringing people
together with some higher Vision uh and
it used to be about God uh you know
there's a and there different versions
but let's go with the Western version
for a moment um there's there's there's
usually a white male in the sky surprise
uh who's telling you how to do things
and they have a set of rules supposed to
follow these rules if you don't you're
going to get hurt in the next life uh
and if you do then you'll get reward in
the next life and a lot of people still
believe that and you know it's fine
religion is a cooperating system for
humans so you know it's good to be
around in certain certain doses
but I think a lot of people when science
came along n famously declared God is
dead and why did you say that because
once you took Newton and the
enlightenment scientist seriously you
realize well maybe there is a guy in a
white robe maybe that's a little too
literal maybe there's something else
maybe there's something less so I think
since then Humanity has been searching
for an organizing
principle and it's hard to argue that
all there is is just this reality of
Mind and Body yes science is great it
lets us navigate the world let us
predict future outcomes lets us build
technology but the fundamental mystery
of existence of Consciousness why am I
even here how did I get here who the
heck am I really you know what happens
when I die those questions science has
not made much progress on it does not
answer so there is always going to be a
religious impulse so and I think it's I
think it's baked into the human species
it's hardwired into us at some level and
so that religious impulse will always be
answered there will always be a religion
uh whether you care to call it that or
not so and I think the founders of the
United States very intelligently
separated church and state they said
thou you know you shall not make any
official state religion and you won't
abridge the exercise of any religion
because they knew that this impulse was
always going to be around and people had
to be free to express it but the state
should not mandate it well now we do
have a state Mandate of religion which
is you just remove God from the equation
and then it doesn't look like religion
anymore but it still has the same
characteristics okay so you know if you
are for example an an enlightened
atheist you don't believe in God and you
don't believe in hell and you don't
believe in heaven you don't believe in
afterlife well what's left well you
could still have a vision of a perfect
world a Utopia that's heaven so you
could say ah well you know if the world
was like a like a paradise it was like a
natural Paradise um Garden of Eden right
everything is perfect until man comes
along and then he ruins everything so
man is a sinner who's destroying the
world Gaia would be just fine if it
weren't for these evil humans so you
have the sinner you have you have the
devil which is mankind um you have the
you have the perfect heaven which is the
Utopia that you want to create you have
the hell which is what man is leading
you towards right now the technological
hell of capitalism and progress and then
who's the Savior well eventually
somebody has to save the day so it's
going to be you and your Merry band of
friends weaponizing the State against
individuals so I think that's the
current religion that's going on it goes
by various names wokeism identity
Marxism just hides sometimes call
liberal it has to be a shadow religion
it can't actually let itself be named
because if it is named as a religion
then it's actually forbidden by the
Constitution the government from
engaging in it but it's very cleverly
disguised but I think it's a
collectivist impulse and it will always
reassert itself and again if you don't
have that you have a brutal Society so
you have to have some variation of it
but at the same time if it takes over
the whole thing it's a that ate the host
um and the whole thing is a fungus now
obviously traditionally religions uh put
man at the center of things and then
science came along and said oh actually
you were just descended from the Apes
and uh you're not even at the center of
the universe uh nor the center of the
solar system right this this whole big
universe that uh most of which like is
so far away we might never be able to
explore and um so you're just like
chemical scum as Stephen this is one of
Deutsch's greatest reputations and
insights which is he shows how humans by
being Universal explainers we're not
just like smarter monkeys um monkeys are
not capable of encoding much knowledge
outside of what's in their genes humans
are capable of anything anything that
can be imagined we can imagine anything
that any intellectual thing can believe
or do or deduce we can and so humans are
just qualitatively different where that
that classic figure of like the you know
the Walk The Crawling to the the sorry
the the Tad poles to the fish to the you
know to the toad to the walking monkey
to the taller and taller monkey to the
grer of the human that is completely
false if you've seen that you need to
un-brainwash yourself that is not true
humans are Universal explainers uh you
know we can create Rockets there's no
amount of evolution that is going to get
a monkey to create a rocket that going
to sorry there's no short of it becoming
a universal explainer like us um no no
number of tadpoles getting together are
going to create a rocket and launch off
to the Stars knowledge is unique output
of human
creativity and then when you look at
what's going on with creativity
creativity is unbounded so we have moved
Evolution from the physical to The
mimetic Domain and it is the most
powerful thing in the known universe if
you were to look at all the stars the
telescope in the night sky and uh you
would find that they would H be
different but they would be different
within certain physical parameters if on
the other hand you get to a certain one
and it's got uh you know you see an
asteroid heading towards it and this is
David's example not mine and the
asteroid gets deflected at the last
second with an explosion like whoa
there's something going on there that's
fundamentally different and and the it
means that there's creative knowledge
there there's life there there's
intelligent life there and intelligence
changes everything because knowledge can
be perfectly replicated you could you
could take the knowledge of how to
terraform a planet if you had it and you
could beam it to another planet and then
a hundred years later you could see that
world is terraformed it's changed so uh
it could be a copy it could be its own
version but knowledge is so powerful
that it can completely change the
environment and you can look and just
see how humans have changed the Earth to
see that uh just recently um I think
David was telling this today actually
where he said that uh he read that the
the uh mass of things produced by humans
for the first time has like P passed the
mass of things created by other things
in the biosphere I don't know exactly
what he meant by that but it just it's
just like if you cannot explain the
Earth without first understanding humans
any alien species that arrives on Earth
the first thing they're going to be
interested in is humans you cannot
explain anything else about this earth
right everything else would go to the
sidelines they would not be interested
in the in the geological crust or the
weather patterns or the uh the structure
of the environment because they would
say well I can figure that out by
looking at any other planet but these
humans that's causing huge change and
the moment we leave this planet we
become multiplanetary species that will
be more obvious but you can no longer
explain the universe without explaining
humans because we are creative entities
not to say that there might not be other
creative entities on other planets there
probably are just by the law of large
numbers but um without explaining
intelligence and knowledge and
creativity you cannot explain the
universe anymore so it's kind of a nice
little full circle where we went from
being the center of the universe to
being infinitesimal and unimportant in
the universe to Bas actually saying well
actually through the knowledge that we
create and the progress that we make we
are actually incredibly important in a
very large
Universe how have you applied Papa and
deuts as a pomology or any other vast
implications in your own life the
epistemology is really helpful because
it helps you figure out what's true and
what's not so uh there are a lot of
authors that I used to read where I
would sort of absorb what they said and
now I realize a lot of that nonsense um
simple example is Guns Germs and Steel
you know where he has a really Jared
Diamond has a beautiful explanation of
um you know why certain cultures evolved
and others didn't he's like well Europe
is horizontal and the Americans and
Africa are vertical and when you're
vertical then the latitude changes
change temperature so Technologies like
food production and domestication of
animals don't transfer and so you're
just your technolog is very narrow
whereas in Europe the technology applies
across the board so you can develop much
faster and that's why they took over the
world it's a neat little explanation it
turns out to be maybe there's some truth
to it but it also turns out to be mostly
false because even a small amount of
creativity or a small amount of error
correction will quickly break you out of
that trap uh so you realize that the
dominant thing that's important is
knowledge creation and then error
correction to get better and better
knowledge creation uh and Geographic and
resource factors don't apply that much
yes resources matter but um there are
areas of the world that are better
resourc than the areas of the world that
where we first developed technologies
that now the entire world relies upon so
creativity is so much more the
dominating force you to pay attention
that that's that's an easy example it
helps you get over the we're running out
of resources argument or that wealth
creation is evil or let's be pessimistic
because we're all going to kill
ourselves or there are too many humans
it's kind of all these anti-natalist
anti-human anti-p people arguments um so
I I think in that sense the epistemology
useful at at a base level you're always
trying to figure out what's true and so
uh poer had the concept of
falsifiability which is very important
like if I make make a statement that
can't be disproven it's kind of a
meaningless statement for example we're
living in a simulation well how would
you disprove it anything you do I'll
just say well that's in the simulation
that's part of the simulation so it's an
unfalsifiable statement which means it's
just religion it's just a nonsense
statement um or the Free Will argument
is another nonsense argument so it helps
you not waste time on those because
they're non-falsifiable
secondly uh Deutsch added the additional
criteria uh which I think is a very good
one saying that a good theory is hard to
vary
which means you can't change the details
of the theory without changing the
outputs uh you can't just move the goal
post afterwards so for example uh the
example he gives in one of his books is
you know why do we have seasons so
there's the old Greek the mythology
Theory well it's because pan got
kidnapped by Hades and when she came out
like spring came out and so on well that
one is really easy to vary why did
spring start later today well later this
month well it's it's because panie you
know got lost in her way out or uh why
panie why wasn't she just Aphrodite
right so it's just a very easy to vary
Theory so it's not really a good
explanation um on the other hand if you
look at the axial tilt theories because
the Earth is tilted 23 degrees and you
know when it's going around the Sun um
there's you know parts of it are further
away and parts of it are closer and that
determines the seasons well okay that's
a very good theory because if I move
from 23 to 22 the date of spring should
change so it's a very precise Theory
it's a very narrow Theory it's hard to
vary and then to that I would also add
uh you know there are parts of his books
where we can read and he he adds a few
more uh not Criterion but these are
telltale signs and so I would say uh
good theories also often make risky and
narrow predictions so now when someone
make makes a good theory say it says
they good explanation they have a new
Theory it's like okay well let's test it
what what prediction are you making that
other people were not making that is a
high-risk prediction that if it turns
out to be true you'll be validated but
if it turned out not to be true then you
know egg on your face and it should be
hard to vary it should be fairly precise
prediction a narrow prediction and you
should be taking risk so I would add
that in another thing he talks about
which I think has been very helpful is
like you don't throw out your theory
just because there's a mistake in it you
only throw it out if you have a better
theory that explains what the previous
Theory did plus corrects the mistake and
that is a good Criterion for choosing
between alternative explanations um
induction oh my God he takes down
induction that's a huge one we live our
whole lives through induction the sun
rose yesterday so it'll rise tomorrow um
you know so humans are very inductive
creatures 1 2 3 4 5 then come 6 7 8 but
a lot of the interesting things in life
are explaining the scene in terms of the
Unseen which means that very often
things will happen that are nonlinear
that suddenly there's emerging
Properties or there's a nonlinearity or
kink in the curve which something
unexpected happens how do that happen
you're boiling water it goes 98 Degrees
99 degrees getting hotter and hotter and
hotter 100° oh it's really hot and then
stays at 100 what's going on well
turning into steam but the water's not
getting any hotter than 100 the steam is
hotter than the water you're going to
burn yourself on the steam or you can
drive an engine with more power with the
steam than you could with just the water
so clearly something here has happened
that you need to explain and life is
full of these um so that's another
example of where his epistemology has
been revolutionary another one is he's
not reductive so he doesn't say like
it's all about particle physics or the
fundamental layer of explanation
everything else above is just like made
up theories because you don't understand
particles no it's because they're
emerging properties at every scale you
can't you can't explain how we got how
you and I are sitting here without
applying to higher level theories about
uh you know capitalism and reasoning and
documentary film making and all that you
you can't just say well it's because of
particle collisions from The Big Bang
till now because that's the theory that
explains everything and theories that
explain everything explain nothing um so
you know an unpopular one is people
these days you know they'll say I'm
depressed I'm unhappy why cuz I I have a
chemical imbalance in my brain well
every mood you have is a chemical
imbalance in your brain that's not
helpful right yes that might be a way to
fix it maybe I can give you drugs that
will make you happy but it's not really
the underlying cause the underline cause
is probably there are things that are
making you depressed there are thoughts
that are making you depressed maybe
there external factors of how you want
things to be different that are making
you depressed but mere chemical
imbalance um it can be useful for trying
to fix it um but it's not really the
explanation at the right level of why
you might be unhappy and that's what
cognitive behavioral therapy tries to do
it tries to unravel why you might be and
happy and talk through it and think
through it and then reevaluate your
decisions and choices and it might help
you so I I think uh you know operating
at the right level of explanation he's
got tons of this by the way tons and
tons of it but uh there's lots of ways
in which it can improve your thinking um
you know all life is error correction um
all judgment is error correction um uh
you know just the core principle of like
you want explanations you won't be
satisfied with mere prediction um mere
prediction is not enough because the
world is a predictor uh you know you can
just if you want to see what's going to
happen next just wait the world will
show you um uh but you also want to
deeply understand why uh and at an expl
at a core level that's what an
explanation does it tries to answer the
question of why and that that I think is
a fundamental question that people
always ask but you can always ask why
that why that thing and because you can
always keep asking why you're always
going to have a new and better problem
underneath when you solve this one and
that's why there's an infinite number of
problems to be solve and you're always
at the beginning of infinity I think
poer and deuts both reject the uh
anything called the scientific method
which gets P into universities nowadays
it's like uh you it's kind of like
inductivist and empiricist a little bit
where you start with observations and
then you form a theory but without a
problem you can't um form any
observations in the first place and some
of these theories come so far out a left
field um in physics it's more obvious
relatively relativity and quantum
mechanics um are exact examples that
come out of left field uh where it it's
not like uh Einstein just dropped more
apples in Newton and then eventually got
to relativity know he just did these
crazy thought experiments that looked
like they had no bearing on anything no
scientist was even talking about them in
inductive sense like go from A to B to C
to D um and then ended up with um with
relativity um but you know even in
simple like everyday life it's like
should I eat chicken or should I eat
beef right
well a a a simple empirical model would
be like well let's lay all the food out
in front of us let me take the but
humans are incredibly creative I just
like I don't want to eat at all I'm
going I'm just not going to eat I'm just
going to fast or I'm just going to drink
or I'm going to make a smoothie out of
this um or I'm going to just throw it
all together so creativity is unbounded
and unlimited so just uh extrapolating
inductively will not get you to the best
answers and the best explanations and
computers are very good at induction um
and a scientific method the moment you
have a method you program it you can
write a program for well if you if you
can write a program for creativity
that's called AGI let me know when you
have it um but until then uh just
programming a method in that just in
just repeats experiments and uses
induction to go a little bit
further um will not get you the best
explanations induction has its place uh
when you're trying to figure out if the
sun's going to rise tomorrow or you know
how much prices are going to go up next
year probably uh induction is very
useful induction works really well in
what Nim TB calls mediocre stand the
space that we operate in most of our
everyday lives but it's not uh it's not
how you want to form a theory or an
underlying explanation of how something
works you can use induction when you
have nothing else to try and predict
what's going to happen next and that's
human nature but you're not going to use
to come up with good explanations of
what's actually going on underneath uh
the Nim TB example that he likes to give
is that uh you know the turkey is being
fed by the farmer and every day it gets
like a nice meal it's like wow this
farmer loves me it's such a benevolent
farmer and Thanksgiving show next gets
cut off cuz it had a bad explanation of
what was going on it was purely
inductive what do you think about the
lwh hanging fruit Theory uh of knowledge
and um I guess like does that explain
the uh slow progress that you seen the
slow down of progress that you've seen
in physics and other scientific Fields I
don't I don't think that's a good
explanation I think the uh first of all
if we're going to run out low hang fruit
we would have run out a long time ago um
so I I don't think I don't know why you
can pick an arbitrary point in the curve
and say this is the point where we run
out um I think it's it's much more
around
um you
know I think science and Academia right
now suffers from a lot of group think um
new ideas are aggressively rejected um
we don't have as many natural
philosophers anymore kind of just off
doing their own thing and just trying to
um figure out better explanations
there's a lot of Reliance on oh we need
a super collider or a bigger telescope
um there's a lot of group think like 30
people's names on a paper um entire
areas of scientific research are sort of
kind of closed off or forbidden
especially in the biological sciences
and genetics um partially for political
reasons partially just because uh you
know no bureaucrat will let you do
anything that might ever harm a single
person because it reflects poorly on
them um and I actually think we are
making a lot of progress it's just not
uh it may not be it may not seem as
fundamental like for a simple example
the theory of quantum computation that
deuts came up with or the Multiverse
Theory uh or Constructor theory that
he's working on I'm sure there other
scientists who working on lots of other
interesting things quantum gravity time
Etc um they may just not have had the uh
immediate visible output but all it
takes is one person figures out the
theory of dark energy and if we can
harness that wow or if we actually get
coal Fusion working that would be huge
um so I I do think more theoretical
breakthroughs are already happening
you're seeing a lot of math conjectures
solv you can see the advances in
Computing how machine learning has
completely turned the whole field upside
down its head and the theory is actually
now trying to catch up to the reality um
the pace of technological progress has
been tremendous uh and you could also
argue that that technological progress
itself is you know Theory struggling to
catch up to it a lot of like we still
don't even exactly know the turbulence
mechanics of helicopters and how they
fly so sometimes technology out and
Engineering outpaces the theory um
nothing wrong with that the theory has
to catch up um so I I don't think it's a
low I don't think lwh hanging fruit is a
good explanation I think it's it it may
be a combination of we have it and we're
still applying it we have it in
technology uh we're looking in the wrong
places with the wrong in kind of the
wrong group thinky way is um we're
relying too much on uh very large and
very expensive equipment um we have this
grant system where I think the average
person who gets a grant in University
now is 48 um whereas most of the
scientific breakthroughs tended to come
through people in their 20s or teen late
teens um so maybe the wrong people are
getting the money and the
encouragement it's hard to say final
question what do you think are the
biggest threats to Western civilization
right now let's get as specific as we
can
well I think the first thing is you want
freedom of thought and communication
that comes with freedom of speech so I
think any efforts to Li limit speech are
misguided there's no such thing as
misinformation your information is my
misinformation my information is your
misinformation that's just putting
somebody who gets to Define what
misinformation is in charge so I think
censorship has to be resisted strongly
secondly I think the the the society is
always structured around the ability to
do violence like it or not because the
people with the guns fundament mentally
eventually need to get paid or they take
over so I I you know even though I
myself am not uh you know I think
they're terrible things that happen with
guns and a lot of crimes and school
shooting soone get committed with guns I
do think that you need something like
the Second Amendment where the citizens
are the ones who are armed because then
they have a chance to speak up against a
government that does not redress their
Grievances and also because freedom of
speech goes away if you can't if you
cannot back up what you believe with
your own ability to inflict violence
when you are threatened then your
freedoms will be eventually taken away
it's just a matter of time and I think
we're seeing that across the world most
of the world lives in unfree societies
um and I think that trend is just
getting worse so I think that is a
difficult
thing
um religion is still around it's just
masquerading is secular so you know that
that invisibility gives it kind of a
mind virus
characteristic
um other threats I mean there is there
is truth to the fact that some kinds of
knowledge are almost Forbidden Knowledge
um in the sense that
like a single virus could end most of
the human species a nuclear war could
end most of the human species the
problem is not discovering these things
you can't stop Discovery and everything
good has a bad kind of side to it in
technology but what hap what the the
tough part happens when the people who
discover it are not the people who are
wielding it and not the people who hold
on to it that knowledge gets spread very
quickly so for example countries that
could never that don't have the
civilization structure and the knowledge
structure and the moral structure to
develop nuclear weapons get nuclear
weapons right and they become the
delivery systems for other cynical
people but again the only way out is
through you can't kind of stop people
because the people who are doing the
stopping then end up with everything
this is this is the mistake that I think
a lot of young people make they believe
in institutions as being infallible so
they basically say well we'll just stop
all the racist from talking and will'll
stop all the evil people from having
guns who's going to do that because
those people will be the evil ones I
guarante you the lesson of History over
and over and over is the people who are
in charge with the guns who are telling
you what to do and what you can't do and
what you can own what you can't own they
end up in charge this is why every
Marxist Revolution ends up with a single
Thug on top uh pole pot running Cambodia
ma dong killing everybody in China
Stalin running Soviet Russia uh Chavez
and Maduro running Venezuela because
when you can no longer allocate
resources through Merit your only
remaining option is to allocate them
through Power even if we live in a
communist Utopia who has to clean the
toilets somebody has to clean the
toilets who's living on the beachfront
property and who's living Inland well
someone you know coincidentally it ends
up being the friends of the people with
guns aka the Communist Party um or the
ruling family so these are just
monarchies by another name they're just
more popular instead of appealing to uh
God and saying I'm ruling because I have
the div divine right of kings and God is
telling me to rule instead these uh
dictators and thugs are saying I'm
ruling on behalf of the people I have
the Divine masses of the people behind
me the state is behind me so I think
that the these are just uh the modern
versions of the old uh Divine
monarchies um we' we've evolved things
have gotten better but there's still
more ways to go um so if I had to say I
would say the greatest greatest threats
um to the Future are suppression of
freedom of speech freedom of mathematics
freedom of expression freedom of
creation
and those are pointless if they can't be
backed up by violence if you don't have
your own ability to inflict violence it
will be taken away from you uh you know
one recent tweet I had was I said the
right to vote does not give you power
power gives you the right to vote you
can just do a simple thought exercise if
there were 100 of us on a on a desert
island uh and we're trapped and we all
kind have to cooperate to make Society
to create a new Society Suppose there
are 10 of us who are 10 people on the
island who are all from the same ethnic
background who are all extremely unified
they have all the guns those 10 have it
the other 90 don't who do you think is
going to end up running the place for
the benefit of the others anyone who's
been around the block a few times knows
what's going to happen so it's just the
nature of humans that if you want
freedom at the individual level if you
want the rights to be dispersed and
distributed and the power has to be
dispersed and distributed um and there's
very few institutions and organizations
that do that um really it's the right to
bear arms cryptography Free Speech
mathematics personal Computing um these
are examples of decentralized
Technologies and capabilities that
spread power amongst people most things
concentrate power mic drop that was
awesome thank you so much appreciate the
time