great job nabal you rocked it maybe I
should have said this on air but that
was literally the most fun podcast I've
ever recorded oh that's on air cut that
in yeah put it in the show put it in the
show I had my theory on why you were
number one but now I have the
realization what's the actual reason you
know us for a long time yeah what was
your theory what's a reality my theory
was that my problem with going on
podcast is usually the person I'm
talking to is not that interesting
they're just asking the same questions
and they're dialing it in and they're
not that interested it's not like we're
having a peer level actual conversation
so that's why I wanted to do air chat
and Clubhouse and things like that cuz
you can actually have a conversation I
see right and what you guys have very
uniquely is four people you know of whom
at least three are intelligent I'm
kidding how could you say that isn't
here what SX isn't even hearing you say
that that is so cold best right these
three are intelligent and all of you get
along and you can have an ongoing
conversation that's a very high hit rate
normally in a podcast you only get one
interesting person and now you've got
three maybe four right okay so that to
me was why Su and by you're talking to
is number four we don't know she remain
mysterious forever of the four right the
problem is like if you get people
together to talk two is a good
conversation three possibly four is the
max that's why in a dinner table at a
restaurant four top right you don't do
five or six because then exp splits into
multiple conversations so you had four
people who were capable of talking right
that I thought thought was a secret but
there's another secret the the other
secret is you guys are having fun you're
talking over each other you're making
fun of each other you're actually having
fun so that's why I'm saying this is the
most fun podcast I've ever been on and
that's that's why you'll be welcome back
anytime no all welcome back yes
absolutely in three smart
[Music]
guys I can't even believe you'd say that
about sax he's not even here to defend
himself sorry David
let your winners
[Music]
ride we open sources to the fans and
they've just gone crazy with
[Music]
it all right everybody welcome back to
the number one podcast in the world
we're really excited today back again
your sultant of science David
freeberg what do you got going on there
freeberg what's in the background
want I used to play I used to play a lot
of a game called Sim Earth on my
Macintosh LC way back in the day that
tracks yeah that tracks and of course
with us again your chairman what games
did you play growing up J actually I'm
kind of curious did you ever play video
games let's say Andrea Allison uh Susan
I mean it was like a lot of cute girls I
was out dating girls freeberg yeah I was
not on my Apple tun playing civilization
let me find one of those pictures of who
whoa don't get me in trouble Man the 80s
were ' 80s were good to me in Brooklyn
rejection the video
game yes you have three lives rejected
rejected it's a numbers game chamal as
you know as you well know it is a
numberous game yeah Nick go ahead pull
up uh pull up Rico Suave here oh no what
is this one instead of playing video
here I am no the80s that's fat that's
fat J you want get
Nick help out help out your unle yeah
here he is out slaying help out your
uncle with the VIN Jak C you know what
he was sling in there snack yeah you
pric and post asmic right correct and
weightlifting beef
jerky go find my Leonardo decaprio
picture please and replace my fat jow
picture with that thank you oh God I was
fat man plus 40 lbs is a lot heavier
than I it's no joke it's no joke 40b a
lot I there's so many great emo photos
of me I'm proud of you thank you my man
thank you my man if you want a good can
you get through the intros please so we
can start come on quick how you doing
brother how you doing chairman
dictator you
good all right all right we're really
excited today today for the first time
on the Allin podcast the Iron Fist of
Angel list the zenik mage of the early
stage he has such a way with words he's
the socer te of nerds please welcome my
guy Namaste Nal how you doing the intros
are back that is the best intro I've
ever gotten I didn't think I don't I
didn't think you could do that that was
amazing that's your super power right
there lock it in quit Venture Capital
just do that absolutely that's actually
you know what interestingly number one
podcast in the world like someone said I
mean that's what I'm manifesting it's
getting close we've been in the top 10
so I mean the weekends are good for all
in this this one will hit number one
this one will go vir I think it could if
you have some really great piffy
insights we might go right to the top I
just got to do a seile and it'll go
viral oh no oh no are you gonna send us
your heart my heart goes out to you my
heart I I end here at the heart I don't
send it out I keep it right here I put
both hands on the heart and I hold it
nice and stady I hold it in it's sending
out to you but just not explicitly all
right for those of you who don't know
Naval was an entrepreneur uh he kicked a
bit of ass he got his ass kicked and
then he started Venture
hacks and he started emailing folks and
saying you know 20 15 20 years ago maybe
15 here are some deals in Silicon Valley
he went around he started writing 50k
100K checks he hit a bunch of home runs
and he turned Venture hacks into Angel
list and then he has invested in a ton
of great startups uh maybe give us some
of the greatest hits there
Dev yeah Twitter Uber notion bunch of
others um Postmates you to me lot of
unicorns buch up coming I it's actually
a lot of deals at this point but
honestly I'm not necessarily proud of
being an investor investor to me is a
side job it's a hobby so I do startups
how how do you define
yourself I don't I mean I guess these
days I would say more like building
things you know every
every so-called career is an evolution
right and all of you guys are
independent and you kind of do what
you're most interested in right that's
the point of making money so you can
just do what you want so these days I'm
really into building and crafting
products so I built one recently called
airchat it kind of didn't work I'm still
proud of what I built and got to work
with an incredible team and now I'm
building a new product and this time I'm
going into Hardware oh and I'm just
building something that I really want I
I'm not it all yourself Nal
partially I bring investors along last
time they got their money back previous
times they've made money next time
hopefully they'll make a lot of money
it's good to bring your friends along
I'll be honest I love that you said I
love the product but it didn't work not
enough people say that yeah I know I I
built a product that I loved that I was
proud of but it didn't catch fire and it
was a social product so it had to catch
fire for it to work so I found the team
great homes they all got paid the
investors that I brought in got their
money back and I learned a ton which I'm
leveraging into the new thing but the
new thing is much harder the new thing
is hardware and software and what did
you what did you learn building in 2024
and 20125 that you didn't know maybe
before then the main thing was actually
just the craft the craft of pixel by
pixel designing a software product and
launching it I guess the main thing I
took away that was a learning was that I
really enjoyed building products and
that I wanted to build something even
harder and something even more real and
I think like a lot of us I'm inspired by
Elon and you know all the incredible
work he's done so I don't want to build
things that are easy I want to build
things that are hard and interesting and
I want to take on more technical risk
and less Market risk this is the classic
VC learning right which is you want to
build something that if people get it if
you can deliver it you know people will
want it and it's just hard to build as
opposed to you build it and you don't
know if they want it so that's a
learning air chat was a lot of fun for
those of you who don't know it was kind
of like a social media Network where you
could ask a question and then people
could respond and it was like an
audio-based Twitter would you say that
was the the best way to describe it
audio Twitter asynchronous AI
transcripts and all kinds of AI to make
it easier for you
translation really good way for kind of
try to make podcasting type
conversations more accessible to
everybody cuz honestly one of the
reasons I don't go on podcast I don't
like being intermediated so to speak
right where you sit there and someone
interviews you and then you go back and
forth and you go through the same old
things I just want to talk to people I
want peer relationships kind of like you
guys have running here nval what
happened when you went through that
phase there was a period where it just
seemed like something had gone on in
your life and you just knew the answers
you were just so grounded it's not to
say that you're not grounded now but
you're you're less active posting and
writing but there was this period where
I think all of us were like right what
does nval think oh really oh okay that's
USS to be I would say it would be like
the late teens the early 20s Jason you
can correct me if I'm getting the dates
wrong but it's been that moment where
like these Naval isms and this sort of
philosophy really started to I think
people had a tremendous respect for how
you were thinking about things I I'm
just curious like what were you going
through something in that moment or like
oh yeah yeah yeah yeah that's right no
very insightful yeah 20 so i' I've been
on Twitter since 2007 cuz I was an early
investor but I never really tweeted I
didn't get featured I had no audience I
was just doing the usual techie guy
thing talking to each other and then I
started Angelus in 2010 the original
thing about matching investors to
startups didn't scale it was just an
email list that exploded at early on but
then just didn't scale so we didn't have
a
business and I was trying to figure out
the business and at the same time I got
a letter from the Securities and
Exchange Commission saying oh you're
acting as an unlic broker dealer and I'm
like what I'm not making any money I'm
not I'm just making intros I'm not
taking anything it's just a public
service but even then they were coming
after me so I wasn't and I'd raised a
bunch of money from investors so I was
in a very high stress period of my life
now looking back it's almost comical
that I was stressed over but at the time
it all felt very real the weight of
everything was on my shoulders
expectations people money regulators and
I eventually went to DC and got the law
change to legalize what we do which
ironically enabled a whole bunch of
other things like icos and incubator
days and so on demo days but in that
process I was in a very high stress
period of my life and I just started
tweeting whatever I was going through
whatever realizations I was happening
it's only in stress that you sort of are
forced to grow and so whatever internal
growth I was going through I just
started tweeting it not thinking much of
it and it was a mix of there are three
things that I kind of always kind of are
running through one is I love science
you know I'm an amateur love physics
let's just leave it at that I love
reading a lot of philosophy and thinking
deeply about it and I like making money
right truth Love and Money that's my
joke on my Twitter bio those are the
three things that I keep coming back to
and so I just started tweeting about all
of them and I
think before that the expectation was
that someone like me should just be
talking about money stay in your lane
and people had been playing it very safe
and so I think the combination of the
three sort of caught people's attentions
because every person thinks about
everything we don't just stay in our
Lane in real life we're dealing with our
relationships we're dealing with our
relationship with the universe we're
dealing with what we know to be true and
you know with science and how we make
decisions and how we figure things out
and we're also dealing with a practical
everyday material things of how to deal
with our spouses or girlfriends or wives
or husbands and how to make money and
how to deal with our children so I'm
just tweeting about everything I just
got interested in everything I'm
tweeting about it and a lot of it my
best stuff was just notes to self it's
like hey don't forget this how to get
rich remember that one how to get rich
that like one theads and super Yeah Bang
Yeah Yeah Yeah I think that is still the
most viral threat ever on Twitter I like
Timeless things I I like philosophy I
like things that are still apply in the
future I like compound interests if you
will in
ideas obviously recently X has become so
addictive that we're all checking it
every day and elon's built the perfect
for you he's built Tik Tok for nerds and
we're all on it but normally I try to
ignore the news obviously last year
things got real we all had to pay of
attention to the news but I just like to
tweet Timeless things I I don't know I
mean people pay attention sometimes they
like what I write sometimes they they go
non ler on me but yeah the how to get
rich sweet storm was a big one is it
problematic when people now meet you
because the the hype versus the reality
there's like it's discordant now because
people if they absorb this content they
expect to see
Somey da yeah floating in the in the air
you know what I mean yes yeah like many
of you have stopped drinking but I used
to like have the occasional glass of
wine and there was a moment there where
I went and met with an information
reporter back when I used to meet with
reporters and she said where are we
going to meet so I said oh let's meet at
the the wine merchant and we'll get a
glass she's like what you drink like it
was like a big deal for I'm so
disappointed I was like I'm an
entrepreneur most of them are alcoholics
or and psychedelics or yeah for sure
takes to
man hot tub yeah right yeah when they
say I'm on therapy you know what that
that's code for um so yes it is highly
Discord medine yeah I'm I'm almost
reminded of that line in The Matrix
where that agent is about to like shoot
one of the Matrix characters and says
only human right so that's kind I want
to say to everybody like only human yeah
yeah yeah you did a recently a podcast
with Tim Ferris on parenting this was
out there I love this and I bought the
book from this guy yeah just give a a
brief overview of this philosophy of
parenting oh I didn't listen to this I
have to write this down tell us this
you're going to love this I this spoke
to me but it was a little crazy yeah so
I'm a big fan of David Deutsch David
deuts I think is basically the smartest
living human he's a scientist who yeah
Quantum computation and he's written a
couple of great books but it's about the
intersection of the greatest theories
that we have today the theories with the
most reach and those are epistemology
the theory of knowledge Evolution
quantum physics and computation this is
the beginning of infinity guy that's
theity is always reference correct yes
the fabric of reality is another book
I've spent a fair bit of time with him
done some podcasts with him hired and
worked with people around him and I'm
just really impressed because it's like
the the framework that's made me smarter
I feel like because we're all fighting
aging our brains are getting slower and
we're always trying to have better ideas
so as you age you should have wisdom
that's your substitute for the raw
horsepower of intelligence going down
and so scientific wisdom I take from
David not take but you know I learned
from David and one of the things that he
pioneered is called taking children
seriously and it's this idea that you
should take your children seriously like
adults you should always give them the
same Freedom that you would give an
adult if you wouldn't speak that way
with your spouse if you wouldn't force
your spouse to do something don't force
a child to do something and it's only
through the latent threat of physical
violence hey I can control you I can
make you go to your room I can take your
dinner away or whatever that you
intimidate children and it resonated
with me because I grew up very very free
my father wasn't around when I was young
my mother didn't have the bandwidth to
watch us all the time she had other
things to do and so I kind of was making
my own decisions from a extremely young
age from the age of five nobody was
telling me what to do and from the age
of nine I was telling everybody what to
do so I'm used to that and I've been
homeschooling my own kids so the
philosophy resonated and I found this
guy Aaron stuple on air chat and he was
an incredible Expositor of the
philosophy he lives his life with it 99%
as Extreme as one can go so his kids can
eat all the ice cream they want and all
the Snickers bars they want they can
play on the iPad all they want they
don't have to go to school if they don't
feel like it they dress how they want
they don't have to do anything they
don't want to do everything is a
discussion negotiation explanation just
like you would with a roommate or an
adult living in your house and it's kind
of insane and extreme but I live my own
home life in that Arc in that direction
and I'm a very free person I don't have
an office to go to I try really not to
maintain a calendar if I can't remember
it I don't want to do it I don't send my
kids to school I really try not to coers
them and so obviously that's an extreme
model but I was sorry sorry sorry hold
on a second so yeah your kids if they if
they were like I want hog and and it's
900 p.m. you're like okay two nights ago
I did this I ordered the hog andas it
wasn't hog andas it was a different
brand I ordered it
I'm just going to go through a couple of
examples in we do ice cream at 9:00 p.m.
and we all ate so they're like Dad I
want and they're happy they're happy
kids I want to be on my iPad I'm playing
fortnite leave me alone I'll go to sleep
when I want you're like okay my oldest
probably plays iPad nine hours a day
okay so then your other kid pees in
their pants because they're too lazy to
walk to the bathroom they don't do that
because they don't like peeing their
pants no I understand but I'm just
saying like there's a spectrum of all of
these things right yeah and your point
of view is 100% of it is allowed and you
have no judgments no no that's not where
I am that's where that's where Aaron is
my rules are a little different my rules
are they got to do one hour of math or
programming plus two hours of reading
every single day and the moment they've
done that they're free creatures and
everything else is a negotiation we have
to persuade them it's a persuasion I
should say not even a negotiation and
even the hour of math and 2 hours of
reading really you get 15 to 30 minutes
of math maybe an hour if you're lucky
and you get half an hour to two hours of
reading if and what do you think the
long-term consequences of that are and
then also what is the long-term
consequences let's say on health if
they're making decisions you know are
just not good like the ice cream thing
at 9:00 p.m. how do you how do you
manage that in your mind I think
whatever age you're at whatever part
you're at in life you're still always
struggling with your own habits I think
all of us for example still eat food and
feel guilty or want to eat something
that we shouldn't be eating and we're
still always evolving our diets and kids
are the same so my oldest is already he
passed on the ice cream last time and he
said I want to eat healthier because
finally I managed to get through to him
and persuade him that he should be
healthier my younger kids will eat it
but they'll eat a limited amount my
middle kid will sometimes eat some so if
they say something you'll enable it but
then you'll guide you'll be like Hey
listen like this is not the choice I
would make I don't think but if you want
it I do it yeah I'll try it but you also
have to be careful where you don't want
to intimidate them and you don't want to
be so overbearing that then they just
view dad is like controll it I find this
so fasc and so what do you think happens
to these kids at the like I'm sure you
have a vision of what they'll be like
when they're fully formed adults like
what is that Vision I I try not to
they're going to be who they're going to
be I this is kind of how I grew up I
kind of did what I
wanted I I would ra I would rather they
have
agency than turn out exactly the way I
want cuz agency is the hardest thing
right having control over your own life
making your own decisions them to be
happy I have a very happy household what
is the Plato what's Plato's goal udonia
right like udonia yeah the happy arist
like the the Fulfillment this Con is
that what you want for
them I don't really want anything for
them I just want them to be free and
their best selves God I
want shamat is worrying about details
he's got like 17 kids now I don't know
if you know but shamat has got like a
whole punch list of things but I love
this interview because the guy made a
really interesting point which was
they're going to have to make these
decisions at some point they're going to
have to learn the pros and cons the the
the upside the downside to all these
things eating iPad and the quicker you
get them to have agency to make these
decisions for themselves with knowledge
to ask questions the more secure they'll
be I found it a fascinating discussion I
like cause and effect especially in
teenagers now that I have a teenager
it's really good for them to learn hey
you know if you don't do your homework
you you have a problem and then you got
to solve that problem how are we going
to solve that problem so I like to
present it as what's your plan anytime
they have a problem 8-year-old kids
15year old kids I just say what's your
plan to solve this and then I like to
hear their plan and let me know if you
want to brainstorm it but I thought it
was a very interesting super interesting
discussion I I would say overall my kids
are very happy the household is very
happy everybody gets along everybody
loves each other yeah
some of them are way ahead of their
peers nobody's behind in anything that
matters nobody seems unhealthy in any
obvious way no one has aberant eating
habits I haven't even found an really an
aberrate Behavior that's out of line so
it's all good self correct me it's like
a i wor I worry a lot about this like
iPad situation I see my kids on an iPad
and it's almost like unless they're
doing an
interactive project if they end up
watching says says the guy who has a
video game theme in the background that
was interactive who probably and who
probably grew up playing video games
nonstop and probably spends 9 hours a
day on his screen just called a phone so
yeah yeah it's the same thing man well I
mean I feel like watch is it but do they
watch
shows no there a h there there's a
hypocrisy to picking up your phone and
then saying to your kid no you can't use
your iPad I grew up playing video games
non-stop in video games when I was older
and I was an avid gamer until just a few
years ago well I'm not I'm not critic
izing the the iPad I was obviously on a
computer since I was four years old so I
totally get it and I think the question
for me is like but I didn't have the
ability to play a 30 minute show and
then play the next 30 minute show and
the next 30 minute show and then sit
there for two hours and just have a show
playing the whole time I was you know
interacting on the computer and doing
stuff and building stuff which was a
little different me from a use case
perspective yeah we we we did use to
control their YouTube access although
now we don't do that
the only thing I ask them is that they
put on captions when they're watching
YouTube so it helps their reading they
learn to read fast good tip yeah I like
that one I will say that one of my kids
is really into YouTube the other two are
not like they just got over it and to
the extent that they use YouTube it's
mostly because they're looking up videos
on their favorite games they want to
know how to be better at a game all
right let's keep moving through this
docket we have David Sachs with us here
so uh David give us your philosophy of
parenting okay next item on the docket
let's go
talk about some real
issues show is not a parenting show a
parenting show I asked D what's your
parenting philosophy he said oh I set up
their trust four years ago so he's done
he's good trust is set up everything's
good g r a t
check you're all set guys let me know
how it works out all right speaking of
working out we've got a vice president
who isn't cuckoo for Coco Puffs and who
actually understands what AI is JD Vance
gave a great speech I watched it myself
he talked about AI in Paris this was on
Tuesday at the AI action Summit whatever
that is and he gave a 15minute banger of
a speech he talked about over regulating
Ai and America's intention to dominate
this and we happen to have with US Naval
the Zar the Zar of AI so before I go
into all the details about the speech I
don't steal your thunder sax this this
uh Speech had a lot of uh verbage a lot
of ideas that I've heard before that
maybe we've all talked about maybe tell
us a little bit about how this all came
together and how proud you are I mean
gosh having a vice president who
understands AI is just it's mind-blowing
he could speak on a
topic that's topical credibly this was
an awesome moment for America I think
what are you implying there JC I'm
implying you have workshopped it with
him no or that he's smart both of those
things the vice president wrote the
speech or at least directed all of it so
the ideas came from him I'm not going to
take any credit whatsoever for this okay
well it was on point maybe you could
talk about I agree it was on point I
think it was a very well crafted and
well- delivered speech he made four main
points about the Trump administration's
approach to AI he's going to ensure this
is point one that American AI continues
to be the gold standard fantastic check
two he says that the administration
understands that excessive regulation
could kill AI just as it's taking off
and he did this in front of all the EU
Elites who love regulation did it on
their home court and then he said number
three AI must remain free from
ideological bias as we've talked about
here on this program and then number
four the White House he said will quote
maintain a pro-worker growth path for AI
so that it can be a potent tool for job
creation in the US so what are your
thoughts on the four major bullet points
and and his speech here in uh Paris well
I think that the vice president you knew
he was going to deliver an important
speech as soon as he got up there and
said that I'm here to talk about not AI
safety but AI opportunity and to
understand what a bracing statement that
was and really almost like a shot across
the bow you have to understand the
history and context of these events for
the last couple of years the last couple
of these events have been exclusively
focused on AI safety the last inperson
event was in the UK at Bletchley Park
and the whole conference was devoted to
AI safety similarly the European AI
regulation obviously is completely
preoccupied with safety and trying to
regulate Away safety risks before they
happen similarly you had the Biden EO
which was based around safety and then
you have just the whole media coverage
around AI which is preoccupied with all
the risks from AI so to have the vice
president get up there and say right off
the bat that there are other things to
talk about in respect to AI besides
safety risk that actually there are huge
opportunities there was a breath of
fresh air and like I said kind of a shot
across the bow and yeah you could almost
see some of the eurocrats they needed
their fainting couches after that
eurocrats
trudo looks like his dog just died so I
think that was just a really important
statement right off the bat to the
context for the speech which is AI is a
huge opportunity for all of us because
really that point just has not been made
enough and it's true there are risks but
when you look at the media coverage and
when you look at the dialogue that The
Regulators have had around this they
never talk about the opportunities it's
always just around the wrist so I think
that was a very important corrective and
then like you said he went on to say
that the United States has to win this
AI race we want to be the gold standard
we want to dominate that was my favorite
part yeah and and by the way that
language about dominating Ai and and
winning the global race that is in
president Trump's executive order from
week one so this is very much
elaborating on the official policy of of
this Administration and the vice
president that went on to say that he
specified how we would do that right we
have to win some of these key building
block Technologies we want to win in
chips we want to win in AI models we
want to win in applications he said we
need to build we need to unlock energy
for these companies and then most of all
we just need to be supportive towards
them as opposed to regulating them to
death and he had a lot to say about the
the risk of overregulation
how often it's big companies that want
regulation he warned about regulatory
capture which our friend Bill Gurley
would like and he said that so basically
having less regulation can actually be
more fair can create a More Level
Playing Field for small companies as
well as big companies and then he he
said to the Europeans that we want you
to be partners with us we want to lead
the world we want you to be our our
partners and benefit from this
technology that we're going to take the
lead in creating but you also have to be
a good partner to us and then he
specifically called out the
overregulation that Europeans have been
engaged in he mentioned the Digital
Services act which has acted as like a
speed trap for American companies it's
American companies who've been
overregulation because the truth of the
matter is that it's American technology
companies that are winning the race and
so when Europe passes these owner
regulations they fall most of all on
American companies and he's basically
saying we need you to rebalance and and
correct this because it's not fair and
it's not smart policy and it's not going
to help us collectively win this AI race
and that kind of brings me just to to
the last point is I don't think he
mentioned China by name but clearly he
talked about adversarial countries who
are using AI to control their
populations to engage in censorship and
thought control and he basically painted
a picture where it's like yeah you could
go work with them or you could work with
us and we we have hundreds of years of
shared history together we believe in
things like free speech hopefully and we
want you to work with us but if you are
going to work with us then you have to
cooperate and we have to create a
reasonable regulatory regime Nal did you
see the uh Speech and your thoughts just
generally on JD Vance and and having
somebody like this you know representing
us and wanting to win American exception
very surprising very impressive I
thought he was polite
optimistic and just very forward-looking
just it's what you would expect an
entrepreneur or a smart investor to say
so I was very impressed I think the idea
that America should win great I think
that we should not regulate I also agree
with I'm not an AI Doomer I don't think
AI is going to end the world that's a
separate conversation but there's this
religion that comes along in many faces
which is that oh climate change is going
to end the world a going to end the
world asteroids going to end the world
covid-19 is going to end the world and
it just has a way of fixating your
attention right it captures everybody's
attention at once so it's a very
seductive thing and I think in the case
of AI it's really been overplayed by
incentive bias you know motivated
reasoning by the companies were ahead
and they want to pull up the ladder
behind them I I think they genuinely
believe it I think they genuinely
believe that there's safety risk but I
think they're motivated to believe in
those safety risks and then they pass
that along but it's kind of a weird
position because they have to say oh
it's so dangerous that you shouldn't
just let open source go at it and you
should let just a few of us work with
you on it but it's not so dangerous that
a private company can't own the whole
thing right because if it was truly the
Manhattan Project if they were building
nuclear weapons you wouldn't want one
company to own that no Sam wman famously
said that AI will capture the light cone
of all future value in other words like
all value ever created at the speed of
light from here will be captured by AI
so if that's true then I think open-
Source AI really matters and little Tech
AI really matters the problem is that
the nature of training these models is
highly centralized they benefit from
supercomputer clustered compute so it's
not clear how any decentralized model
can compete so to me the real issue
boils down to is how do you push AI
forward while not having just a very
small number of players control the
entire thing and we thought we had that
solution with the original open AI which
was a nonprofit was supposed to do for
Humanity but now because of they want to
incentivize the team and they want to
raise money they have to privatize at
least a part of it although it's not
clear to me why they need to privatize
the whole thing like why they need to
buy out the nonprofit portion you could
leave a nonprofit portion and you could
have the private portion for the
incentives but I think that the the real
challenge is how do you keep AI from
naturally centralizing because all the
economics and the technology underneath
are centralizing in nature if you really
think you're going to create God do you
want to put God on a leash with one
entity controlling God that to me is the
real fear not I'm not scared of AI I'm
scared of what a very small number of
people who control AI do to the rest of
us for our own good because that's how
it always works it's well said probably
should go with the Greek model having
many gods and uh Heroes as well freeberg
you heard the uh JD van speech I assume
what are your thoughts on overregulation
and uh maybe to nal's point one person
owning this versus open source I think
that there's this kind of big definition
of social balance right now on what I
would call techno optimism and techno
pessimism generally people sort of fall
into one of those two camps generally
speaking techno
optimists I would say are folks that
believe that accelerating outcomes with
AI with automation with bioengineering
manufacturing semiconductors Quantum
Computing nuclear energy Etc will usher
in this era of abundance by making by
creating leverage which is what
technology gives us
technology will make things cheaper and
it will be deflationary and it will give
everyone more so it creates abundance
the challenge is that people who already
have a lot worry more about the exposure
to the downside than they desire the
upside and so you know the techn
pessimists are generally like the EU and
large Parts frankly of the United States
are worried about the loss of X the loss
of jobs the loss of this the loss of
that whereas countries like China and
India are more excited about the
opportunity to create wealth the
opportunity to create leverage the
opportunity to create abundance for
their people you know GDP per capita in
in the EU $60,000 a year GDP per capita
in the United States like 82,000 but GDP
per capita in India is 2500 and China is
12,600 there's a greater incentive in
those countries uh to manifest upside
than there is for the United States and
the EU who are more worried about
manifesting downside and so it is a very
difficult kind of social battle that's
underway I do think like over time those
governments and those countries and
those social systems that Embrace these
Technologies are going to become more
capitalist and they're going to require
less government control and intervention
in job creation the economy payments to
people and so on and the countries that
are more techn pessimistic are
unfortunately going to find themselves
asking for greater government control
govern intervention in markets
governments creating jobs government
making payments to people government's
effectively running the economy my
personal view obviously is that I'm a
very strong advocate for technology
acceleration because I think in nearly
every case in human history when a new
technology has emerged we've largely
found ourselves assuming that the
technology works in the framework of
today or of yester year the automobile
came along and no one envisioned that
everyone in the United States would own
an automobile and therefore you would
need to create all of these new
Industries like mechanics and car
dealerships roads all the people
servicing building roads and all the
other industry that emerg and it's it's
very hard for us to sit here today and
say okay AI is going to destroy jobs
what's it going to create and be right I
think we're very likely going to be
wrong whatever estimations we we give
the area that I think is most
underestimated is large technical
projects that seem technically
infeasible today that AI can unlock for
example habitation in in the oceans like
it's very difficult for us to Envision
like creating cities underwater and
creating cities in the oceans or
creating cities on the moon or creating
cities on mars or finding new places to
live those are like technically people
might argue oh that sounds stupid I
don't want to go do that but at the end
of the day like human civilization will
drive us to want to do that but those
technically are very hard to pull off
today but AI can unlock a new set of
Industries to enable those transitions
so I think we really get it wrong when
we try and assume the technology as a
transplant for last year or last century
and then we kind of become techn
pessimists because we're worried about
losing what we have are you a techn
pessimist are you Optimist because I you
uh bring up the downside of awful lot
here on the program but you are working
every day in a very optimistic way to
breed you know better strawberries and
potatoes for folks so you're a little
bit of a no I have no techn pessimism
whatsoever I try and point out why the
other side is acting the way they are
got it okay putting it in full context
and what I'm trying to highlight is I
think that that framework is wrong I
think that that
frame
transology the way operating the way
about and it creates this you know
because of this manifestation about
worrying about downside it creates this
fear that that creates regulation like
we see in the EU and as a result China's
GDP will scale while the euus will
stagnate if that's where they go that's
my assessment or my opinion on what will
happen chath you want to wrap this up
for us what are your thoughts on JD I'll
give you two okay the first is I would
say this is a really interesting
moment where I would call this the tale
of two vice presidents very early in the
Biden Administration kamla was
dispatched on an equally important topic
at that time which was illegal
immigration and she went to Mexico and
Guatemala and so you actually have a
really interesting AB test here you have
both vice presidents dealing with what
we're in that moment incredibly
important issues and I think that JD was
focused he was precise he was
ambitious and even the part of the press
that was very supportive of kamla
couldn't find a lot of very positive
things to say about her and the feedback
was it was Meandering she was ducking
questions she didn't answer the
questions that she was asked very well
and it's so interesting because it's a
bit of a microcosm then to what happened
over these next four years and her
campaign quite honestly which you could
have taken that window of that feedback
and unfortunately for her it just
continued to be very consistent so that
was one observation I had because I
heard him give the speech I heard her
and I had this kind of moment where I
was like wow two totally different
people the second is on the substance of
what JD said I said this on Tucker and
I'll just simplify all of this into a
very basic framework which
is if you want a country to thrive it
needs to have economic Supremacy
and it needs to have military
Supremacy in the absence of those two
things societies
crumble and the only thing that
underpins those two things is
technological Supremacy and we see this
today so on Thursday what happened with
Microsoft they had a $24 billion
contract with the United States Army to
deliver some whizbang thing and they
realized that they couldn't deliver it
and so what did they do they went to
andril now why did they go to andril
because andril has the technological
Supremacy to actually execute a few
weeks ago we saw some attempts at
technological Supremacy from the Chinese
with respect to deep seek so I think
that this is a very simple existential
battle those who can harness and
govern the things that are
technologically Superior will
win and it will drive economic vibrancy
and Military Supremacy which then
creates safe strong societies that's it
so from that perspective JD nailed it he
saw the forest from the trees he said
exactly what I think needed to be said
and put folks on notice that you're
either on the ship or you're off the
ship and I think that that was really
good yeah and there was like um a little
secondary conversation that emerged
Sachs that I I would love to engage you
with if you're willing which is this
Civil War quote unquote between maybe
Maga 1.0 magga 2.0 techies ver in the
Maga party like
ourselves and maybe the core Maga folks
we can pull up the Tweet here in JD's
own word and he's been engaging people
in his own words it's very clear that
he's writing these tweets a distinct
difference between other politicians and
this Administration and they just tell
you what they think here it is I'll try
and write something to address this in
detail this is JD Vance's tweet but I
think this Civil War is overstated
though yes there are some real
divergences between the populace I would
describe that as magga and the techies
but briefly in general I dislike
substituting American labor for cheap
labor my views on immigration and
offshoring flow from this I like growth
and productivity gains and this informs
my view on Tech and regulation when it
comes to AI specifically the risks are
number one overstate to your point Nal
or two difficult to avoid one of my any
real concerns for instance is about
Consumer Fraud that's a valid reason to
worry about safety but the other problem
is much worse if a pure nation is 6
months ahead of the US on AI again I'll
try and say more and this is JD going
right at I think one of the more
controversial topic
sacks that the administration is dealing
with and has dealt with when it comes to
immigration and Tech because these two
things are dovetailing each other if we
lose millions of driver jobs which we
will in the next 10 years just like we
lost millions of cashier jobs well
that's going to impact how our nation
and many of the voters look at the
border and immigration we might not be
able to let as many people immigrate
here if we're losing millions of jobs to
Ai and self-driving cars what are your
thoughts on him engaging this directly
saxs well the first point he's making
there is about wage pressure right which
is when you throw open our Borders or
you throw open American markets products
that can be made in foreign countries by
much cheaper labor that's not held to
the same standards the same minimum wage
or the same Union rules or the same
safety standards that American labor is
and has a huge cost Advantage then
you're creating wage pressure for
American workers and he's opposed to
that and I think that is an important
point because I think the way that the
media or neoliberals like to portray
this argument is that somehow mag's
resistance to unlimited immigration is
somehow based on xenophobia or something
like like that no it's based on bread
and butter kitchen table issues which is
if you have this ridiculous open border
policy it's inevitably going to create a
lot of wage pressure for people at the
bottom of the pyramid so I think JD is
making that argument but and this is
point two he's saying I'm not against
productivity growth so technology is
good because it enables all of our
workers to improve their productivity
and that should result in better wages
because workers can produce more the
value of their labor goes up if they
have more tools to be productive so
there's no contradiction there and I
think he's explaining why there isn't a
contradiction a point I would add he
doesn't make this point in that tweet
but I would add is that one of the
problems that we've had over the last I
don't know 30 years is that we have had
tremendous productivity growth in the US
but labor has not been able to capture
it all that benefit has basically gone
to Capital or to companies and I think a
big part of the reason why is because
we've had this largely unrestricted
immigration policy so I think if you
were to Tamp down on immigration if you
were to stop the illegal immigration
then labor might be able to capture more
of the benefits of productivity growth
and that would be a good thing it' be a
more equitable distribution of the gains
from productivity and from technology
and that I think would help Tamp down
this growing conflict that you see
between technologists and the rest of
the country or certainly the heartland
of the country nval this is a okay you
want to add anything else David sorry
well I think just the final point he
makes in that tweet is that he talks
about how we live in a world in which
there are other countries that are
competitive and specifically he he
doesn't mention China but he says we
have a pure competitor and it's going to
be a much worse world if they end up
being six months ahead of us on AI
rather than six months behind that is a
really important point to keep in mind I
think that the whole Paris AI Summit
took place against the backdrop of this
recognition because just a few weeks ago
we had deep seek and it's really clear
that China is not a year behind us
they're hot on our heels or only maybe
months behind us and so if we hobble
ourselves with unnecessary regulations
if we make it more difficult for our AI
companies to compete that doesn't mean
that China's going to follow suit and
copy us they're going to take advantage
of that fact and they're going to win
all right nval this seems to be one of
the main issues of our time four of the
five people on this podcast right now
are immigrants so we have this amazing
in America this is a country built by
immigrants for immigrants do you think
that should change now in the face of
job destruction which I know you've been
tracking self-driving pretty acutely we
both have an interest there I think over
the years you know what's the solution
here if we're going to see a bunch of
job displacement which will happen for
certain jobs we all we all kind of know
that should we shut the border and not
let the next Nal chamat Max and
freedberg into the country well let me
let me declare my biases up front I'm a
first generation immigrant I moved here
when I was 9 years old rather my parents
did and then I naturalized
citizen so obviously I'm in favor of
some level of immigration that said I'm
assimilated I consider myself an
American first and
foremost I bleed red white and blue I
believe in the Bill of Rights and the
Constitution first and second and fourth
and all the proper amendments I get up
there every July 4th and I deliberately
defend the Second Amendment on Twitter
at which point half my followers Go
Bananas you know cuz you're because I'm
not supposed to I'm supposed to be a
good immigrant right and and carry the
usual set of coherent leftist policies
globalist policies so I think that legal
High skill immigration with room and
time for assimilation makes sense you
want to have a brain drain on the best
and brightest coming to the freest
country in the world to build technology
and to help civilization move forward
and you know as chth was saying economic
power and military power is Downstream
of technology in fact even culture is
Downstream of Technology look at what
the birth control pill did for example
to culture or what the automobile did to
culture or what radio and television did
to culture and then the internet so
technology drives everything and if you
look at wealth wealth is a set of
physical Transformations that you can
affect and that's a combination of
capital and knowledge and the bigger
input to that is knowledge and so the US
has become the home of knowledge
creation thanks to bringing in the best
and brightest you could even argue deep
Seek part of the reason why we lost that
is because a bunch of those kids they
studied in the US but then we sent them
back home right so I think you
absolutely is that actually accurate
that they were uh yeah yeah yeah some a
few of them really oh my God that's like
exhibit a wow I didn't know that so I
think you absolutely have to split
skilled assimilated immigration which is
a small set and it has to be both they
have to both be skilled and they have to
become Americans that oath is not
meaningless right it has to mean
something so skilled assimilated
immigration you have to separate that
from just open borders whoever can
wander in just come on in that that
latter part makes no sense if the Biden
administration had only been letting in
people with 150 IQs we wouldn't have
this debate right now the reason why
we're having this debate is because they
just opened the border and let millions
and millions of people in it was to
their advantage to conflate legal and
illegal immigration so every time You'
be like well we can't just open the
Border say what about Elon what about
this and they would just parade if they
were just letting Elon and the Jensen
and freed bgs we wouldn't be having the
same conversation today the correlation
between open borders and wage
suppression is irrefutable we know that
data and I think that the
Democrats for whatever logic
committed an incredible error in
basically undermining their core cohort
I want to go back to what you said
because I think it's super important
there is a new political calculus on the
field and I agree with you I think that
the the three cohorts of the future are
the asset light working in middle class
that's cohort number one there are
probably 100 to 150 million of those
folks then there are patriotic business
owners and then there's leaders in
Innovation those are the three and I
think that what Maga gets right is they
found the middle ground that intersects
those three cohorts of people and so
every time you see this sort of left
versus right dichotomy it's totally
miscast and it sounds discordant to so
many of us because that's not how any of
us identify right and I think that
that's a very important observation
because the policies that we adapt will
need to reflect those three cohorts what
is the common ground amongst those three
and on that point nval is right there's
not lot that those three would say is
wrong with a very targeted form of
extremely useful legal immigration of
very very very smart people who agree to
assimilate and be a part of America I
mean I'm so glad you said it the way you
said it like I remember growing up where
my parents would try to pretend that
they were in Sri Lanka and sometimes I
would get so frustrated I'm like if you
want to be in Sri Lanka go back to Sri
Lanka I want to be Canadian because it
was easier for me to make friends it was
easier for me to have a life I was
trying my best I wanted to be Canadian
and then when I moved to the United
States 25 years ago I wanted to be
American and I feel that I'm American
now and I'm proud to be an American and
I think that's what you want you want
people that embrace it doesn't mean that
we can't dress up in a show AR CES every
now and then but the point is like what
do you believe and where is your loyalty
freeberg we used to have this concept of
in a Melting Pot of this assimilation
and that was a good thing then it became
cultural appropriation we we kind of
made a right turn here where where do
you stand on this recruiting the best
and brightest and forcing them to
assimilate making sure that they're down
Jason find the people that care to be
here yeah let me res that uh I reject
the premise this whole
conversation wait wait hold on look I'm
look I'm a first generation American who
moved here when I was five and became a
citizen when I was 10 and yes I'm fully
American and that's the only country I
have any loyalty to but I the the
premise that I reject here is that
somehow an AI conversation leads to an
immigration conversation because
millions of jobs are going to be lost we
don't know that that's also true I agree
you're making a huge assumption buying
into the
dorismond of jobs that is not those are
fact not evidence I think any jobs have
any jobs been lost by AI let's be real
we've had AI for two and a half years
and I think it's great but so far it's a
better search engine and it helps high
school kids cheat on their essays I mean
you don't believe that self driving is
coming hold on a second Sach you don't
believe that Millions but but hold on
those those driver jobs weren't even
there 10 years ago Uber came along and
created all these driver jobs door Dash
created all these driver jobs so what
technology does yes technology destroys
jobs but it replaces them with
opportunities that are even better and
then either you can go capture that
opportunity yourself or an entrepreneur
will come along and create something
that allows you to capture those
opportunities AI is a productivity tool
it increases the productivity of a
worker it allows and do more creative
work and less repetitive work as such it
makes them more valuable yes there is
some retraining involved but not a lot
these are natural language computers you
can talk to them in plain English and
they talk back to you in plain English
but I think David is absolutely right I
think we will see job creation by AI
that will be as fast or faster than job
destruction you saw this even with the
internet like YouTube came along look at
all these YouTube streamers and
influencers that didn't used to be a job
new jobs really opportunities cuz job is
a wrong word job implies someone else
has to give it to me and sort of like
their handed out it's a zero some game
forget all that it's opportunities after
covid look at how many people are making
money by working from home in mysterious
little ways on the internet that you
can't even quite grasp here's the way I
categorize it okay is that whenever you
have a new technology you get
productivity gains you get some job
disruption meaning that part of your job
may go away but then you get other parts
that are new and hopefully more elevated
you know more interesting and then there
is some job loss I just think that the
third category will follow the
historical Trend which is that the first
two categories are always bigger and you
end up with more net productivity and
more net wealth creation and we've seen
no evidence to date that that's not
going to be the case now it's true that
AI is about to get more powerful you're
going to see a whole new wave of what
are called agents this year a agentic
products are able to do more for you but
there's no evidence yet that those
things are going to be completely
unsupervised and replace people's jobs
so you know I think that we have to see
how this technology evolves and I think
one of the mistakes of let's call it the
European approach is assuming that you
can predict the future with perfect
accuracy with such good accuracy that
you can create regulations today that
are going to avoid all these risks in
the future and we just don't know enough
yet to be able to do that that's level
of certainty I agree with you and the
companies that are promulgating that
view is what nval said those that have
an economic vested interest in at least
convincing the next incremental investor
that this could be true because they
want to make the claim that all the
money should go to them so they could
Hoover up all the economic gains and
that's that is the part of the cycle
we're in so if you if you actually
stratify these reactions there's the
small startup companies in AI that
believe there's a productivity leap to
be had and that there's going to be
Prosperity everybody on the sidelines
watching and then a few companies that
have an extremely vested interest in
them being a gatekeeper because they
need to raise the next 30 or $40 billion
doar trying to convince people that
that's true and if you view it through
that lens you're right saxs we have not
accomplished anything yet that proves
that this is going to be cataclysmically
bad and if anything right now history
would tell you it's probably going to be
like the past which is generally
productive and a cre Society yeah and
just to bring it back back to JD's
speech which is where we started I think
it was a quintessentially American
speech in the sense that he said we
should be optimistic about the
opportunities here which I think is
basically right and we want to lead we
want to take advantage of this we don't
want to hobble it we don't even fully
know what it's going to be yet we are
going to Center workers we want to be
Pro worker and I think that if there are
downsides for workers then we can
mitigate those things in the future but
it's too early to say that we know what
the program should be it's more about a
statement of values at this point do you
think it's too early freeberg given
optimists and all these robots being
created what we're seeing in
self-driving you've talked about the
ramp up with
wh to actually say we will not see
millions of
jobs and millions of people get
displaced from those jobs what do you
think freeberg I'm curious your thoughts
because that is the
counterargument my experience erence in
the workplace is that AI
tools that are doing things that an
analyst or knowledge worker was doing
with many hours in the past is allowing
them to do something in minutes that
doesn't mean that they spend the rest of
the day doing nothing what's great for
our business and for other businesses
like ours that can leverage AI tools is
that those individuals can now do more
and so our throughput our productivity
as an organization has gone up and we
can now create more things faster so
whatever the product is that my company
makes we can now make more things more
quickly we can do more development
you're seeing it on the ground correct
at a hollow and I'm seeing it on the
ground and I don't think that this like
transplantation of how bad AI will be
for jobs is the right framing as much as
it is about an acceleration of
productivity and this is why I go back
to the point about GDP per capita and
GDP growth countries societies areas
that are interested or industries that
are interested in accelerating output in
accelerating productivity the ability to
make stuff and sell stuff are going to
rapidly Embrace these tools because it
allows them to do more with less and I
think that's what I really see on the
ground and then the second point I'll
make is the one that I mentioned earlier
and I'll wrap up with a third point
which is I think we're underestimating
the new industries that will emerge
drastically dramatically there is going
to be so much new sh that we are not
really thinking deeply about right now
that we could do a whole another 2hour
brainstorming session on on what AI
unlocks in terms of large scale projects
that are traditionally or typically are
today held back because of the
constraints on the technical feasibility
of these projects and that ranges from
accelerating to new semiconductor
technology to Quantum Computing to
Energy Systems to transportation to
habitation etc etc there's all sorts of
transformations in every industry that's
possible as these tools come online and
that will spurn insane new Industries
the most important point is the third
one which is we don't know the overlap
of job loss and job creation if there is
one and so the rate at which these new
technologies impact and great new
markets but I think nval is right I
think that what happens in capitalism
and in free societies is that capital
and people rush to fill the hole of new
opportunities that emerge because of AI
and that those grow more quickly than
the old bubbles deflate so if there's a
deflationary effect in terms of job need
in other Industries I think the loss
will happen slower then the rush to take
advantage of creating new things will
happen on the other side so my bet is
probably on the order of I think new
things will be created faster than old
things will be lost I think actually as
a quick side note to that the fastest
way to help somebody get a job right now
if you know somebody in the market who's
looking for a job the best thing you can
do is say hey go download the AI tools
and just start talking to them just
start using them in any way and then you
can walk into any employer in almost any
field and say hey I understand Ai and
they'll hire you on the exactly nval you
and I watched this happen we had a front
row seat to it back in the day when you
were doing Venture hacks and I was doing
open Angel Forum we had to like fight to
find five or 10 companies a month then
the cost of running these companies went
down they went down massively from five
million to start a company to two then
to 250k then to 100K I think what we're
seeing is like three things concurrently
you're going to see all these jobs go
away for automation self-driving cars
cashier Etc but we're going to also see
static team size at places like Google
they're just not hiring because they're
just having the existing bloated
employee base learn the tools but I
don't know if you're seeing this the
number of startups able to get a product
to Market with two or three people and
get to a million in revenue is booming
what are you seeing in the startup
landscape definitely what you're saying
in that there's leverage but at the same
time the I think the more interesting
part is that new startups are enabled
that could not exist otherwise uh my
last startup air chat could not have
existed without AI because we needed a
transcription and translation even the
current thing I'm working on it's not an
AI company but it cannot exist without
AI it is relying on AI even at angelist
we're significantly adopting AI like
everywhere you turn it's more
opportunity more opportunity more
opportunity and people like to go on uh
Twitter or the artist formerly known as
Twitter and and and basically they like
to exaggerate like oh my God we've hit
AGI oh my my God I just replaced my all
my mid-level Engineers oh my god I've
stopped hiring to me that's like moronic
the two valid ones are the onean
entrepreneur shows where there's like
one guy or one gal and they're like
scaling up like crazy things to AI or
there are people who are embracing Ai
and being like I need to hire and I need
to hire anyone who can even spell AI
like anyone who's even used AI just come
on in come on in again I would say the
easiest way to see that AI is not taking
jobs of creating opportunities is go
brush up on your learn a little bit
watch a few videos use the AI Tinker
with it and then go reapply for that job
that rejected you and watch how they
pull you in in 2023 an economist named
Richard Baldwin said AI won't take your
job it's someone using AI that will take
your job because they know how to use it
better than you and that's kind of
become a meme and you see it floating
around X but I think there's a lot of
Truth in that you know as long as you
remain adaptive and you keep learning
and you learn how to take advantage of
these tools you should do better and if
you wall yourself off from the
technology and don't take advantage of
it that's when you put yourself at risk
another way to think about it is these
are natural language computers so
everyone who's intimidated by computers
before should no longer be intimidated
you don't need to program anymore in
some esoteric language or learn some
obscure mathematics to be able to use
these you can just talk to them and they
talk back to you that's magic the new
programming language is English chath
you want to wrap us up here on this
opportunity slash displacement slash
chaos I was gonna say this before but I
I'm pretty unconvinced anymore that
you should bother even learning many of
the hard sciences and maths that we used
to as underpinnings like I used to
believe that the right thing to do was
for everybody to go into
engineering I'm not necessarily as
convinced as I used to be because I used
to say well that's great first
principles thinking etc etc and you're
going to get trained in a toolkit that
will scale and I'm not sure that that's
true I think like you can you can use
these agents and you can use deep
research and all of a sudden they
replace a lot of that skill so what's
left over it's creativity it's judgment
it's history it's psychology it's all of
these other sort of like softare
leadership communication that allow you
to manipulate these models in
constructive ways because when you think
of like the prompt engineering that gets
you to Great answers it's actually just
thinking in totally different orthogonal
ways and
nonlinearly so that's my last thought
which is it does open up the aperture
meaning for every smart mathematical
genius there's many many many other
people who have high EQ and all of a
sudden this tool actually takes the
skill away from the person with just a
high IQ and says if you have these other
skills now you can compete with me
equally and I think that that's
liberating for a lot of people I'm in
the camp of more opportunity you know I
I got to watch the movie industry a
whole bunch when the digital cameras
came out and more people started making
documentaries more people started making
independent film shorts and then of
course the Youtube Revolution people
started making videos on YouTube or
podcasts like this and if you look at
what happened with like the special
effects industry as well we need far
fewer people to make a Star Wars movie
to make a Star Wars series to make a
Marvel series as we've seen now we can
get the Mandalorian and shoka and all
these other series with smaller numbers
of people and they look better than
obviously the original Star Wars series
or even the prequels so there's there's
going to be so many more opportunities
we're now making more TV shows more
series everything we wanted to see of
every little character that's the same
thing that's happening in startups I
can't believe that there is a app now
nval called slopes just for uh skiing
and there are 20 really good apps for
just meditation and there are 10 really
good ones just for fasting like we're
going down this long taale of
opportunity and there'll be plenty of
million to10 million businesses for us
you know people learn to use these tools
I love how that's the thing that tips
you over which
one you get an extra Marvel movie or an
extra Star Wars show so that tips you
over I think for a lot of people it's it
feels great that AI may take over the
world but I'm gonna get next to Star
Wars movie so I'm I'm cool yeah I mean
it's are you not entertained want to
final point on this is look I mean given
the choice between the two categories of
techno Optimist and techn pessimist I'm
definitely in The Optimist camp and I I
think and I think we should be but I I
think there's actually a third category
that I would submit which is techno
realist which is technology is going to
happen trying to stop it is like
ordering the tides to stop if we don't
do it somebody else will China's going
to do it or somebody else will do it and
it's better for us to be in control of
the technology to be the leader rather
than passively waiting for it to happen
to us and I just think that's always
true it's better for businesses to be
proactive and take the lead disrupt
themselves instead of waiting for
someone else to do it and I think it's
better for countries and I think you did
see this theme a little bit I mean these
are my own views I don't want to ascribe
them to the vice president but you did
see I think a hint of the Techno realism
idea in his speech and in his tweet
which is look AI is going to happen we
might as well be the leader if we don't
we could lose in a key category that has
implications for National Security for
our economy for many things so that's
just not a world we want to live in so I
think a lot of this debate is sort of
academic because whether you're an
optimist or pessimist is sort of glass
half empty half full the question is
just is it going to happen or not and I
think the answer is yes so then we want
to control it this just you know let's
just boil it down there's not a
tremendous amount of choice in this I
think I would agree heavily with one
point and I would just tweak another the
point I would agree with is that it's
going to happen anyway and that's what
deep seek proved you can turn off the
flow of chips to them and you can turn
off the flow of talent what do they do
they just get more efficient and they
exported it back to us they sent us back
the best open source model when our guys
were staying closed source for safety
reasons and exactly and I deep explo
safety of their Equity deep seek
exploded the fallacy that the US has a
monopoly in this category and that
somehow therefore we can slow down the
train and that we have total control
over the train and I think what deep
seek showed is no if we slow down the
train they're just going to win yeah the
part the part where I TR to tweak a
little bit is the idea that we are going
to win by we when you say America the
problem is that the best way to win is
to be as open as distributed as
Innovative as possible if this all ends
up in the control of one company they're
actually going to be slower to innovate
than if there's a dynamic system and
that dynamic system by its nature will
be open it will leak to China it will
leak to India but these things have
powerful Network effects we know this
about technology almost all Technologies
has Network effects underneath and so
even if you are open you're still going
to win and you're still going to control
you look at the internet that was all
true for the internet right the
internet's an open Technologies based on
tons of Open Source Who are the Dom
companies all the dominant companies are
us companies because they were in the
lead exactly right exactly right we we
embrac the open internet we embrac the
open internet right that was different
yeah so there will be benefits for all
of humanity and I think the vice
president's speech was really clear that
look we want you guys to be on board we
want to be good
Partners however there are definitely
going to be winners economically
militarily and in order to be one of
those winners you have to be a leader
who's going to get to AGI first nval is
it going to be an open source who's
going to win is it going to be open
source or closed Source who's going to
win the day if we're sitting here 5 10
years from now and we're looking at the
top three language models lot of trouble
for this but I don't think we know how
to build AGI but that's that's a much
longer discuss who's going to have the
best model five years from hold on I I
100% agree with you I just think it's a
different thing but what we're building
are these incredible natural language
computers and actually David in a very
pithy way summarized the two big use
cases it's search and it's homework it's
paperwork uh it's it's really paperwork
and a lot of these jobs that we're
talking about disappearing are actually
paperwork jobs they're paperwork
shuffling these are madeup jobs like the
federal government as we're finding out
through Doge you know a third of it is
like people digging holes of spoons and
the another third are filling them back
up they're filling up paperwork and then
burying it in a m shaft they're buing M
shaft Mountain yeah so I I I think a lot
of these madeup jobs they got to go down
the M shaft to get the paperwork when
someone retires and bring it up you know
what I'm going to get them some thumb
drives we can increase the throughput of
the elevator with some thumb drives it
would be incredible what we found out is
the the DMV has been running the
government for the last 70 years it's
been a compounding compounding that's
that's really what's going on DMV is in
charge I mean if the world ends in
nuclear war God for bid the only thing
that's be left will be the Cockroaches
and then a bunch of like government work
documents s report TPS reports down in
the M shaft basically
yeah let's take a moment everybody to
thank our
Zar we miss him we wish he could be here
for the whole show and thank you Zar
thank you to the Zar see you guys miss
you we miss you little buddy I wish we
could talk about Ukraine but we're not
allowed get back to work we'll talk
about it another time over cfee I'll see
you in the comissary thanks for the
invite bye man I'm so excited I'm nval
saaks invited me to go to the the
military mess I'm going to be in the
commissary no he didn't J you invited
yourself be honest I did yes I did I put
it on his calendar to keep the
conversation moving let me segue a point
that came up that was really important
into tariffs and the point is even
though the internet was open the US won
a lot of the internet a lot of us
companies won the internet and they won
that because we got there the firstest
with the mostest as they say in the
military and that matters because a a
lot of Technology businesses have scale
economies and network effects underneath
even basic brand-based Network effects
if you go back to the late 90s early
2000s very few people would have
predicted that we would have ended up
with Amazon basically owning all of
e-commerce you would have thought it
would have been a perfect competition
and very spread out and that applies to
how we end up with Uber as basically one
taxi service or we end up with Airbnb
meta Airbnb it's just Network effects
Network effects Network effects rule the
world around me but but when it comes to
tariffs and when it comes to trade we
act like Network effects don't exist the
classic ricardian comparative advantage
Dogma says that you should produce what
you're best at I produce what I'm best
at and we trade and then even if you
want to charge me more for it if you
want to impose tariffs for me to ship to
you I should still keep tariffs down
because I'm better off you're just
selling me stuff cheaply great or if you
want to subsidize your guys great you're
selling me stuff cheaply the problem is
that is not how most modern businesses
work most modern businesses have Network
effects as a simple thought experiment
suppose that we have two countries right
I'm China you're the US I start out by
subsidizing all of my companies and
industries that have Network effects so
I'll subsidize Tik Tok I'll ban your
social media but I'll push mine I will
subsidize my semiconductors which tend
do tend to have win or take-all in
certain categories or I'll subsidize my
drones and then B exactly byd
self-driving whatever and then when I
win I own the whole market and I can
raise prices and if you try to start up
a competitor then it's too late I've got
Network effects or if I've got scale
economies I can lower my price to zero
crash you out of business no one in
their right mind will invest and I'll
raise prices right back up so you have
to understand that certain industries
have hesis or they have Network effects
or they have economies of scale and
these are all the interesting ones these
are all the high margin businesses so in
those if somebody is subsidizing or
they're raising tariffs against you to
protect your industries and let them
develop you do have to do something you
can't just completely back
down what are your thoughts jamath about
tariffs and network effects it does seem
like we do want to have uh redundancy in
supply chain so there are some
exceptions here any um thoughts on how
this might play out because yeah Trump
brings up tus every 48 hours and then it
doesn't seem like any of them land so I
don't know I'm I'm still on my 72-hour
Trump rule which is whatever he says
wait 72 hours and and then maybe see if
it actually comes to pass where do you
stand on all these tariffs and tariff
talk well I think the tariffs will be a
plug are they coming absolutely the
Quantum of them I don't know and I think
that the way that you can figure
out how extreme it will be it'll be
based on what the legislative plan is
for the budget so there's two paths
right now path one which I think is a
little bit more likely is that they're
going to pass a slim down plan in the
Senate just on border security and
Military spending and then they'll kick
the can down the
road for probably another three or four
months on the budget plan two is this
one big beautiful bill that's irking its
way through the
house and there they're proposing
trillions of dollars of cuts in that
mode you're going to need to raise
revenu somehow and especially if you're
giving away tax breaks and the only way
to do that is probably through tariffs
or one way to do it is through
tariffs my honest opinion Jason is that
I think we're in a very complicated
moment I think the Senate plan is
actually on the margins more likely and
better and the reason is because I think
that Trump is better off getting the
next 60 to 90 days of data I mean we're
in a real pickle here we have persistent
inflation we have a broken fed they are
totally asleep at the switch and the
thing that Yellen and Biden did which in
hindsight now was extremely dangerous is
they issued so much short-term paper
that in totality we have $1 trillion
dollar we need to finance in the next 6
to9 months so it could be the case
that we have rates that are like five
five and a quarter 5 a
half% I think that that's extremely bad
at the same time as inflation at the
same time as delinquencies are ticking
up so I think tariffs are probably going
to happen but I think that
Trump will have the most
flexibility if he has time to see what
the actual economic conditions will be
which will be more clear in 3 four five
months and so I almost think this big
beautiful bill is actually
counterproductive because I I'm not sure
we're gonna have all the data we need to
get it right fre B any thoughts on these
tariffs you've been involved in the
global uh Marketplace especially when it
comes to produce and wheat and all this
corn and everything what do you think
the dynamic here is going to be or is it
saber rattling and a tool for Trump the
biggest buyer of us a exports is China
China a exports are a major Revenue
Source major income source and a major
part of the economy for a large number
of states and so there will be as there
was in the first Trump presidency very
likely very large transfer payments made
Farmers because China is very likely
going to tariff Imports or stop making
import purchases altoe which is what
happened during the first presidency
when they did that the federal
government I believe had transfer
payments of north of $20 billion to
Farmers this is a not negligible sum and
it's a not- negligible economic effect
because there's then a Rippling effect
throughout the a economy so I think
that's one key thing that I've heard
folks talk about is the um the activity
that's going to be needed to support the
farm
economy as the US's biggest a customer
disappears in the early 20th century we
didn't have an income tax and the
federal revenue was almost entirely
dependent on tariffs when tariffs were
cut there was an
expectation that there would be a
decline in federal government revenue
but what actually happened is volume
went up so lower tariffs actually
increased trade increase the size of the
economies this is where a lot of
economists take their basis in hey guys
if we do these tariffs it's actually
going to shrink the economy it's going
to cause a reduction in trade the
counterbalancing effect is one that has
not been tested in economics right which
is what's going to happen if
simultaneously we reduce the income tax
and reduce the corporate income tax and
basically increased Capital flows
through reduced taxation while doing the
Tariff implementation at the same time
so it's a grand economic experiment and
I think we'll learn a lot about what's
going to happen here as this all moves
forward I do think ultimately these
countries are going to capitulate to
some degree and we're going to end up
with some negotiated settlement that's
going to hopefully not be too short-term
impactful on the economies and the
people and the jobs that are dependent
on trade economy feels like it's in a
very precarious place it does to asset
holders obviously and obviously they've
left it in a bad place in the last
Administration and we shut down the
entire country for a year over Co the
bill for that has come due and that's
reflected inflation I I think there are
a couple other points in tariffs first
is it's it's not just about money it's
also about making sure we have
functional middle class with good jobs
because if you have a non-tariff world
maybe all the gains go to the upper
class and an underclass and then you
can't have a functioning democracy when
the average person is on one of those
two
extremes so I think that's one issue
another is strategic Industries if you
look at it today probably the largest
defense contractor in the world is DJI
they got all the drones even in Ukraine
both sides are getting all their drone
parts from DJI now they're getting it
through different supply chain chain and
so on but Ukrainian drones and Russian
drones the vast majority of them are
coming through China through DJI and we
don't have that industry if we have a
kinetic conflict right now and we don't
have good drone supply chain internally
in the US we're probably going to lose
because those things are autonomous
bullets that's the feature of all
Warfare we're buying f-35s and the
Chinese are building swarms of Nar scale
at scale so we do have to re onore those
critical Supply chains and what is a
drone supply chain it's not just there's
not thing called drone it's like Motors
and
semiconductors and Optics and lasers and
just everything across the board so I
think there are other good Arguments for
at least reshoring some of these
industries we need them and the the
United States is very lucky and that
it's very aaric we have all the
resources we have all the supplies we
can we can be Upstream of everybody with
all the energy to the extent we're
importing any energy that is a choice we
made that is not because fundamentally
we the energy yeah because of between
all the oil resources and the natural
gas and fracking combined with all the
work we've done in nuclear fishing and
small reactors we should absolutely be
energy independ we should be running the
table on it we should we should have AB
a massive Surplus and hey you know if
you if you're worried about you know
couple of million of door Dash Uber
drivers losing their jobs to automation
like hey there's going to be factories
to build these parts for these drones
that we're going to need so there
there's a lot of opportunity I guess for
people and there is a difference between
different kinds of jobs those kinds of
jobs are better jobs building difficult
things at scale physically that we need
for both National Security and for
Innovation th those are better jobs than
you know paperwork writing essays for
other people to read yeah or even
driving cars all right listen I want to
get to two more stories here we have a
really interesting copyright story that
I wanted to touch on Thompson Reuters
just won the first major US AI copyright
case and fair use played a major role in
this decision this has huge implications
for AI companies here in the United
States obviously open Ai and the New
York Times Getty Images versus stability
we've talked about these but it's been a
little while because the legal system
takes a little bit of time and these are
very
complicated cases as we've talked about
Thompson Reuters owns Westlaw if you
don't know that it's kind of like Lexus
Nexus it's one of the the legal
databases out there that lawyers use to
to find cases Etc uh and they have a
paid product with summaries and Analysis
of legal decisions back in
2020 this is two years before chat GPT
reuter sued a legal research competitor
called Ross for copyright infringement
Ross had created an AI powered legal
search engine sounds great but Ross had
asked Westlaw if they would pay a
license to its content for training
wesla said no this all went back and
forth and then Ross signed a similar
deal with a company called Legal ease
the problem is legal E's database was
just cop copied and pasted from a bunch
of Westlaw answers so Reuters Westlaw
sued Ross in 2020 accusing the company
of being vicariously liable for legal
eases direct infringement super
important Point anyway the judge
originally favored Ross in fair use this
week the judge reversed this ruling and
found Ross liable noting that after
further review fair use does not apply
in this case this is the first major win
and uh we debated this so here's a clip
you know you heard it here first on the
all-in Pod what I would say is you know
when you look at that fair use Doctrine
I've got a lot of experience with it you
know the fourth Factor test I'm sure
you're well aware of this is the effect
of the use on the potential market and
the value of the work if you look at the
lawsuits that are starting to emerge it
is Getty's right to then make derivative
products based on their images I think
we would all agree stable diffusion when
they use these open web that is no
excuse to use an open web crawler to
avoid getting a license from the
original own owner of that just because
you can technically do it doesn't mean
you're allowed to do it in fact the open
Web projects that provide these say
explicitly we do not give you the right
to use this you have to then go read the
copyright laws on each of those websites
and on top of that if somebody were to
steal the copyrights of other people put
it on the open web which is happening
all day long you still if you're
building a derivative work like this you
still need to go get it so it's no
excuse that I took some site in Russia
that did a bunch of copyright violation
and then I indexed them for my training
model so I've think this is going to
result fre free can you shoot me in the
face and let me know when this
okay oh great I feel same way same way
now exactly I know me too yeah okay good
good segment let's move
on well since these guys don't give a
about copyright holders what do you
think about uh you know I'm so glad
you're here nval to actually talk about
the topics these two other guys I'm
going go thinner limb I'm going to go
and even thinner Limb and say I largely
agree with you I think it's a bit Rich
to crawl the open web Hoover up all the
data offer direct substitution for a lot
of use cases because you know now you
start and end with the AI model it's not
even like you link out like Google did
and then you just close off the models
for safety reasons I think if you
trained on the open web your model
should be open source yeah absolutely
that would be a fine thing I have a
prediction here I think this is all
going to wind up wind up like the Naps
or Spotify case for people who don't
know Spotify pays I think 65 cents on
the dollar to the original Underwriters
of of that content the music industry
and they figured out a way to make a
business and Napster is roadkill I think
that there is a nonzero chance like it
might be five or 10% that opening eye is
going to lose the New York Times lawsuit
and they're going to lose it hard and
there going to be injunctions and I
think it's the settlement might be that
these language models especially the
closed ones are going to have to pay
some
percentage in a negotiated settlement of
their revenue half 2/3 to the content
holders and this could make the content
industry have a massive massive uplift
and a and a and a massive Resurgence I
think that the problem there's an
example on the other side of this which
is that there's a company that provides
technical support for Oracle third party
company and Oracle has tried times to
soo them into Oblivion using copyright
infringement as part of the
justification and it's been a PA over
the stock for a long time the company's
name is riny Street don't ask me why I
it's on my radar but I just I've been
looking at it and they lost this huge
lawsuit Oracle one and then it went to
appella court and then it was all
vacated why am I bringing this up I
think that the legal Community has
absolutely no idea how these models work
because you can find one case that goes
one way and one case that goes the other
and what I would say should become
standard reading for anybody bringing in
of these lawsuits there's an Incredible
video that carpath just dropped that
Andre just dropped where he does like
this deep dive into llms and he explains
chat GPT from the ground up it's on
YouTube it's three hours it's excellent
and it's very difficult to watch that
and not get to the same conclusion that
you guys did I'll just leave it at that
H I tend to agree with this there's also
a good old video by ilas sover where he
he was a I believe the founding Chief
scientist or CTO of open Ai and he talks
about how these these large language
models are basically extreme
compressors and he models them entirely
as their ability to compress and they're
L com compression exactly lossy L
compression exactly exactly and Google
got sued for fair use back in the day
but the way they managed to get past the
argument was they were always linking
back to you they showed tiny sent you
the traffic they sent you the traffic
this is lossy compression it is
absolutely I'm now on your p i I hate to
say this
Jason I agree with you you were you were
right you were right that's all I wanted
to hear all these years that's all I
wanted shaking my head when I saw those
videos cuz I was like oh man Jason was
right Jason was right oh my God no I
just I've been through this so many
times that these I think this is you
know rer Murdoch said we should hold the
line with Google and not allow them to
index our content without a license and
Google navigated it successfully and and
they were able to to not get him to stop
I think what's happened now is that the
New York Times remembers that they they
all remember losing their content and
these Snippets and the one box to Google
and they couldn't get that Genie back in
the bottle I think the New York Times
realizes this is their payday I think
the New York Times will make more money
from licenses from llms then they will
make from advertising or subscriptions
eventually this will renew the model
almost I think the New York Times
content is worthless to an llm but
that's a different story I think the
actual Val cont political reason
whatever but I can tell you as a user I
loved the wire cutter I think you knew
Brian and everybody over the wire cutter
we that was like fair enough yeah wire
cutter what a great product I used to
pay for the New York Times I no longer
pay for the New York Times my main
reason was I would go to the wire cut
yeah and I would just buy whatever they
told me to buy now I go to chat gbt
which I pay
forb tells me what to buy based on the
wire cutter so it's it and I'm already
paying for it so I stop paying for it I
philosophically disagree with all of
your nonsense on this topic all three of
you are wrong and I'll tell you why
number one if information is out in the
open internet I I believe it's
accessible and it's viewable and I view
an llm or a WebCrawler as basically
being a human that's reading and can
store information in its brain can if
it's out there in the open if it's
behind a pay wall 100% if it's behind
some protected password wait wait wait
wait David David in that in that case
can a Google crawler just crawl entire
site and serve it on Google why can't
they do that there so here here's the
fair use the fair use is you cannot copy
you cannot repeat the content you cannot
take the content and repeat it that is
how the law is currently written but now
what I have is I have a tool that that
can remix it with 50 other pieces of
similar content and I can change the
words slightly and maybe even translate
into a different language so where does
it stop do you know the musical artist
girl talk we should have done a girl
talk track here today he's got musical
taste this guy oh good here we go he
basically take takes small samples of
popular tracks and he made and he got
sued for the same problem there was
another guy named white panda I believe
had the same problem Ed Sharon got sued
for this yeah but but their entire sites
like stack Overflow and Wiki that have
basically disappeared now because you
can just swallow them all up and you can
just spit it all back out in chat GPT
with slight changes so I I think that
the the the fair how much of a slight
change is exactly the right question how
much are you changing yeah so that's the
question are and it actually boils down
to the AGI question are these things
actually intelligent and are they
learning or are they compressing and
regurgitating that's the question I
wonder this about humans and that's why
I bring up the white panda the girl talk
in audio but also visual art there was
always artists and all even in classical
music I don't know if you guys are
classical music people but right there
was there's a demonstration of how you
know one composer learned from the next
and that you can actually track the
music as kind of being standing on the
shoulders of the prior and the same is
true in almost all art forms in almost
all human knowledge and Media
communication it's very hard to figure
that out well that's exactly right
that's the hard it's very hard to figure
that out which is why I come back to
there's only one of two stable solutions
to this and it's going to happen anyway
if we don't crawl it the Chinese will
crawl it right deep seek prove that so
there's only one of two stable Solutions
either you pay the copyright holders
which I actually think doesn't work and
the reason is because someone in China
will crawl it and they just dump the
weights right so they can just crawl and
com and dump the compressed weights or
if you crawl make it open at least
contribute something back to open source
right you crawled open data contributed
back to open source and the people who
don't want to be crawled they're going
to have to go to a huge length to
protect their data now everybody knows
to protect the data yeah well
thing is happening here I have a book
out from Harper business on the shelf
behind me and uh I'm getting 2500
smackaroos for the next three years for
uh Microsoft indexing it so they're
going out and they're licensing this
stuff and um they're going $2500 so your
book literally I'm getting $2,500 for
three years a bunch of Harper to go into
an llm to go into Microsoft specifically
and you know what I'm going to sign it I
decided because I just want to set the
precedent maybe next time it's 10,000
maybe next time it's 250 I don't care I
just want to see people have their
content respected and I'm just hoping
that Sam wman loses this lawsuit and
they get an injunction against it hey uh
well just because he's just such a
weasel in terms of like making open AI
into a Clos thing I mean I like Sam
personally but I think what he did was
like the super weasel move of all time
for his own personal benefit If he if he
and this whole lying like oh I have no
equity I get healthare he does it no bro
he does it he does it for the love what
what was the statement he does it for
the I do it for the Jo benefit out of
the benefits I think he got Healthcare I
think in opena defense they do need to
raise a lot of money and they got to
incent their employees but that doesn't
mean they need to take over the whole
thing that the nonprofit portion can
still stay the nonprofit portion and get
the Lions share the benefits and be the
board and then he can have an incentive
package and employees can have an
incentive package why don't they get a
percentage of the revenue just AB I
don't understand has to be bought out
right now for 40 billion and then the
whole thing disappears into a closed
system that part makes no sense to me
that's called a shell game and a scam
yeah I think Sam and his team would do
better to leave the nonprofit part alone
leave an actual independent nonprofit
board in charge and then have a strong
incentive plan and a strong fundraising
plan for the investors and the employees
so I think this is workable it's just
trying to grab it all just seems way off
especially when it was built on open
algorithms for Google open data from the
web and nonprofit funding from Elon and
others I mean what a great proposal like
we just workshopped here what if they
just what do they make six billion a
year just take 10% of it 600 million
every year and that goes into uh a bonus
they're losing money Jason so they have
to okay eventually they no but even
Equity they could they could give Equity
to the people building it but they could
still leave it in the control of the
nonprofit I just don't understand this
conversion I mean there was a there was
a board coup right the board tried to
fire
took now it's
hispi selfing right and yeah they'll get
an independent valuation but we all know
that game you hire valuation expert
who's going to say what you're going to
say and they'll check box if you're
going to capture the life cone of all
future value or build super intelligence
that's worth a lot more that's why Elon
just spit 100 billion exactly you're
saying you're saying the things that
actually The Regulators and and the
legal Community have no Insight because
they'll see a fairness opinion and they
think oh it says fairness and opinion
two words side by side it must be
and they don't know how all of this
stuff is gamed so yeah yeah I man I got
stories about 409a that would
exactly 49a are gamed these fairness
opinions are gamed but the the reality
is I don't think the legal and the
judicial Community has any idea I mean
imagine if a Founder you invested in
just is just a total imaginary situation
nval had like a great term sheet at some
incredible dollar amount didn't take it
ran the valuation down to like under a
million gave themselves a bunch of
shares and then took it three months
later I don't know what would that be
called Securities for wrap yeah let's
wrap on your story I had an interesting
Nick we'll show you the photo I had an
interesting dinner on Monday with Brian
Johnson the don't die guy came over to
my house how's his erection doing
overnight what we talked about is he's
got three hours a night of nighttime
erections wow look at this by the way
first of all I'll tell you I think that
I I think that he's um wait which
one of those is giving him the erection
no no no he measures his nighttime
erection I think has given him the
erection or he but he said he said that
when he started so by the way he said
he's he was 43 when he started this
thing he was basically clinically obese
yeah and in these next four years has
become a specimen he now has 3 hours a
night of nighttime erections but that's
not the interesting thing at the end of
this dinner by the way his skin is in I
I was not sure because when you see the
pictures online but his skin in real
life is like a porcelain dolls I've both
my wife and I were like we've never seen
skin like this and it's incredibly soft
wait wait wait whoa whoa whoa how do you
know skin is soft you know you brush
your hand against his forearm or
whatever you know gives a hug at the end
of the night I'm telling you the guy
skin is had Supple skin bro it's the
softest skin I've ever touched in my
life anyways that's not the
point it was really fascinating din he
walked through his whole protocol but at
the end of it I think it was Nash the
CEO ofo alter networks he was just like
give me the top three things top three
and of the top three things what I'll
boil it down to is the top one thing
which is like 80% of the
80% it's all about sleep I was about to
guess sleep and he walked through his
nighttime routine and it's incredible
and it's straightforward it's really
simple it's like how you do a wind down
anyways I have tried to explain the wind
down briefly let's just say that because
Brian goes to bed much earlier so our
normal time let's just say you know 10
10:30 so my time I try to go to bed by
10:30 he's like you need to be in bed
you need to first of all stop eating
three or four hours before right and I
do that I eat at 6:30 so I have about 3
hours you're in bed by 9:30 or
10 you deal with the selft talk right
like okay here's the active mind telling
you all the things you have to fix in
the morning talk it out put it in its
place say I'm gonna deal with this in
the morning write it down in a journal
you're saying whatever you do so that
you put it away you cannot be on your
phone that's got to be in a different
room it's or you just got to be able to
shut it down and then read a book so
that you're actually just engaged in
something and and and he said that he
typically falls asleep within three to
four minutes of getting into bed and
starting this what I tried it so I've
been doing it since I had dinner with
him on Monday last night I fell asleep
within 50 minutes H the hardest part for
me is to put the phone away I can't do
it of course of course what about youal
tell us your one down oh yeah I know so
I know I know Brian pretty well actually
and I joke that I'm married to the
female Brian Johnson because my wife has
some of his routines but she's like the
natural version no supplements and she's
intense and I think when Brian saw my
sleep score from my eight sleep he was
shot he was he he was just like you're
going to die he's like you're literally
going to die well you got 70 80 no it's
ter it's terrible it's awful but it's
tell what's your number what's your
number it like in 30s 40s but you know
yeah but it's also because I don't sleep
much I only sleep a few hours a night
and I also move around a lot in the bed
and so on but it's fine I I never have
trouble falling asleep but I I would say
that Brian's yes skincare routine is
amazing his diet is incredible he is a
genuine character I do think a lot of
what he's saying minus the supplements
I'm not a big believer in supplements
yeah does work
I don't know if it's necess going to
slow down your aging but you'll look
good you'll feel good yeah sleep is the
number one thing in terms of falling
asleep I don't think it's really about
whether you look at your phone or not
believe it or not I think it's about
what you're doing on your phone if
you're doing anything that is
cognitively stressful or getting your
mind to spin then yes you think you can
scroll Tik Tok and fall asleep is fine
anything that's entertaining or that is
uh like you could read a book right on
your Kindle or on your iPad and I think
it'd be fine falling asleep or you can
listen to like some meditation video or
some spiritual teacher or something and
that'll actually help you fall asleep
but if you're on X or if you're checking
your email then heck yeah that's going
to keep you up so my hack for sleep is a
little different I normally fall sleep
within minutes and the way I do it is I
you all have a
meditation you have a set time no no I
sleep whenever I feel like usually
around 1 in the morning two in the
morning God damn I'm in bed by 10 yeah I
need to sleep I'm an owl but if you want
to fall asleep the hack I found is
everybody has tried some kind of a
meditation routine just sit in bed and
meditate and your mind will hate
meditation so much that if you force it
to choose between the fork of meditation
and sleeping you will fall asleep every
time well okay so after if you don't
fall asleep you'll end up meditating
which is great too so just I like the
meditation do the body scan the coda to
this story was a friend a friend of mine
came to see me from from the UAE and he
was here on Tuesday and I was telling
him about the dinner with Brian and he
told me the story cuz he's friends with
kabib the UFC fighter and he says you
know when kib goes to his house he eats
anything and everything fried food pizz
whatever but he trains
consistently and my friend adala says
how are you able to do that and how does
it not affect your physiology goes I've
learned since I was a kid I sleep 3
hours after I train in the morning and I
sleep 10 hours at night and I've done it
since I was like 12 or 13 years old
that's a lot of sleep it's a lot of
sleep I you know the direct correlation
for me is if I uh do something
cognitively like you know big heavy duty
conversations or whatever so no heavy
conversations at the end of the night no
existential conversations the night and
then if I go rucking I have the you know
on the ranch I put on a 35b weight vest
I walk you do that at night before you
go to bed no no no if I do it anytime
during the day I typically do it in the
morning or the afternoon but the 1 to2
mile Ruck with the 35 lbs whatever it is
it Just Tires my whole body out so that
when I do lay down is that why you don't
prepare for the
podt you know I mean this pot is the top
10 pot in the world Chim do you think
it's an accident freeberg what's your
what's your sleep routine can you just
go to bed you just like warm bath and I
send J Calli a picture of my feet I'll
wait till jal's done I do take a nice
warm bath
it but you do you do it every night a
warm bath I do yeah I do a warm bath
every night with candles too and do you
do it right before you go to bed yeah I
usually do it after I put the kids down
and I'll basically start to wind down
for bed I do watch TV sometimes but I do
have the problem and the mistake of
looking at my phone probably for too
long before I turn the lights off so do
you have a consistent time where you go
to bed or
no usually 11:00 to midnight and then up
at 6:30
man I I need I need eight hours
otherwise I'm a mess I go to I'm trying
to get eight I hit between 600 and seven
consistently I try to go to bed that 11:
to 1:00 a.m. window and get up the 7 to
8 window my problem is if I have work to
do I'll get on the computer or my laptop
and then when I start that after in my
evening routine I can't stop and then
all of a sudden it's like 3 in the
morning and I'm like oh no what did I
just do and then I still have to get up
at 6:30 so that does happen to me so
last night was unusual for me but it was
kind of funny anyway I thought oh I
should go to bed early cuz I'm an Allin
yeah but I ended up eating ice cream
with the kids
late wait what was the brand you said
you went for another brand I want to
know the brand I think it's van Luen or
something like
that New York
and the holiday cookies and cream oh my
God so good yeah it's so good so after I
polish that off then I was like oh I
probably ate too much to go to bed so I
better work out so I did a kettle bell
workout you sound like Mo what did you
say I have eight kettle bells right here
right next
to free this is called working out
fre and then while I'm doing my
kettlebell suitcase carry I was texting
with an entrepreneur friend so you can
tell how intense my workout was and he's
in Singapore so it was in the middle of
the night for me and early for him and
was time to go to bed I was like I was
like okay now I got to get to bed how do
I get to bed I'm my body is all amped up
I've got food in my stomach
Bells my brain is all my brain is all
amped up and all in podcast is tomorrow
and what time is it's 1:30 in the
morning I better get to bed so I I put
on like a little one of those spiritual
videos to calm me down and then I just
and then I got in bed and I was like
there's no way I'm falling asleep and I
started meditating and 5 minutes later I
was asleep you know actually the dolly
Lama has these great on his YouTube
channel he's got these great like 2hour
discussions you get about 20 30 minutes
into that you will fall asleep well yeah
my but my learning is yeah watch any
Dharma lecture from the SS exactly and
my my lesson is my learning is that the
mind will do anything to avoid
meditation yeah yes by the way did you
guys see just before we W did you see
all the confirmations RFK Jr confirmed
Brook rolands confirmed by the way if
you look at Poly Market poly Market had
it all right a couple weeks ago like I
was TR Market there was a moment where
fell to like 56% there was a moment when
RFK fell to 75% but then they bounced
back and it was done could you got snip
that man you could have made money yeah
and the media the media was like no way
he's getting confirmed this is not going
to happen but poly Market knows it's so
interesting huh well I saw a very
insightful tweet and I forget who wrote
it so I'm sorry I can't give credit but
the guy basically said look Trump has a
narrow majority in the house and the
Senate yeah and he can get everything he
wants as long as a Republicans stay in
line so all the pressure and all the
anger that all the mega movement is
doing against the left is pointless it's
all about keeping the rightwing in line
so it's all the people saying to the
Senators hey I'm going to primary you
Nicole Shanahan saying I'm going to
primary you it's Scott Pressler saying
I'm moving to your District that's the
stuff that's moving the needle and
causing the confirmations to go through
that's how you get cash Patel that's how
you get toy gabber the dni that's how
you get RF you worry about any of these
you think any of them are are too spicy
for your taste or you just like the
whole burn it down put in the crazy like
Outsiders that's such a bad
characterization that's not a fair
characterization mean the out honestly
it's like I never thought I'd see it but
I think between Elon and sax and people
like that we actually have Builders and
doers and financially intelligent people
and economically intelligent people in
charge and you know despite all the
craziness elon's not doing this for the
money he's doing it because he thinks
it's the right thing to
do he moved into the Roosevelt
I I think like many of us I had I had
bought into the great forces of History
mindset where it's just like okay it's
inevitable this is what's happening
government always gets bigger always
gets slower and we just have to try and
get stuff built before they just shut
everything down and we turn into Europe
but the thing that happened then was you
know Caesar crossed crossed the Rubicon
the great man theory of History played
out and we're living in that time and
it's it's an inspiration to all of us
despite Sam Alman and elon's current
fighting I know Sam was inspired by Elon
at one point and I think all of us are
inspired by Elon I mean the guy can be
the Diablo player and do Doge and run
SpaceX and Tesla and boring and neural
link I mean it's incredibly impressive
it makes us that's why I'm doing a
hardware company now it makes me want to
do something useful with my life you
know Elon always makes me question am I
doing something useful enough with my
life it's why I don't want to be an
investor you know Peter te ironically
he's an investor but he's inspirational
that way too because he like yeah the
future just doesn't just happen you have
to go make it so you know we get to go
make the future and I'm just glad that
Elon and Doge and others are making the
future thatare what the what do we got
going on here maybe I'll all in podcast
in a couple of months but it's really
it's really difficult I'm not sure I can
pull it off so let me try let me just
make sure it's viable is it drone
related is it self-driving drone drones
are cool but no it's not maybe podcast
should be an angel investor oh yes
absolutely no no Syndicate Jason just
our Mone what are you talking about you
know how I learned about syndicates was
Nal the first syic I ever did on
angelist I think is still the biggest I
don't know 5% and Nal is my partner on
this for.com I think you'll love what
I'm working on if I pull it off I think
you guys will love it i' love to show
your demo let us know where to send the
check get that black cherry chip van
Leen I love you guys what have we
learned I gotta go okay big shout out to
Bobby and to Tulsa that's a huge huge
huge room for America I'm stoked about
both of them congratulations I love me
thanks for coming
let's get bobbyy Bobby come back on the
Pod four thear David Sachs your sulan of
science David freeberg the chairman
dictator chamath P hatita
POA and Namaste N I am the world's
greatest moderator we'll see you next
time on the all in pond say
byebye let your winners ride
Rainman
David and instead we open source it to
the fans and they've just gone crazy
with it love you queen
[Music]
of Besties
are that's my dog taking your
[Music]
driveways oh man myit will meet me at we
should all just get a room and just have
one big huge orgy cuz they're all this
usess it's like this like sexual tension
that they just need to release
[Music]
somehow we need to get mer
our I'm going all in