this was one of the biggest days of my
podcasting career that's the magic of
naal ravikant Nal rant Nal ravikant
founder of Angel Del no rikan Naro rakan
the founder of angelist which is a giant
business I mean Global I I wonder if
you've ever thought of that reality if
your parents didn't leave India and go
to the US how would your life be
different according to you the first
time I used an Apple computer it was an
old Macintosh I just fell in love with
it at some point if you have high agency
you will end up where you're meant to go
it's just going to take some effort did
it do anything for your mind I kind of
sometimes have these near-death
exercises where it's just like I imagine
myself dying it's like you can see
things fading out they call orgasm the
petite more The Little Death right did
you ever smoke weed you know I live in
California well the common belief now is
that like mushrooms are harmless right
they're
not do you miss your childhood I don't
have a it's like a dream is it real
actually
happened B has had a great saying in
every human there is a sense that
something infinite has been lost wow has
marriage brought further understanding
when it comes to life there's a secret
to a happy relationship is to happy
people you know what I've learned about
marriage one's wife is always right and
that's the rule one should follow yes I
reject that completely uh yeah people
say like happy wife happy life that's
all propaganda that's all feminine
propaganda you're being brainwashed no
both people have to be equally happy
really you know from the outside looking
in I personally have this impression of
Naval rikan the brand and the human and
I feel like nothing hurts that guy I'm a
very paranoid person so my rule is I
don't fight with people if somebody
wants to fight with me we get one fight
and then it's over there's a lot of
people out there and life is long do you
pray if you are older in life and you
don't have the Next Generation to look
forward to then you better find God fast
because I don't think like your own mind
and your own life will be kind to you as
you get older
if you know who Naval ravikant is please
head straight into the conversation this
intro is primarily crafted for those of
you who are being introduced to Naval
ravikant for the first time surprisingly
there's a lot of people in India who are
yet to be introduced to who I consider
to be the greatest philosopher of our
times I genuinely believe that history
will remember him as one of the greatest
Minds that lived in the 21st century
he's an extremely humble extremely
relaxed individual so I know that this
intro is going to bother him on some
level that's the side of Naval that I
got to know through this conversation
this is the most casual conversation
that the internet has ever seen with
this man it was one of the biggest
honors of my own podcasting career to be
sharing screen space and podcasting
space with Naval ravikant if I had to
introduce him professionally of course
I'd tell you how he's one of the most
iconic Angel Investors in the world of
course i' tell you about how he's one of
the most important thought leaders for
Silicon Valley and the world of Global
Twitter or X it's Naval ravikant on the
RV show this is one of the most
memorable episodes for me on a personal
level but if you're looking for depth in
conversation it doesn't get deeper than
Naval rikan's mind it's Naval on
TRS huge day for my career honestly huge
day for my own Human Experience
enjoy the
[Music]
episode this is one of the biggest days
of my podcasting career but I'm also
feeling supremely comfortable that's the
magic of Nel ravian oh you're very nice
welcome to the ren show sir thank you
thanks for having me uh visualize this
moment so much over the years so as I
told you in the car ride on the way here
uh I'm full of gratitude and as we go
forward in this conversation I'm going
to pour more and more gratitude on you
uh when we were on our way here from the
network state conference I saw how much
you were hounded uh people just want to
come up and say that they love you uh
this takes me back to that Joe Rogan
episode you did in 2019 are you aware of
how many young men's lives that episode
affected I have no idea why to be honest
I feel like I just said the same things
I was saying they're kind of obvious and
maybe uh don't be so easily influenced
really yeah think for yourself you know
decide for yourself you know how I look
at it so in 2019 I was 26 running four
businesses parall getting extremely
stressed out but those two hours of that
episode created switches in me and my
journey from age 26 to age 31 has been
much more lubricated especially from a
mental health perspective so you've done
a lot for the mental health of many men
all over the world how how much do we
really figure out ourselves right
there's like there there's what are the
different kinds of knowledge this weth
thinking through right I'm just thinking
it through with you so there's Knowledge
from direct experience right you
experience something and that generates
knowledge inside of you there's
knowledge that you pick up from other
sources you just a vessel that's passing
through you you picked it up you
synthesize it you
regurgitate there's uh knowledge that
you create which is rare um um I don't
know if I said anything original really
yeah I don't know I don't know but I
think you accumulated a lot of data
which is back by years of reading and
research I think if I were to look back
I would say that the only true knowledge
I have is the knowledge that is uh
directly verified by me and uh fits in
with the other pieces so I view myself
as a very basic thinker really yeah I
don't view myself as an advanced thinker
I'm not an expert in anything but what I
like to do is everything that comes my
way I like to deeply understand it as
simply as possible I have to be able to
put it in simple words and simple
Frameworks and simple Concepts and I
have to be able to do it uh almost
visually in my mind and exponentially
have to map it to some experience that I
have and then I have to be able to take
that and I have to be able to plug it
into something else I understand it has
to fit in a steel frame of understanding
at the basics of knowledge uh so for
example mathematics I was never very
good at mathematics I wanted to be a
physicist but I I wasn't good at
calculus but my basic math is really
really good um the same way I don't have
the largest vocabulary but I have a very
solid vocabulary and I can be very
precise with my words even when I speak
I'm not the fastest speaker I'm not the
slowest speaker so I think for me it's
just about I don't take there's a great
uh motto from the Royal Society which
was the Society of scientists in uh
Britain during their Enlightenment era
and uh the motto of the royal so Society
is nullus and verba I'm sorry if I'm
mangling the Latin but it means take no
one's word for it and I love that uh
take no one's word for it so I think uh
we are encouraged these days to take in
knowledge pour it into our heads like a
bucket and uh we regurgitate it and we
use fancy words to cover up what we
don't mean what we don't know and I
don't accept that unless I understand
something at its core fundamental level
I don't understand it and then beyond
that level I get bored I don't care to
understand it so I think just being able
to be very particular about what you
take in make sure you truly understand
it and that it is true truth is the most
important thing because if you're going
ahead with falsehoods because they're
convenient you're just going to walk
around bumping your head against reality
and wondering why it hurts so it's
important to just always look for the
truth figure it out for yourself make
sure it fits into your understanding be
open to revising it because you're
always wrong it's just question of how
wrong you are uh and then using that to
uh find the commonalities in life and
and navigate it and I think that's why
uh you're better off asking someone like
me about very basic things uh than about
very Advanced things can I ask you a
basic question sure yeah please what's
the meaning of
life we talk about this for hours I
think about it all the time I think
about it I I want to kind of reframe it
a little bit sure yeah uh what's new
right now in life for you it's been 5
years since that Joe Rogan episode and
we got to know you so deeply then yeah
but what's happened in the last five
years I don't I don't I don't uh
retrospect on myself I don't think about
myself that's what's new no no I just
don't I I couldn't tell you because I
don't think about myself I don't think
about what's changed in my life and if
my life is good or bad or if this
happened or that happened and I don't
look at all photos of me and I don't
think about old trips and I think about
people that are gone you know I don't I
don't think about the past I just don't
live in the past at all do you pray uh
not in the traditional sense no uh I
think prayer implies some kind of an
external entity that I'm asking
something for and sure like every person
I might have done that here or there um
usually we're fair weather friends with
any God that's out there right when we
need help we're like all prayer and when
we don't we're like everything's good
it's all me right so no I don't I don't
pray in the traditional sense
uh but I am very deeply I hate the word
but it's spiritual right and I would
Define spiritual in a negative way it
just means not mental not physical right
so but why do you hate the
words because it's overloaded with a lot
of religiosity um all of a sudden you're
supposed to be a spiritual being you're
supposed to do yoga you're supposed to
meditate and you're supposed to sit
cross- lugged and you're supposed to you
know then you argue about is the bagat
Gita or the asash Gita or the you know
all of these roads lead to the same
place um the the the best way I would SU
Ariz my thinking on this is that I think
existence itself is a miracle the oldest
questions are why is there something
instead of nothing why are we here
what's the meaning of life these are all
just variants in the same question and
there is no answer to that does that
mean there can never be an answer to
that no not necessarily but if you start
going down that road you'll find all
kinds of contradictions for example with
just the meaning of life right if there
was a single meaning of life then we
would all be slaves to it suppose the
meaning of life was to help others and
we would all be running around trying to
help others and you know there'd be no
room for the individual if the meaning
of life was to you know be strong and
fit and healthy then we'd all be working
out um we'd all be I don't know how beer
and biceps go together but you know we'd
all be building our biceps so it's
better that there is no overarching
singular meaning of life it's better
that there are personal interpretations
got um however within those personal
interpretations you know we we all have
even though we have complete freedom to
choose any meaning that we want and we
can create our own meaning at any moment
um
there are certain common things in what
we all want as well and so that's kind
of the Paradox of being a human
individual where you're completely an
individual but you're also completely
Interlink to everything and anything
that exists you couldn't change you
couldn't change a particle in the
universe without changing this moment
right not in any meaningful way um
although that's not entirely true there
are error correcting mechanisms built
into into the structure of the universe
so uh but a lot of things had to cons in
a very particular way to bring us here
together today right um so in that sense
everything is very interconnected on the
other
hand my life is and your lives are
single player games inside our heads you
know we interpret everything from birth
to death uh your experience of uh your
experiences are singular to you uh no
one will truly ever understand you or
get you uh and you're always searching
for that Unity that connection that that
going back to uh you know Oneness Source
togetherness whatever you want to call
it Community there's many words for
it in terms of uh you know back to
meaning of life the way I think of it is
that existence itself is a miracle and
everything else is science and I think
that's the best of all possible worlds
so spirituality is a side that lies on
what who am I why am I here how long
have I got what am I here for and these
are questions that are really only
answerable at a personal level this
miraculous little world that we're in is
beautifully put together I couldn't I
couldn't do a better job for sure for
sure I couldn't even begin to do the job
and just to give you some ideas as to
you know just some observations how well
it's put together the fact that science
works that's magic technology works that
is Magic you go back and you read books
on magic or magicians or fantasy books
they don't have a hundred of the power
that we have they don't have
self-driving cars they don't have
smartphones they don't have antibiotics
they don't have Rockets um they don't
even have fantasy novels they don't even
have clean running water they don't have
reliable food they don't have food
delivery services right uh so we are
already living in an age of Miracles
that the best part is we can control and
the magic spells that we cast are under
the opice of science the Wizardry that
we create is through technology and
that's all manipulable through laws and
and rules and systems that we discover
and we discover and we create and that
is incredible we're all magicians I
wouldn't I couldn't ask for a better
system if an actual Miracle showed up
afterwards supposed somebody showed up
and turned uh loaves into fish or water
into wine that would destroy our world
because all of a sudden you be like oh
my God there's all these rules for this
new thing that we don't understand how
it works so now science is junk and you
wouldn't know how to navigate the world
and now You' be the mercy of demons and
angels and spirits and you'd be running
around worshiping and praying then you
would pray because you'd be like how do
I make sense of this world so I think we
live in the best of all possible worlds
okay uh I think the geography that one
grows up in definitely determines their
mindset in life to a large degree
and uh personally my take on
spirituality is affected by growing up
in India you read books like the
autobiography of your Yogi you read the
life of the Buddha uh I definitely feel
that there's a higher stage of
Consciousness and I don't feel like
we've reach the final state of evolution
uh there is definitely an end point
which is also beyond the next stage of
evolution uh and I do believe that you
know you say that Cal a calm mind is
earned MH I think that's one of the
steps on the ladder and then there's
like higher stage
mhm I I don't know how useful it is to
prognosticate about where humanity is
headed unless you get there yourself
first uh and and you don't have the
ability to do anything for anyone unless
you embody it yourself uh so so to the
extent that you think humanity is headed
there I say get there first and then
show them the way I definitely think
that Nal rant is already on that ladder
as compared to other human beings I have
no idea where I'm on that ladder you
don't think you're slightly more
evolved no I I
don't that's a loaded question
uh first of all I don't think of myself
I I just want to be clear on that and
that's not a rule it's just a habit I've
kind of developed because I found that
thinking about yourself is a source of
all unhappiness and misery really yes
self-obsession is the root of all
unhappiness what did Buddha do conquer
the self what does that mean means that
he saw through the illusion of the
separate self what does that did Buddha
think about himself not for an instant
you know anyone that you think of as an
enlightened being does not think about
themselves for an instant the happiest
people in life when people are their
best is because uh they love something
more than they love themselves they love
their children they love God they love
their mission what have you and all
misery comes from rumination from
sitting around being depressed going in
circles in your own head about me me me
me is a disease and uh you need the a
concept of a me to be effective and to
keep track of things you have a memory
you have certain predictions your
personality patterns but the more you
self- obsessed the less happy you're
going to be I guarantee you that and I'm
not doing I'm not saying I don't think
about myself to be happy I can't even
tell you why I don't think about myself
I think it just comes from having
thought through a lot of things and then
just I I get interested in topics and
Concepts and ideas and understandings
and the more that I sort of focus that
way the less I just end up thinking
about myself so even like you know
people ask me like oh how's your day
going I'm like I have no idea I don't
think about it really yeah good maybe if
I'm really tired I'll say okay I'm tired
you know if something really bad
happened like oh it wasn't a great day
but most of the time I couldn't even
tell you my own State of Mind okay cuz
I'm not interested in it I don't think
it's interesting it's interesting for us
and I'll give you some perspective here
yeah we were one of the first podcasts
in India uh currently the biggest and I
feel that's an outcome of constantly
tearing apart people's chest getting
into their hearts and getting to know
them because in India we're emotional
people and we want to know the emotions
of others we want to know what's in
other people's mind or it's dumb luck
cuz you started early I'm just kidding
or or that of course not I'm just joking
with you luck is definitely a part of me
I mean look luck favors are prepared uh
Joe Rogan uh is incredibly successful
because he was doing podcasting before
his podcasting he was the top guy on
Ustream which was just like a streaming
thing on the internet before podcasting
came along so uh there's a certain kind
of person that it takes to be
early you make your own luck in that
sense I actually
luck is luck is one of those things that
you shouldn't believe in even if it's
true because believing it will hurt your
agency just like victim mentality right
thinking you're a victim even if it's
true don't believe it because it'll just
hurt your agency because you have no
power as a victim you have no power if
things are up to luck uh whatever power
you have in life comes from believing
that you can change things and do things
and even if you can't change the outside
you can at least change the inside No
One controls your mind but you um so
yeah it's it's not luck I was jok
talking the question I have for you is
while all of us sit in India and view
Naval ravikant ruling the internet in so
many ways uh a lot of Indians feel very
proud okay to see someone from India uh
you know who shares genetics with us uh
kind of kill it on a world stage uh so
I've had this thought experiment lately
as I've been researching for this
episode I thought to myself that what if
Noel's parents didn't leave India and
what if he was in Delhi I'm pretty sure
you'd still uh take up some form of
Entrepreneurship knowing your
personality because I think there's some
traits that don't change uh but then
there's a lot that changes because of
geography I I wonder if you've ever
thought of that reality if your parents
didn't leave India uh and go to the US
how would your life be different
according to you I don't I don't want to
downplay geography at all I actually
think where you live is the single most
important decision you make uh but the
first part of that is making a decision
uh I like to think that even if my
parents had not immigrated to the US I
would have probably done so at a later
age because I was ambitious uh and I
wanted to be around smart people and I
wanted to build things uh when I
immigrated to the US I was not in any
position to go to Silicon Valley and
build things I had to kind of you know
claw my way there um and I got there a
little later than I should have frankly
but at any given time in the world's
history there's usually only one or two
places that really matter in terms of
moving the world forward so there was a
time when it was Athens in ancient
Greece there's a time when it was
Florence in Italy there's a time when it
was uh London in the United Kingdom and
the the time when I was kind of coming
into my formative years it was Silicon
Valley and I knew that I the first time
I used an Apple computer it was an old
Macintosh in uh the computer room in my
high school I just fell in love with it
and I and I just knew that I had to get
closer to uh Apple that that was the
thing that pulled me in when I got to
Silicon Valley the first thing I did was
with my bags I went in a taxi straight
from the airport to app's headquarters
and I wandered around um and I'd read
this book by Guy Kawasaki called the
Macintosh way that was very
inspirational to me so at some point if
you are if you have high agency if
you're a person that's selfmotivated
which I think almost everybody watching
this is um you will end up where you're
meant to go it's just going to take some
effort the universe drops plenty of
opportunity around you but it's not
necessarily on your head and you have to
walk over there and pick it up your
podcast didn't build itself for example
counterfactuals are impossible to do
like uh yes if you had gone if you had
immigrated to the US early you'd
probably be doing a podcast in the US um
or uh you know if you weren't born a
podcaster you found your way to being a
podcaster so even though yes there's
luck involved there's counterfactuals
involved there's immigration involved
don't believe that stuff you know it's
better to uh just kind of take
responsibility both externally and
internally externally for what you manag
to do and internally for how you feel
about it uh like one of my little tweets
to myself and all the good ones are to
myself was I and I alone am responsible
for everything I think and feel um so
for example if I get mad at somebody
about something it's my fault why am I
mad why am I making myself angry um why
can't I just deal with the same
situation in a cool calm and collected
way why do I have to show to or not even
show why do I have to lose control
because anger is a loss of self-control
why why am I still so broken inside that
that happens so I I kind of reject this
line of questioning to be honest you
know what if what if what if who cares
what if we're here um you know you
constantly talk about that steel
framework thing you say that learn the
first principles yes um while we were at
the event a lot of the people backstage
were like ask navel about how he
achieved this level of clarity and I
understand that you focus on first
principles thinking but what's
underneath that thought like did you
read a book at some point in life that
pointed you towards it no no no no no I
I think uh when I was young my dad
wasn't around much and uh he was gone he
had to he immigrated to the US before
the rest of us did it took four years
where he could pull us there and then my
parents went through divorce and so on
so one good thing was I never had
anybody telling me what to do ever um
and I had to figure everything out for
myself and I think that helps a lot it
makes you very high agency um I also
nobody in my like my aunts and my mom
they loved us to death but there was
nobody saying this is right that's wrong
do it this way don't do it that way so
you figure it out for yourself and
started with reading but eventually just
goes to thinking but I don't think
there's anything special I I think I
think deep down everybody wants to
understand things right everybody wants
to learn everyone's curious all children
are curious any young child they'll be
asking questions all day long and I
think the trick is just don't stop
asking questions and keep asking
questions until you can answer something
your own
satisfaction um maybe I had the luxury
of the time to read you know that's
helpful because it helps answer
questions when you're younger at least
some some reading a lot of too much
reading or reading the wrong things can
be bad too right because you can stuff
your head with the wrong things I I I
guess for for decades I did not feel
like I was that smart because what would
happen is I would talk to somebody and
they'd say well there's this and that
and there's this and they would just
start using big terms and big words and
defining huge things and and it took me
a long time to figure out they didn't
know what they were talking about if
someone's using a lot of big words you
know it's the mark of a charlatan to
explain simple things in a complex way
and uh it's a mark of a Genius Like
Richard Fineman to to explain
complicated things in simple ways the
smartest people actually understand what
they're talking about so they can
explain it in plain English they don't
need to resort to abstractions they
don't need to impress and a lot of times
with abstractions are leaky you poke at
them and it doesn't quite map or it
doesn't mean what what they think it
means um I'd rather like stick and I'm a
failed physicist I wanted to be a
physicist so and my ma math wasn't good
enough plus I wanted to make money so it
didn't work out but uh I was surrounded
by a lot of physicists and I read a lot
of physics and so I felt dumb compared
to the other physicists and so I I well
I you're not going to trick a physicist
you're not going to walk in and start
talking physics and then suddenly like
you you say something that's wrong
they're going to call you on it physics
is very rigorous and same thing with
computer science which I did end up
studying is the code has to compile the
code has to run the code has to work you
can't you can't trick the machine using
words and so I think having a grounding
in scientific disciplines around
scientific people forces you to be
rigorous and humble about your actual
sphere of knowledge uh you can't Bluff
people um systems in which you get
feedback like real feedback uh free
markets and nature right you can't trick
nature I can't lie to Nature uh and I
can't trick free markets all end up
broke so these systems give you very
good feedback and they force you into
being rigorous um but it's very easy to
trick people so if you're in politics if
you're in law if you're in journalism if
you're in media uh if you're just you
know bsing with your friends it's very
easy to trick people and then you get
social rewards you don't get the
negative feedback and that gets baked
into your personality your identity your
way of thinking uh so I think I was
fortunate enough to be
scientifically uh to get scientific
feedback and to be pushed back upon
through science and scientific people um
also grew up in a tough environment so
it was a no BS environment you had to be
correct so you know when you're trying
to survive you have to be correct uh
when you have an abundance of resources
and things are easy you don't have to be
right because you there's cushions
everywhere in the environment for you um
so maybe I was forged that way but like
I said I don't I don't introspect much I
don't it doesn't really matter to me
it's ancient history all that matters is
here because this is all there is so
let's talk about the Hein now yeah uh
you're 50 now yeah has your definition
of Love changed at all love is just it's
one of these overloaded words it's like
Freedom you know it means anything you
want but what does love mean okay I I
think so what is love
okay this romantic love which we're all
familiar with Bollywood thrives on that
right that's that's an attachment thing
it's like I love you if you love me
let's go have kids together yes this a
biological programming it's there it's
important it's good to have that's not
the real love or you love like a fanboy
like how all of us love you yeah love
love is a feeling of unity it's the it's
the attraction to yourself actually it
is seeing yourself in something else and
then kind of wanting to complete with it
um so you can have a spiritual love
which is a love for Oneness or God you
can have a love for your children
because they're just part of you you can
have a love for your community because
it's it's like you you can have love for
your ideas so love is attraction in that
sense it's like a it's a positive
attraction where you you see the unity
in the thing with you and you don't
necess want anything out of it and you
know that's a that's a genuine love um
the nice thing about love is if you
think back in your life to when you were
loved a lot right like you were loved by
your parents great wonderful to be loved
by your parents some point you took it
for granted let's be honest we all take
our parents for granted that's one of
the things you learn as a parent
yourself you're like oh my God my
parents put up with all of this they
were Saints right um You you really only
start valuing your parents when you have
your own children then you realize what
a one-way relation relationship that
love relationship and it's fine that's
the way it's meant to be even your
parents they want what's best for you
they want you to love your kids not to
love them back at the same level so uh
one of the things you learn about love
is okay when you're receiving love you
take it for granted and it can even be a
little too much like for example
someone's attracted to you and you're
not attracted to them you're like right
the overzealous fan you know the girl
the guy who's like chasing you around
you're like I don't really know I don't
I'm not really into this so that kind of
love is the love that we think we want
but we don't really I mean yes we want a
little bit of it so we don't feel
completely alone and and it makes us
feel safe but it's not really the love
that you want now think back to when you
were in love when you're in love with an
idea how you just work on it
passionately when you're in love with
let's say God or spirituality how you're
just taken and you're you're you're
swept away or when you're even in love
with a person you're in love with a
woman or your love with a man and all of
a sudden everything is brighter and
everyone's happier and you're just like
walking on Cloud9 the feeling of being
in love is greater than the feeling of
being loved is my point okay and you can
be in love anytime you want and how do
you be in love well you can't be forced
right you can't buy love you can't force
love but I will say a commonality is
generally the less you are thinking
about yourself going back to what I was
saying earlier the more you're going to
be able to love other people and other
things so for example the Buddhas uh you
know I you know people will sometimes
say well that's not a Buddha cuz that
person is not loving enough well that's
that's not necessarily true love is not
a requirement for being a Buddha but it
is an output of being a Buddha because a
Buddha is a person who has seen through
the illusion of the separate self uh and
once they've seen through the illusion
of the separate self they're no longer
self- obsessed and therefore their love
that was earlier turned inwards and
became ego love for the self went
outwards and it still flows uh as a very
simple example you know here's something
I uh uh is a little embarrassing but
I'll be vulnerable you like vulnerable
vulnerability right so I I I I kind of
sometimes have these near-death
exercises right where it's just like I
imagine myself dying and it's not
something that I do deliberately just
kind of happens the the moments when you
go into bed but before you fall asleep
are really interesting because your mind
goes into a really hazy almost
psychedelic State and and I used to
meditate a lot and somewhere along the
way I just found that state between
sleeping and waking to be really
entertaining and entertaining
entertaining yeah it's just entertaining
so next time you're falling asleep just
make a just just the smallest effort
because if you make any real effort
you'll fall you won't be able to sleep
but make the smallest effort just to be
aware of your thoughts as you're falling
asleep as you're going to sleep and your
thoughts start going wackier and wackier
and wackier and they will just get wild
like I'll have cats talking to me and
you know just like weird stuff going in
and out just it's like dreams you're
you're basically lucid dreaming as
you're falling asleep and they're the
craziest dream they don't make any sense
it's all nonsense You observe your own
thoughts as you're about to fall asleep
as I'm about to fall asleep that's when
that's when your thoughts start going
off the rails you stop thinking about
like what am I doing tomorrow and how to
work go today and you just start having
these wacky random Connections in your
head and it can be really fun to watch I
was doing it just as an entertainment
thing the an exploratory thing what have
you found out I'm not looking to find
anything so I think that's part of
curiosity you have to be a little
careful because if you go looking for
something in particular then you're only
open to seeing that thing and that's not
how you find anything that's true um but
it it's just pure mere curiosity it's
it's an entertaining State that's that's
a fine reason to do it right we do
everything because we enjoy it at the
end of the day if you didn't you
wouldn't do it right or you want to not
NE enjoy it but you do it because you
want to um so I did it just because I
wanted to and once in a while once in a
while and I'm not trying to suggest
anything because again if I suggest
something then it's not going to happen
for you but you know I'll basically feel
like I'm dying so I'm falling asleep but
I feel like I'm dying it's like you can
see things fading out right and as you
fall asleep the the French uh no that's
not they call orgasm the petite more The
Little Death right but uh but it's also
because your mind shuts down right so
what's happening is your your mind is
shutting down from waking to sleeping
State and that's kind of a death
transition you can kind of feel like
you're dying and you can literally see
thoughts going offline your mind goes
offline and as your mind goes offline
pay atten attention to what
remains pay attention to what actually
remains and don't be afraid of it don't
be AF you're just falling asleep but
like I said sometimes it feels like
you're dying and don't be afraid of
death right you just kind of go with it
it's what's just what's happening and
then as your mind disappears as things
disappear as things Fade Out of
existence see what remains okay there's
a version of something like this that I
do for me the last two thoughts are
always
the girl I'm seeing and or uh the God I
know MH which is just Universal energy
yeah these are all manifestations of
what you would call love right this is
this is you stop thinking about yourself
because thoughts are what Drive the
self- obsession the self is ultimately
just a thought it's a it's a the self is
a thought that I am a separate creature
I'm a body I'm a mind and if you truly
were not thinking like you're in deep
meditation or you're on a psychedelic or
you're a Buddha you wouldn't have a
thought of the self and you would just
be you just be be aware that's all
that's all there is I think the
difference in your state of
consciousness and mine is one you're
much older and you've seen life and by
older I mean brain older not physical
body older you're a wiser human being
and I think over the years you've just
learned to observe and pick up data from
everywhere U my early life experiences
kind of catered me towards a deep sense
of what we call bti in India which is uh
nisat prame or unselfish love towards
the Divine it's just an outcome of
living in India in my eyes yeah no I I
what matters is truth not who says what
or what where you lived or what book you
read what just matters is what's true
and that you can figure out for yourself
and you can figure it out just as well
as me and you probably have your your
core experience of of your awareness
same as mine every emotion you felt I
felt every emotion I felt you felt we're
human no Human Experience is alien to us
so we can have all the same feelings and
thoughts just in different levels and
different bases um i s i s I sort of
reject this idea that I'm Wiser or more
advanced I don't think that's true no if
I was wise I'd be a Buddha I'm not so
it's like you know two ants debating
like you know who's smarter and there's
like a there's like a human walking
around over there right what ises it
matter okay not in our eyes because for
a lot of dudes in their 20s and 30s you
are what we want to become especially
from a peace perspective I'm the same
guy I've always been and I wouldn't even
say I'm that peaceful my mind is a wreck
really yeah I'm always like my mind's
always running all over the place it's
it's it's always active you know how you
said that happiness is peace and motion
mhm uh that's something that stayed with
me over the years and it's something I
practiced the the person who's going to
know the most about weight loss is the
person who was fat as a kid the person
who's going to know the most about peace
and happiness is the one who was the
most miserable inside so don't take from
anything I write to say that I'm some
peaceful Zen Buddha inside I'm not my
mind still runs out of control it's I'm
a crazy person I'm a I'm a crazy person
who's trying to be a little less crazy
and observing my own craziness that
that's how I can come back to you and
say like you know when I started
tweeting a lot uh about anything other
than technology so I I you know I was an
investor in Twitter early on small
investor in 2007 and Twitter really
launched and started getting big around
2010 not even big it was still small but
I was active on Twitter from the start
but around 2012 2013 I was going through
a tough period and that's when I started
tweeting uh the stuff that I was
supposed to tweet and I you know I
started getting feedback from people in
the environment who were like hey that's
weird you know you're like a VC you're
like an entrepreneur people not going to
trust you they think you're strange are
you high you know that was like a
constant uh thing and I was just like I
I don't care I'm just writing to myself
right and and I was writing down my
crazier and crazier thoughts uh and I
for a long time I got no positive
feedback on it which is fine it's
actually fine because if you if you're
doing it for positive feedback you're
eventually going to end up doing the
right the wrong thing right I like
burning my audience I like occasionally
I'll tweet things that I don't
completely believe that are a little
incendiary because I want to find all
the people who get easily triggered so I
can block them uh I just want to blow
them out I don't care about followers
followers are worthless right if easy
mechanism to adjust your friend list
yeah if you're if you're if you're doing
anything for followers your followers
are worthless uh you know who would you
have rather follow you 10 people that
you respect that are intelligent and
interesting and wise or like a million
monkeys so the the follower count thing
is utterly worthless and I don't even
want followers I only want peer
relationships um because follower is
kind of a weird thing now this this
person's not thinking for themselves and
uh no what what every intelligent person
craves is other intelligent people right
to help things things through uh and to
kind of bond with but um I don't know
where I was going with this but yeah
screw followers anyway yeah I was I was
tweeting and I was tweeting like the
craziness in my mind right I was I'm a
crazy person
and so I was just going through my own
head and trying to sort out my own
thoughts and it's a complete mess and uh
it turns out that we all have the same
internal thoughts and we all have the
same internal experiences we all do we
have them in different order maybe we
interpret different things from them but
we all have the same feelings so every
time I put out some late night tweet
with some crazy thought you know people
around the world would just be like yeah
I'm thinking that too um I forget who
said this there was a great line that I
read a long time ago but it was
something like oh I think it was Emerson
uh and he said uh you know in every
genius we see our own ordinary thoughts
but they come back to us with a certain
alienated
Majesty right so it's it's just the
willingness to say it combined with
saying it in an interesting way so what
I realized was that what I liked about
Twitter it was like an open Journal
which forced me to craft my thoughts it
would give me feedback obviously because
people will come out and correct you
even if you're correct
and what I enjoyed writing was I liked
saying things that I thought were true
that were novel to me in that moment
obviously anything I can think of
somebody else has probably thought of
with very few exceptions
so it was something novel to me
something that was true and I would say
it in an interesting way so that I would
remember it uh and because I read a lot
as a kid I tried writing I wasn't I
didn't have the patience to be a long
form writer I wrote a few blog posts and
never even wrote a book and uh I tried
poetry um because I like reading poetry
but I didn't care to learn meter and
Rhythm and rhyme I just cared about the
words and the and how evocative they
were and so Twitter was a perfect medium
for me it allowed me to be to use word
selection and simple Framing and
explanation to really hone down things
that I thought to be true and were
interesting to me and write them as
notes to myself and to this day like
every day I go on Twitter and someone's
quote tweeted me on something or there's
like some Nal bot that's like thrown up
a noal quote and I look at them I'm like
oh I should follow that advice damn that
was good like that was written to me
that's a note to sell from me from five
years ago I should take my own advice
it's kind of like you're growing up in
front of the world yeah it's and we're
all always growing up right we're all
we're all always on this journey of
self-discovery this single player game
or we're alone inside but yet we're
deeply interconnected because we're all
having the same thoughts the same
emotions the same experiences with maybe
different interpretations often the same
interpretations the great questions in
life the meaning of life or you know
what am I doing here or what should I do
uh they all have paradoxical answers uh
so for example you know does life have
any meaning uh I could say no life is
meaningless you you arrive with nothing
you die nothing survives you you don't
remember anything as far as you're
concerned the moment you close your eyes
at last time the entire universe
disappears it's like a dream that never
happened poof no meaning
okay on the other hand I could say
actually life has infinite meaning uh
every moment is connected to every other
moment you can this it's the only thing
that actually exists uh you can ascribe
complete and utter meaning to it right
uh another question you ask is am I
alone and yeah of course you're
completely alone no one else knows your
thoughts you're single point of
awareness nobody else can have that same
point of awareness and any two points
are infinitely different in space on the
other hand it could say no of course
you're not alone the entire universe had
to conspire to to bring you here at this
moment it's all particle collisions from
The Big Bang till now and then poof here
you are and uh how can you and
everything that you do is a function of
your environment and your genes neither
of which you selected so you're not
alone you're just you're you're part of
everything you're you're indispensable
part of everything um so all of these
great questions are paradoxical answers
uh and that's one of the ways that you
know you're dealing with one of the
great questions uh and it turns out you
know if you think it through the reason
when when you see these par OES often
what you'll find is that the question is
being asked you know what is the meaning
of life but then it's being answered at
two different levels and one level is a
level of the individual separate self
which says oh the meaning is just what I
ascribe to it um and then sometimes you
answer it there's a slate of hand and
you answer it the level of the universal
self where you say well of course you
know the meaning is the universe or the
meaning is life itself um or like am I
alone if you answer that at the
individual level then the answer is yes
if you answer at the universal level the
answer is no so the paradoxical answers
come from do you choose to take do you
choose to adopt the Viewpoint of
yourself as a separate person or do you
take the Viewpoint of your spiritual
self uh and we jump between those those
contradictions very Loosely without
paying attention and we end up with
these paradoxical answers and we think
the the question is not solvable but
that's not entirely true it is solvable
it's just which level are you speaking
from so for example going back to the
Buddha a Buddha not the Buddha but a
Buddha any Buddha any enlightened person
they don't have any sense of persistent
separate self and so they're always
answering at the universal level and in
that sense they're freed of
contradictions and I think the reason we
admire those people is because we
ourselves want to be freed of this
internal contradiction uh Bor has had a
great saying that uh in every human
there is a sense that something infinite
has been lost wow and uh I love that
phrase uh because to me that's kind of
if if I think about kind of what's going
on here right I can't prove it so at the
end of the day you should figure it out
for yourself but I think what's going on
here is that there is a universal self
which is just raw awareness and that's
all there is everything in your
experience is awareness in my eyes based
on what I've read and learned through
the show uh I feel like Hinduism
explores exactly this question what is
the infinite s yeah H Hinduism gets
closer than anybody else but any ISM
isn't going to quite get you there cuz
it's an individual thing you know the
word Hinduism is not like by modern day
Hindus we we refer to it as sanatan D
which is like the Eternal fith yeah and
what I like about Hinduism is that it
lets kind of everybody find their own
way and you can pick your God you can
pick your path it's a buffet yeah it's a
buffet and but it has to be because
there are as many paths as there are
people uh and because you create an
individual story right there's kind of
an awareness or a Consciousness
everything that you experience
experience is in this awareness it
arises in the awareness it's probably
made of awareness it's known by
awareness so what else is there
everything is intermediated through your
awareness and then on top of that you
layer your identity and your body and
your problems and your issues and your
achievements and your desires and then
eventually you unlayer all of that and
you lose that and you go back to this
undifferentiated awareness which has
kind of always been around it's
hypothesis I don't know if it's true a
lot of people say it you know um and I
do read a lot of old Indian texts oh
really yeah well like I I'm a fan of uh
obviously everyone says bhagad Gita but
I like the ashtavakra Gita if You' read
that one uh that's yeah didn't expect
you to say that no Ash vakar is amazing
uh vista's yoga which has a lot of the
Enlightenment stories uh Herman Hesh
wrote that book sidartha which is kind
of a fictionalized Buddha story um but
you know then I've read you know Raja
yoga and autobiography of Yogi and all
that stuff Oso Krishna MTI blah blah
blah Dello uh Michael if if it's I got
into would call Enlightenment porn and I
tracked down about a dozen of these
people in real life and I interviewed
them and I met them I spent time with
them and I meditated and I did all that
stuff but the conclusion I kind of came
to is that you got to figure it out
yourself all that stuff is inspirational
but and uh you can only kind of do it if
you want to like right now I'm on
YouTube and I'm watching uh old Krishna
myy talks I'm watch watching papa Muji
Rupert spir uh ascendor random Youtube
videos the guy has like 10 followers but
he's enlightened the YouTube algorithm
is really good it finds Enlighten good
people if you just click around far
enough um but obviously at some level
I'm not fully serious about it because
if I was serious about it I would be
there but there is a greater truth out
there again this is a bit of a
compliment to you in my eyes um you're
the definition of what a sanatani is in
terms of exploration and collecting
knowledge and then coming to a
conclusion about life and the Divine
yourself based on your own experiences
and knowledge then using the shastras
the ancient books as reference points so
that's just how I I think we all want to
know the truth and there's little truths
and there's big truths and there's
bigger truths and this is probably the
biggest truth right and I did cheat I
skipped to the end I looked at the
answer uh might have been a mistake to
be honest because the the point is not
to earn a PhD in Enlightenment actually
be enlightened right and so I don't know
exactly how you get there there doesn't
seem to be a copyable path but I'm still
fascinated with it my mind is still
circling the drain on it does the
Mahabharat have any influence on your
mind I don't remember remember too well
I I think uh now this is where I'm going
to just offend a lot of people but I
think that's mostly historical uh thing
obviously everything you know old Indian
mythology has a lot of uh spirituality
weaved into it but no it's not one that
I've spent much time on okay it's more
the philosophies like the ashaka Gita
and all that yeah I love the ashaka Gita
it's incredible the song of
self-realization yeah when you're
reading that stuff yeah is there a part
of your DNA that feels stimulated being
Indian you everyone keeps trying to nail
me on this uh on being Indian
it's it's it's it's a very brown person
thing to do well I think I think we want
a certain pride in being Indian right
because it was stripped off because it
was stripped off I think that's exactly
right and I sort of reject that it was
stripped off really in the sense that
I'm just like hey I'm equally valid
right I don't consider myself inferior
to anyone I don't consider Superior to
anyone so in that sense like don't let
them strip you in the first place that
you have to then go needing it fulfill
it and and re really only the individual
can can truly transcend only the
individual can rise above whatever is
facing them um so putting your faith in
a group identity you're sort of Bound
for disappointment I mean how many
Indians are there it's over a billion
right so there's going to be as many
points of differentiation as their
commonality it's not like all billion
Indians link arm and March do the same
thing we're not we're not ants um so at
least I approach it more from an
individual level I'm happy to be Indian
I have no objections with it I think
it's a rich culture uh and I think it's
you know helped me a lot and half the
books I read these days were written by
Indians you know back in the day almost
all the philosophy I read is Eastern
philosophy um and the little bit of
Western philosophy that I like uh
schopenhauer and Emerson were incredibly
and D they were incredibly influenced by
Eastern philosophy they basically just
cribed Eastern philosophy and they put
it in western words right um because
Eastern philosophy has the virtue of
being correct it's true right right uh
one side says well you know God has this
shape this skin color this size lived at
exactly this time and has exactly these
rules like skeptical you know the other
side says well you are the self that
you're looking for it's all inside of
you you have to figure it out for
yourself and you know here are some
practical steps that you can take
towards self-realization that seems more
you know that seems more correct um I
think it's an outcome of just kind of
being older like you had more time to
contemplate I think anyone who is highly
truth seeking will eventually find their
way to Eastern
philosophy uh because it has the virtue
of being true just like Western science
has the advantage of being true okay so
Western physics so when people talk
about like oh we're going to have
indigenous math no 2 plus two has to
equal four right okay we could be wrong
but I doubt it that's our best theory
right now that 2 plus 2 equals 4 so I
Look to Western for science technology
advancement by the way the East is now
starting to make strides there as well
um but when it comes to the oldest
questions the best answers are the
oldest ones like the these some of a lot
of what we've been discussing has been
around us questions since the dawn of
mankind so and Indian civilization is
one of the oldest civilizations it's
probably the oldest large civilization
that explored these topics where we have
written materials and records and
practitioners and so on um and there's
probably more Buddhas and alive on the
Indian subcontinent than there are
anywhere else in the world so if you're
attracted to the truth of the old
questions and you want to find the old
answers you're going to head there this
is natural I think there are some
problems with traveling in India uh
namely hygiene and it's a little chaotic
but if one is ever seeking for the right
answers in life especially when it comes
to these questions India opens up
certain portals in your head it can be
influential that said if if you can't
figure something like that out exactly
where you are exactly when you are there
then it's not true the truth is not
something that's going to live in a
certain region at a certain place at a
certain time and has to be told to you
by a certain person a certain way that's
not a truth that's just another
experience uh so anything that because
the whole point of spirituality is to be
freed of the monkey mind and to be at
peace in the moment and so it can't be
reliant on anything outside it can't be
it can't it can't be in the future it
can't be in a different place uh you
know one of my problems that I have with
all religions is this idea that like oh
this is the word of God and it was p
down through this book well okay well
what if I didn't speak that language
what if I was born at the wrong time no
any fundamental truth that spiritual has
to be accessible to every human at every
time in every place regardless of
language culture religion age you know
gender whatever or even physical being
like you could be you could have mental
retardation you could be crippled you
could be dying you should still be able
to see and find and experience that same
truth on your own otherwise if it's if
it's brought to you from the outside if
it's temporal it can be taken away from
you and so I think the best path towards
truth is understanding because when you
deeply understand something um you're
not going to unand it it's the nature of
truth that once you see it once you
learn it you don't unlearn it because
it's true that's truth is indestructible
knowledge in your mind uh it can only be
replaced by a better truth it can only
be replaced by oh okay that was that
truth wasn't complete here's another
piece of the truth that I was missing um
but in that sense truth cannot be
destroyed it can only be overruled by
other truths so if you find uh some
understanding then that can be with you
forever has marriage brought further
understanding when it comes to
life I I don't marriage is fine
household is great I don't like to
discuss personal life okay I just don't
think it as relevant to other people's
lives I I will say like uh you know I
was talking about this earlier today but
my own favorite tweet uh to myself is
the you know a Fit Body a calm mind and
a house full of love these things cannot
be bought they must be earned uh and
house full of love is is that part and
you can create a house full of love
anytime you want by giving love uh that
said you know marriage is complicated
it's a negotiation uh between people you
have to learn how to live together you
have kids it's not easy uh but I'm not
the person to give marital advice if
only you will agree
with it's it's too personal and every
marriage is so unique and even the
concept of marriage is sort of going
away in a lot of Western societies uh uh
I do encourage children I think children
are amazing
everyone should have kids yeah
absolutely I don't understand this
anti-natalist thing we here you're here
I'm here because an unbroken chain of
our ancestors from tadpoles to monkeys
to now uh you know had children are you
going to be the first ones to miss that
Branch I mean if you believe in some
afterlife all your ancestors looking
down you're saying oh my God I can't
believe it we struggle so hard you know
we fought Tigers we we we cross
mountains we we froze during the ice
ages and this idiot just decided not to
have children cuz he couldn't be
bothered
for bad guy to stop this CH yeah he's
screwed up right but I will tell you
like if if you are older in life and you
don't have the Next Generation to look
forward to then you better find God fast
because I don't think like your own mind
and your own life will be kind to you as
you get
older you know what I've learned about
marriage M from the outside I'm not
married yet but this is conjectural okay
uh I think one's wife is always right
and and that's the rule one should
follow yeah see I reject that completely
uh yeah people say like happy wife happy
life that's all propaganda that's all
feminine propaganda you're being
brainwashed no both people have to be
equally happy uh the secret to a happy
relationship is two happy people and uh
you can't be happier than your spouse so
it's not happy wife happy life it's
unhappy wife unhappy life you know so so
you both have to be happy both of you
have to work hard to make each other
happy um you have to be a good fit and a
good match but the point of getting
married is to have children so so you
know have the kids and then you know
worst case you have kids which is still
an amazing outcome and best case you're
happily married and you have kids but I
would I don't buy the you know keep the
wife happy propaganda that's that's
that's that's letting her Sher her
duties it's been kind it's kind of you
now that that approach would work if I
asked your fiance or girlfriend and she
said Oh My Philosophy is like uh you
know keep the husband happy at all cost
if she said that then I would be like
okay that's a good match they're both
trying to keep each other happy but if
it's all one-sided no that doesn't work
yeah I mean personally I'm very sanatani
yeah and sanatan D says the key to a
happy relationship is um tolerance and
selfless service so those are the two
kind of flag Poes I've got uh after
finding the right that's good if
everybody follows it uh you know if both
people are selfless and tolerant with
each other then it'll work out well but
you're not going to be in any voluntary
relationship where you're selfless and
tolerant the other person's intolerant
and selfish it won't last so you can
only
make those kind so those are good
guidelines for society they're not
necessarily good guidelines for the
individual uh as an individual mate
selection is a real thing you have to
pick a person who you're incredibly
compatible with uh you know the
traditional model is that the you know
the man earns and creates and the woman
uh kind of takes care of the household
the man takes care of things outside she
takes care of things inside that's a
traditional model I know in the west
it's falling out of favor but it works
and in that model the man has to be
capable and do his duty and the woman
has to be kind and love loving and you
know take care of the household and so
that is a valid model of how the world
works and you can kind of I don't know
sonan or whatever you can have some
prescriptions about how to run that but
the reality is life is very complicated
every every individual is completely
unique the combinatorics of human DNA
are staggering you'll never meet two
people who are even vaguely alike if you
leave a friend you break up with a
girlfriend you lose a person in your
life a loved one you're never going to
find a substitute you're never going to
find anybody who's like the same or even
close even close right I've never met
two human beings who are even vaguely
similar um except perhaps identical
twins but that's theoretical I don't
know any up close that well so if every
person is unique just imagine how unique
every relationship is so having other
people navigate your relationship with
hard and fast rules doesn't work you can
look to it for inspiration you can look
to it for principles but each
relationship has to work on its own
merits and I am I am a lazy person and I
hate conflict so my rule is if a
relationship has conflict I just leave
it I don't fight with people if somebody
wants to fight with me we get one fight
and then it's over because there's a lot
of people out there there's a lot of
people out there and life is long so you
have to navigate your way towards the
people who love you for who you are and
you love them the way they are nobody
needs anybody to change and if they
change it's okay because you still kind
of value the core and you change
together um the same way like you find
you have to navigate your way to the
career the job the profession the
obsession where you like the thing for
what it is the the moment is complete in
of itself as you perform that act and if
you get some reward out of it that's
fantastic but that's not the core reason
you do it um and the same way U I think
you can apply that to every facet of
your life even if you're eating you want
to find the healthy food that you
actually enjoy eating there's many
healthy foods out there just find the
ones that you enjoy eating and just
focus down on those uh for exercise find
the sport or the hobby where you it
doesn't feel like work to you like play
tennis or you know if you like running
then go run if you like lifting then go
lift if you like playing tennis then go
play tennis so I think uh the the beauty
of Modern Life is it gives us so many
options uh and that's not a bad thing
options are good uh it's just you have
to navigate your way through the options
and find out what works for you and then
commit to that and so on relationships I
don't view uh and I know this is uh
antithetical to the classical Indian way
of arranged marriage which had its
merits that was basically saying hey
let's find someone who's culturally
similar socioeconomically similar uh you
know worthy of you and the purpose of
marriage is to build a household and
have children so we'll take care of the
basics didn't always work but you know
pretty good hit rate compared to Modern
where it's just like I'm going to marry
my high school sweetheart or I'll roll
the dice or oh I got this girl pregnant
accidentally and then off we go so it
can work better than some models but in
a choice-based model which is where
Western Society is and I think
increasingly Eastern Society is there um
you have to be picky uh so if you're
having to sacrifice for your SP spouse
and they're not sacrificing in return
just go somewhere else if you're in
constant conflict then both of you need
to go find someone who's you're not each
of you is not going to be in constant
conflict with and I think that's a much
better recipe that that ability to
search and to look uh and to cut your
losses quickly uh because there's High
sunk cost in these relationships the the
biggest problem in relationships is
dishonesty where we're trying to make
the other person happy we're trying to
appear our best and so for the first
year of the relationship you just fake
it you just you're just a different
person and sometimes that's just your
emotions are driving you and you're in
love so you're being on your best
behavior without even thinking about it
and sometimes it's a little more
deliberate but the reality is the longer
you fake it the worse it's going to be
because then you get trapped and now
it's sunk cost and you don't want to
walk away and breaking that relationship
is hard and your friends and family
expect you together and you can't
imagine life separately uh and now
you're stuck uh so it's just better to
be brutally honest upfront about who you
are and your needs and your worst sides
and and all of that and don't try to
throw off any Impressions because if
eventually this person will see you at
your worst and eventually you will see
them at their worst um so you might as
well just start there you know from the
outside looking in I personally have
this impression of Naval rikan the brand
and the human and I feel like nothing
hurts that guy does anything hurt you at
all uh you know I'm a very paranoid
person uh so I do stress out about uh
you know um I I grew up with very little
so I'm always stressed stressing over
like like politicians and money you know
like the West has now come become very
fashionable to hate money to hate wealth
to hate entrepreneurs to try to tear
people down uh We've turned into cancel
culture right so yeah so you know those
kinds of things occasionally stress me
out um but I would say
that
um there's there's not anything I
want right need is the need is the
ultimate monkey other than knowledge
right I have not even that like what is
knowledge going to do for me I'm going
to die it's all going to go to zero
anyway so it's fun I enjoy learning
things I love the aha moment when I
connect something together and I would
tweak it a little bit I would say it's
understanding not knowledge knowledge is
because knowledge gets conflated with
memorization and you know memorizing
facts and I got chat GPT for that and
the internet um so I enjoy understanding
I enjoy learning
um my my own tweet to myself on this was
spend your life in the company of
geniuses sages children and books
right those are the four things that I
enjoy the most and there's a fifth thing
a great Indian
podcaster I thought you were going to
say you're wife or a woman uh she's
gonna she's gonna nail you on this one
um I I think uh not there was there was
an old thing a story that I was liked
about Socrates where they took him into
um they took him into the quent of the
mall the market and there were all these
luxuries and fineries and and things
laid out and and Delicacies to eat and
he
said there are so many things in this
world that I do not want and I was like
oh that's power that's that's it right
there right or when Alexander the Great
met diogenes uh who was living in a
barrel uh you know Alexander was like I
wish if I came back in their life that I
could be like diogenes and diynes said
something along the lines so well if I
came back I wouldn't want to be
Alexander right so being freed from need
is the ultimate but I'm not I'm not a
Buddha I'm not the guy who's going to
suddenly renounce everything and not
have a need uh and renunciation doesn't
work anyway uh but it's more that you
know I like games I think we all like
games we all play games we play the
social game we play the video games we
play the money games we play the fitness
game we play The Fame game we play the
love game we play the happiness game we
all play
games and I've played a lot of games my
whole life of every kind and I've won a
lot of games and the reason to win the
game is so you can be done with it so
you can see through it if you just keep
playing the same game over and over and
over grinding you know trying to go
higher and higher and higher maybe that
works for somebody it doesn't work for
me so I like to either see through games
or I like to be done with them so I used
to be an avid video gamer until very
recently actually this a couple of years
back maybe like five years ago I
probably spent more time playing video
games than I spent working did it do
anything for your mind it was fun uh
yeah probably I mean it was I was
playing harder than harder games and
more and more intellectual games and
strategy games and War games and
thinking games but they're just games
they're meaningless games right what was
your favorite there were so many I mean
mostly war games I was a I was a deep
war game magic the Gathering if you
remember that game you know so
anyway theic game doesn't matter the
point is I would just play lots and lots
of games and at some deep deep level I
knew they were worthless because you
know you're playing this game and then
you get some stupid reward at the end
and then they change the rules of that
game and then the game changes in like
your your reset or like you you forgot
your login or you lost it cuz you
upgraded your computer or your whatever
or this they rolled out version five
against a version four you're starting
all over right so you know it's
worthless you're just running in a
circle right and all games are worthless
because you die in the end but at least
some are longer live than others right
there are games that like for example if
I'm playing the wealth creation game I
can make money which has an actual
effect on my remaining life as opposed
to just playing a video game which has
none of that benefit
I'm not taking away from games games are
useful uh they're they're training for
the intellectual athlete just like
sports might be training for War for the
physical athlete um that
said I was still playing a lot of games
I knew they were kind of worthless I was
doing it to blow off steam or just
because I don't even need a reason I was
it was entertaining um but then one day
I read a blog post and uh you know truth
is that when you see it you can't unsee
it and this guy in just the right turn
of phrase he called games a shadow
career he said games are a shadow career
and I was like oh that's so good that is
so good it's like a career that you're
building that's fake you know it's a
shadow it's just going to disappear I
was like and and since that moment I
haven't been able to see games as
anything other than a waste of time so I
still do play games occasionally so once
in a blue moon mostly with my kid I'll
pick up a game I'll play for a little
bit but now I'm thoroughly in completely
aware that it is a quote unquote waste
of a time and if I'm okay wasting the
time it's fine but these days I'm not
really okay wasting time you still play
war games with your kid uh I'm going to
pick one or two up uh mostly these days
though they're on their iPads playing
their own games it's fine but what what
game would you have your kid play and I
asked this from the perspective of I
feel when I was growing up as a teenager
few games that really affected my
mindset in life FIFA uh like the
football game because it just teaches
you something about team play uh Age of
Empires obviously because you learn
strategy Sim City because you learn
Administration and Sims because you
learn about self
I mean look I I can argue for many of
them I can argue for The Sims and the
civilization type games I can argue for
board games war games uh strategy games
um the reality is even the few games I
play these days they're just like
runners or Jumpers or Fighters you know
they don't have any real meaning to them
it's fine
there's I think one of the one of my
tweets or analogies that went more viral
than others was like I really believe
that you should live your life like an
athlete or like a lion right which means
that most of your time you're resting
you're just fussing around uh you're
lazing around you're just doing whatever
you find entertaining and then once in a
while you get obsessed with something
and something is important and you just
pour everything into it so I would
rather be recharged and ready for my
next intellectual or physical Obsession
than putting myself on the grinder of I
have to wake up at this time then eat my
blueberries and then do my push-ups and
and just like live a regimented
mechanical life uh I want to live a very
free life I don't want a calendar I
don't want have to be in a specific
place at a specific time I don't want
have to answer to people um I just want
to be free and I think that's how you do
your best work and especially in an age
where we have so much leverage in the
system either through code or Media or
through other people or through Capital
the quality of your decision- making
dominates everything um Warren Buffett
is one of the richest men in the world
just because he makes a right decision
once a year and so having a clear mind
is way more important than anything else
which and this is all exuse for
laziness which just lets me relax and
relax and relax until I need to make
that decision but it's like even if I
look at my you know
um uh you know having made money in life
has happened through a bunch of
different sources but the number one was
like way bigger than the number two
through end put together two number two
was bigger than three through nend put
together three was bigger than four
through nend put together and that's
kind of how your entire life Works what
was number one if you don't mind me I'm
not going to get into it but it's uh but
it it's it the compound interest applies
in all intellectual and often even in
relationship domains uh so for example
your number one relationship in your
life eventually your kids currently your
wife maybe one of your parents is going
to be more valuable to you than kind of
all the rest put together right there so
maybe not so much in relationships but
definitely in definitely in uh learning
you know your best ideas is going to be
worth more than all the rest my best
Tweets the few best Tweets you know
you're only judging your best work not
your worst so in that sense being high
output is really good current generation
May judge you on your average but the
future what'll happen is let's say you
record I don't know how many podcasts
have you recorded 800 800 great so you
know by the time you're done you'll
probably have 2,000 or something before
you're finally like okay I'm bored of
this game right so let's say you have
2,000 podcasts in your life what's going
to happen is 20 of them are going to be
amazing okay and those will stand the
test of time and they'll slowly trickle
down trickle down trickle down 100 years
from now people will be watching 20 of
them and then 200 years from now 300
years from now they'll be watching one
of them right so it's you so in all of
these intellectual domains you are only
judged by your best work in posterity
which is not to say you can just
shortcut to it but most effort in life
in that sense is wasted but it's both
training wheels for the winning one plus
you just never know when or where the
right thing is going to emerge so you
kind of just have to keep moving um but
I I the thing I'm not a fan of is
wasting time wasting time you know
tedious meetings with tedious people uh
you know traveling to places for for
business where there's like you don't
actually enjoy it um anything ceremonial
or ritual meetings you know complete
with of time most meetings uh just save
your time save your energy um just be
happy enjoy yourself and be and be ready
for the opportunity because there there
a time when opportunity comes and if you
yourself are rested and ready and you
find yourself interested in it then you
have the space in your life and in your
mind that you can be sucked into it um
and again without any uh desire for a
specific outcome because when you desire
for a specific outcome you're moving
away from truth seeking because now
you're looking for something and if that
thing turns out not to be true you're
going to try and force it and we can't
help it we're Desiring creatures you
wouldn't even be here on this Earth if
you weren't a Desiring creature right
you just lie there in the dirt and let
worms eat you so you are a Desiring
creature but you just have to be careful
with your desires because they will take
you away from your truth because uh true
true reasoning is UN motivated it's or
it's motivated purely by curiosity
curiosity just means you want to know
the truth that's all it is so in that
sense curiosity is the pure Mo
motivation every other motivation is
motivated reasoning and leads you to is
more likely to lead you to an incorrect
answer and then the worst thing you can
do is get through motivated reasoning
get to the falsehood and then you bake
that into your identity you identify it
with yourself you say well because I'm a
Hindu or I'm a Christian or I believe
this or because I'm a Republican or
Democrat I believe this and then you get
locked into that now that is a part of
your understanding it's a shaky
foundation and then you start attaching
other things to that shaky Foundation
politics is a good example of this well
you know because I you know believe in
uh women's right for abortion now I also
have to believe that you know trans
women or men or men or women and I have
to believe that like you know there's no
heritability in certain things but there
is in other things I have to believe
that capitalism is evil you start
plugging all these things together that
don't actually belong together they're
voting coalitions they're coalitions of
Voters that have assemble single issue
voters but now all of a sudden you have
to adopt all of these beliefs or in
Christian you know if I'm Christian then
I have to believe this and this and this
otherwise I'm not a true Christian I
have to believe this and this Hindu sect
otherwise not a true Hindu all that is
nonsense one of the best lines I heard
on this was Buddha wasn't a Buddhist you
know so all the people that you admire
all the people that you look up to
they're they're not they don't strongly
self-identify with any movement you know
lean you created Singapore where we're
sitting today he didn't consider himself
Singaporean right he created that thing
so I think uh all of us are meant to not
okay not nobody's meant to do anything
but all of us function at our best when
we don't identify with anything outside
of
ourselves the one thing that this
conversation is teaching me is that uh
the universe is kind of wired to us
up a little
bit well it would have to be to be
interesting right if you could just if
it was predictable it' be boring there
be no point in being here is this the
most most unserious podcast that you've
ever done I don't
know probably maybe I don't know are you
comfortable being unserious sure yeah
I'm comfortable being me I mean I was so
intimidated by the thought of speaking
to you but once I got talking to you uh
I've just realized that you're like any
of us you've just done the right things
consistently and you've done the things
that you felt were easy but made a habit
out of a few other difficult things I
think if there's one thing that my
friends would say is that like I try to
figure everything out for myself I don't
listen to anybody else not even your
wife
nobody your kid nobody really yeah no
gurus no mentors no teachers no holy
this or that I mean I I definitely have
learned from people for sure I've almost
everything I know I've learned from
other people but I verified it for
myself is your work your Guru my work
work I don't
work you you know how you have that
saying about you choose something that
feels like play to you but work for
others oh yeah yeah yeah and I think
once you advance in that journey of play
it turns into art after a point and
that's how you look at all the products
that you invest in that they art for you
do they teach you things for life okay
whether it's in politics science
business spirituality whatever history
remembers the artists the artists are
the people who are creative and March to
their own beat and do their own thing um
great software is Art great business is
Art starting even like starting a new
country you know some level is Art
you're creating x n Hilo you're creating
something out of nothing um and uh that
to me is like the most rewarding thing
to be doing at any given time but art
can't be forced uh it can't in a sense
art is done for its own sake it's not
done for any external purpose if you're
doing it for money it's less you're
you're hurting it's uh it's cap ility to
be Arts not to say it can't still be
great art but you're just you're now
beholden to other interests it's like
motivated reasoning it's like true
scientists try to figure things out to
fulfill their desire to figure things
out right and the moment they figure it
out it's complete they don't need a
Nobel Prize or a Fields medal afterwards
and in fact some of the better ones have
rejected that or like uh famously Bob
Dylan I think rejected the pz or Prize
or whatever it was like he got some
massive prize didn't even show up didn't
even bother cuz he knows his music is
good he created for himself so I I do
think that is the highest calling
creating something for yourself because
you want to exist now nobody's perfect
we're not all going to get there um and
there's always going to be external
motivations but the less the more
internally motivated you can be the more
the thing itself is the reward um the
better the work you will do um and uh
the more F fulfilling it it is so that's
kind of what I aim for okay but maybe
that's just my excuse for being useless
these days okay
um you know again everyone views the
world with the lens that their own mind
has placed due to their own stories MH
so the lens I view the world with is
honestly pretty spiritual and I know you
don't like the word but again it's an
outcome of growing up in India in my
eyes um there's a concept of the flow
state state of flow where your best work
happens and I've always wondered to
myself about your Flow State nal's Flow
State and for me at least based on
what's visible to the public eye it
happens when you're TW eting when you're
in one of your speet storms and it
happens when someone's asking you the
right questions and unlocking things am
I right in like yeah I mean in a flow
State your mind isn't uh obsessing with
itself it's you're not thinking about
yourself you're focused on the thing
you're focused on the activity uh it's a
meditative State it's it's a state where
like for example if you're drawing or
painting then you are the brush you are
the paint you're only thinking about
that and there is no internal chatter
you're not saying oh man you know can't
wait for dinner or I can't believe my
wife said this to me that that's all
gone and that's and you're also
operating at the edge of your capability
so it's interesting enough that you you
are being stressed you're being strained
you know you're operating at the edge
but it's not so far forward that you are
being confused or you're like obviously
screwing up um so flow state is a
wonderful thing it's it's a very
meditative State
um but probably the the shortest way to
not be in a flow state is to try to be
in a flow state right because it's again
it's that effort right so it comes much
more from you find things that you like
to do and then when you and because you
like to do something you're interested
in it you're going to get good at it
you're going to be doing it and as
you're doing it you're climbing that
ladder of uh of Mastery and any you can
climb that ladder in literally anything
um as you get more and more into it um
you're going to be more and more in flow
uh I my problem is I switch around a lot
so I fall in love with something I
obsess over it I learn everything I
possibly can about it over a couple of
months kind of period and then once I
figure the basics out 8020 I start
getting bored and then when I start
getting bored I just sort of background
it I becomes a piece of my knowledge and
understanding and then I just move on to
the next thing or I just spend time
being bored until the next thing comes
along do you think that the Flow State
sometimes allows you to channelize
knowledge
that's present
externally I don't know what I'm going
to say until I say it so it's kind of
funny that one of the ways that I learn
what I think is by saying it and the
same way one of the ways that I learn
what I know is by tweeting it so very
often I'll just be talking with a friend
I'll be hanging out I'll be having
dinner or I'll be sitting at home by
myself late at night and I'll just have
a thought and I'll come into my mind
almost fully baked and I'm like oh I
should tweet that and then I'll tweet it
and then sometimes I have a second
thought I better changed this and
usually the first version is always the
best uh I don't know where it comes from
it's kind of interesting it comes from
Beyond whatever that means right maybe
it comes from the depths of my mind
maybe comes from somewhere else but they
come to me fully formed which is kind of
the entertaining thing I mean I'm of the
belief that it comes from somewhere
else creativity is a mysterious Force
right yeah I don't know I mean that's
again I keep bringing this up man but
when I'm talking to you I feel like I'm
talking to Rishi you know Rishi is so uh
kind of embarrassing sorry
but that's that's what it feels like so
you know on a very Primal level the
podcast for me is based on my childhood
dream of wanting to explore the
Himalayas and have conversations with
sages and I'm just like making money off
of it right now spend your life in the
company of geniuses sages children and
books right yeah but again this is one
of those things that figured through the
show whenever I speak to monks they keep
talking about the Flow State how it is
meditative it is a form of working your
mind towards Evolution but one needs to
be humble with in the Flow State and
understand that it's not their own
thoughts and creativity but it's being
placed in their head externally by the
yeah in a real Flow State you're not
thinking about yourself so it's not
coming from this look when when we self
is a very loaded word right it's another
one of the self it's another one of
these words that can mean a lot of
different things
but there's kind of the separate self
the identity the story The Character the
name the uh kind of the the emotional
predilections toward doing certain
certain things and not doing others the
reactions the memories that's the false
self okay we know that from Hinduism and
Buddhism and Hindu mythology and they've
written it down much better than I could
ever say um that's the false self but
yet that's the self that we function
under 95% of the time and when we go
into a flow state that self quiets down
for a bit and then All That Remains is
true self which is
just I don't have a name for it maybe
you have name for it it's just the thing
that is right it's existence itself it's
Consciousness it's awareness to me
they're identical right as an aside one
of the I think I think there's a lot of
great questions out there that people
just don't ask because they're so
cliched right so uh one of the questions
I love is like if a tree falls in the
forest and there's no one around to hear
it doesn't make a sound so cliche I
think about that one all the time you
know because it really asks a question
like you know is existence and are
existence and Consciousness the same
thing like in what sense can something
be said to exist if nothing is ever
conscious of it or its or its effects um
another one that I like to think about
is the philosophical zombie problem
which is uh you know why do we even need
Consciousness why couldn't you just be
walking around reacting like an
automaton to everything and I could see
the exact same reactions the exact same
emotions and whatever but you just don't
need to be conscious why why why does
that why aren't we all just uh philosop
why aren't we all just zombies um and
actually it's funny because the Buddhist
answer to that is if you think it
through it's kind of it's not why
Consciousness the answer is why zombie
like does the zombie actually exist or
is that just a figment of the you know
awareness's imagination um another one
that I like is uh you know some of the
wisdom that's really old is so embedded
in culture we don't think about it uh
row row row your boat you know that one
row row row your boat gently down the
stream yeah it's so smart nobody thinks
about it nobody talks it's so smart
that's that's like one of the greatest
works of art ever created row row row
your boat in other words your work right
the analogy is you're sitting in a boat
you're kind of by yourself yeah there
might be other boats but you're kind of
by yourself you're rowing you got to row
you got to do some work gently down the
stream gently yeah you don't struggle
too much you know you kind of have to
figure out what you can navigate without
getting all stressed out down the stream
it's a good analogy for Life the river
you know it's going off you know it's
going to die at the end um merrily
merrily merily merily yeah that's that's
the right attitude life is but a dream
that's the cold hard truth life is but a
dream it appears it disappears it ends
Infinity on both sides right there's so
much wisdom in that little poem and
stuck around forever but instead we have
to go looking at complicated books to
figure this out as I've learned through
the show they say that the curse of
human life is that once you die you
realize that human life was the
dream yeah I mean nobody knows what
happens when you die right that's kind
of the mystery that makes it all fun um
but you know to your point about being
attracted to like Indian
uh sort of ideals and memories I I have
found as I grow older I gravitate more
and more towards those things like um do
you mind that I'm bringing it up so much
in this conv no no it's fine it's fine
anything is fine it's just a part of my
identity yeah it's fine I mean I'm
Indian too by origin and probably will
end up back there at some point when I'm
old enough you know I think about it I I
like India I love India these are these
are these are my brothers and sisters
right these are my people I am I am one
of them so there's a couple of places I
would love to take you to in India I
told you about one of them in the car uh
which is the mountains like Himalayas
there too many Secrets like that's where
you actually find the wisdom of the
sages and you feel it in the air the
other place is Banaras Varanasi yeah
which is in according to sanatan it's
the oldest city in the world and you do
feel that it is chaotic but there's
another part of it that's extremely
quiet there's a part of Banaras called
the manikarnika G mhm where they
perpetually burn bodies for the sake of
cremation MH mhm they say that when you
stand at the manikara and you view the
bodies burning whatever is inside you
FRS up and comes on to the outside and
that's where something inside you shifts
so for me I just became very curious and
I became more serious about this journey
of podcasting I realized that this is my
true iy guy um Japanese concept for the
sake of curiosity because you come uh
face to face with death you see human
body's burning you know if if you
actually view a human body burning at
some point the skull
explodes so when you see that happening
in front of you it shifts something
inside and I Feel Again India is
definitely not for everyone but it is
for Seekers I mean if you could keep
your death in front of you at all times
you would live a magical life then you
would value the exact moment at it's you
know as being the complete and wholesome
and only real sacred thing that exist
do you keep it death in front of you I
try to it's not it doesn't always work
but I do it's
probably it's probably the most
liberating thing that I do it's not I
don't do it as an exercise I just but it
is on my mind a lot what's an ideal
death for
you it doesn't matter hopefully not
slowly or painfully but you know it's
it's when it when it's gone it's gone I
guess the ideal would be it would be
good to be to have uh self-realized
before for that you know ultimate
truth be good I don't know if there's
such a thing that's that's Enlightenment
is not something you
necessarily from what I can tell it's
not something you necessarily find or
create it's more just unlearning it's a
shedding it's what remains when
everything else is gone so it's it is a
mini death of its own sort it is a death
of the separate self in the mind um and
I'm not looking for that kind of death
but I would say I'm looking for truth
and if that's true then I'll take the
truth I'll take the truth TR I'll take
an unhappy truth over a lie any day and
I don't think it's an unhappy truth
anyway but it doesn't matter I'm I'm
open to whatever the truth is if the
truth is oh I'm just a brain and a vat
this is a simulation and someone's pting
and poking at me and they're going to
torture me for eternity fine show me the
truth I'd rather know the truth you know
in The Joe Rogan episode you spoke about
how uh you used to meditate yeah and you
would just view your own thoughts You'
sit in a place and just view your own
thoughts and through that process
sometimes you read Stillness but you
also had some psychedelic experiences do
you ever think about
those I kind of got bored of it um and
and I and I just I don't think
experiences are are the thing did the
distractions yes any experience that
comes will also go uh the the thing that
matters is what your state of mind is
you know at 2:30 p.m. in the afternoon
when you're sitting by yourself how do
you feel are you are you peaceful are
you happy are you good you know 2:37
p.m. you're walking down the street are
you okay how do you feel are you good
that's what matters Ms right it's the
exact moment in time what is your
internal State what is your external
State um you know what are the thoughts
that are going through your head if any
that's what matters so I don't want
Bliss for an hour a day uh that's just
another experience that comes and goes I
want I want something that's
indestructible did you ever smoke
weed uh you know I live in
California when you were younger no no
know luckily that's the kind of thing
that if I discovered in my youth I don't
think I would have had a very productive
youth because you get too into it yeah
it's it's it's it's too easy to turn off
your brain I think things like weed uh
you know the the West is going through a
very hedonistic phase where it's all
about being single and partying and
doing drugs and um those are hard things
to resist they can really destroy your
sense of self-being uh I've definitely
seen people who have done way too many
even like say for example common belief
now is that like mushrooms are harmless
right they're not I mean you do enough
of that stuff it'll break your brain
you'll end up believing too many things
that aren't real um you know same thing
with weed it'll rob you of ambition
because it's it's a very feminizing drug
it's a plant estrogen so you're just
going to sit there all day and smoke
weed and you're not going to go do
anything with your life so yes there are
definitely things that I have tried but
luckily I would say I'm I I'm not
getting sucked into any of them fair I
mean even water in excess is bad sure
alth that one we're pretty well evolved
for right it's just like for example if
you just from an evolutionary past if
You' had access to like easy weed all
the time you would have gotten eaten by
something right you wouldn't have made
it very far um it's just in modern
society yeah we can do that modern
society is really weird where we we've
we've changed our physical environment
much faster than we're adapted for so we
do need all kinds of coping mechanisms
right for example we're all overfed
we're UND ex exercised uh we're
overstimulated uh our minds are worrying
about far away things right the media
the purpose of the media as I've joked
before is to make every problem your
problem right you go on you go on social
media and it's just all dueling meme
viruses each one trying to occupy a slot
in your brain to Make You Care well you
know thousand years ago someone could
have gotten shot or blown up in some Far
Away country you would have never heard
about it you had no stake in it you had
no way of knowing about it now it's just
your brain is not man is not designed to
handle all the world's emergencies in
real time as they break it's breaking
your brain at some deep level you're not
even meant to see violence or
pornography like those are very weird
and rare and unique new things uh and so
the modern struggle is to navigate
through the fruits of
abundance uh that are wrecking you right
it's actually the
the the challenge of modernity is
avoiding the fruits of modernity right
for you have to become almost a yogi in
self-defense uh to protect yourself it's
called ver in in our culture and it
means being in the middle of a party
yeah and seeing everyone party around
you and being happy for them but not
taking part in the party yourself other
than just keeping your mind there yeah
this is why I'm finding it harder and
harder to go to
parties because it's hard not to get
involved and to indulge but it's so
meaningless it's just another game right
uh and they're fun and occasionally I do
go to parties and I do like a good party
and you have a higher odds of dragging
me out to good party than to like some
tedious meeting um but all that said
like Even parties have kind of lost
their
luster what's Nal R can't like when he's
drunk or
high uh same but more talkative more
talkative more talkative yeah because
you're inherently a bit of an introvert
yes yeah got yeah on a podcast I'm not
but uh left to my own devices I'm very
much an inter I would much rather read
or be on the Internet or just be walking
around thinking
or you know listening to YouTube or a
podcast or something than uh hanging out
with people do you miss your
childhood
no but I don't really think about it I
don't think about the past much
consciously yeah they when you're asking
me the question I'm being forced to
think about it for the first time in a
long time my bad no no there's nothing
wrong with it I'm just saying I don't
think about it so I don't I don't have a
I don't have a predigested answer for
you that's great yeah no but I would say
no I don't miss my childhood I don't
it's it's like a dream is it real did it
actually
happen wow there's a quote that goes
like the past is fiction it is fiction
the P the past is uh it it is a
narrative you don't remember most of it
the little bit that you do remember is
very selective memory stitched into a
narrative uh there's no point in really
remembering it uh presumably there are
lessons to learn but you probably
already digested those and learned them
you don't even have to think about those
uh so what's the
point um do you think about about the
future at
all uh I think about the future for
practical things career stuff well like
yeah if I have to make money or an
investment or if I have to like figure
out what to do with the this child and
this problem and solve that or you know
where do I want to have dinner so yeah
and that sense we are future planners
but uh I don't I don't think too far
ahead I don't I don't obsess over it but
I'm more of a future creature than a
past creature for sure uh in an ideal
world I wouldn't think that much about
the future either but I'm not there I
think we're forced to in order you have
to I mean you're you're a functioning
creature that has to navigate the world
but I I I I want to think about the
future as regards to utilitarian things
you know food money uh you know those
kinds of things problem solving I don't
want to think about the future in sense
of what does it hold for me like am I
going to be happy am I going to be uh in
a good relationship you know am I going
to die like the death thing is
interesting to think about you kind of
can't look away it's like the most
important thing that's going to happen
to you right so you have to think about
it but uh I I don't want to think about
I don't want to self-
obsess in the future the reason I don't
self- obsess anymore or never even got
that into it is because I just found it
both a waste of time uh as well as it
was just destroying my
happiness happiness is a big word so
more peace intruding on my peace gotcha
I think we're almost at the end of the
episode episode what advice do you have
for me I don't have advice for you I
mean you you must have gotten to know
something about me at this point or
maybe I'll ask you the career advice
aspect because I could reframe this
question as how do you view the world of
content creators going into the future I
would okay I'll give you some advice I
like I like being provocative so uh I
would say be selfish be more selfish uh
make sure you really enjoy your work
make sure you really are only working
with the people that you really like
doing like working with uh make sure you
are only have the guests on that you're
proud to have on that you genuinely want
to have conversations with um because I
I think the the value you've already
built something of incredible value and
it's going to continue compounding so
the value now is about the longevity how
long can you keep it going whether you
go to episode a th000 or 2,000 or 5,000
matters more than uh you know you don't
want to be in grinder mode if you're
just grinding you're going to burn out
and the day you or not this thing is
over so I would say just make sure you
enjoy yourself and uh so that's part of
it uh so be selfish and make sure you
enjoy yourself and then the second part
of being selfish is talk to people where
you genuinely want to talk to them don't
don't just record a podcast or record a
podcast because you know you have to
make certain amount of money or you got
to check a box because you will be
judged at the end of the day by your
best work not by any by your average all
my content that is out there that people
like I didn't do it for them I didn't do
it for anything I didn't do it for
anyone I just did it for me and it was
deeply selfish it was just notes to self
and there's nothing wrong with that
because we're all the same inside so if
you if you're creating art then you do
it for its own sake you do it because
you enjoy it and then other people will
see the same thing that you saw in it um
and they'll get value out of it so I say
just be selfish and you can sustain it
okay now I will uh you know take the
layers off I'll take the filters off and
tell you that this was one of the
biggest days of my podcasting career man
you're very nice um you have helped me
so much from a professional perspective
being on the other side of the world and
just speaking on other podcasts and
there's so many people like me who just
sit in different parts of this globe and
consume pieces of Your Mind through
Twitter through the stuff you say on
podcast and I know you're very
nonchalant about it like you're just
enjoying it but you're adding so much
value to our lives and so many of us
have daddy issues and mommy issues and I
think Nal ravikant has become kind of a
big brother figure to people all over
the globe and to just be able to share
screen space with you is one of the
biggest honors of my life yeah at the
same time the worst thing I could do for
myself is is get into the idea of having
a fan base because uh Fame is a beast
it'll lead you alive and I don't want to
do anything for other people I don't
care about if they respect me or not
disrespect all day long who cares sh I
mean I hear you uh and you know just
observing you go about how you handle F
we were together at an event right now
it it's taught me a lot uh just sharing
I don't think I handle it well you know
I get approached by a lot of people they
want to take a photo it always kind of
weirds me out a little bit uh no it's
just it'd be better not to be famous to
be honest if I had to do it over again
it might be better to be
anonymous thank God you're not
Anonymous but Nal genuinely from the
bottom of my heart I bow down to you no
don't bows please that's embarrassing PE
relationships only I I hear you but no
bows no gurus anybody calls me you want
to not be my friend call me a guru not
going to be friends I I don't think
you're a guru but you are a bit of a b
you know what bayya means brother yeah
big brother yeah so that's what I look
at you as and that's how a lot of brown
people look at you as we're all brothers
that works there's some people who just
emit that Sensei energy and it's not
their will again it's the universe
working through you that's how I look at
you so thank you for everything you've
given all of us you're guiding a lot of
young people and you're helping everyone
with the mental and spiritual health
without knowing it thank you you're very
kind as are you 800 episodes and you're
obviously seeking bigger and bigger
truths so you're on a good path thank
you thank Youk you uh I hope we get to
speak again in life and I hope you had a
very nice time to me thank you I did
thanks for having me that was the
episode uh was not easy to make this
particular episode happen I had to to
fly to Singapore which is a 5-hour
flight away from Mumbai of course Nal
flew from halfway across the world uh
our common friend Balaji told me uh that
there is this opportunity and nal's
agreed to do this particular episode so
this was the first ever episode we shot
on foreign soil in my eyes it's the
first International episode on TRS even
though we've shot one with Arnold
schweger in Korea we've shot an episode
with Ronnie Coleman in India we've shot
episode with Braun strowman in India
countless foreign cricketers but I truly
feel like my International phase of this
podcasting Journey Begins with this very
important and very iconic episode of the
ranir show couldn't sleep on the night
of this episode because this was a very
important life moment for me it's
something I've visualized for a very
long time before we executed upon this
podcast uh dream come true for anyone
who's been listening to podcasts for the
last decade
we all know what a big deal naal
ravikant is I'm just glad I got to do
this very easygoing conversation with
him and I hope that he returns on the
renv show at some point in the future I
will be attaching all his social handles
down below so for those of you who are
being introduced to him for the first
time please go follow Nel ravikant on
every social media platform I also urge
you to pick up Snippets from this
conversation and turn them into reels
and shots for social media thank you for
listening in DRS and the whole team
we'll be back very very soon
[Music]